Jeremiah

36 Now it came about in the fourth year of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, that this word occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “Take for yourself a roll of a book, and you must write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and against Judah and against all the nations, since the day that I spoke to you, since the days of Jo·si′ah, clear down to this day. 3 Perhaps those of the house of Judah will listen to all the calamity that I am thinking of doing to them, to the end that they may return, each one from his bad way, and that I may actually forgive their error and their sin.”

4 And Jeremiah proceeded to call Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah that Bar′uch might write at the mouth of Jeremiah all the words of Jehovah that He had spoken to him, on the roll of the book. 5 Then Jeremiah commanded Bar′uch, saying: “I am shut up. I am unable to enter into the house of Jehovah. 6 And you yourself must enter in and read aloud from the roll that you have written at my mouth the words of Jehovah in the ears of the people at the house of Jehovah in the day of fast; and also in the ears of all Judah who are coming in from their cities you should read them aloud. 7 Perhaps their request for favor will fall before Jehovah and they will return, each one from his bad way, for great is the anger and the rage that Jehovah has spoken against this people.”

8 And Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah proceeded to do according to all that Jeremiah the prophet had commanded him, to read aloud from the book the words of Jehovah at the house of Jehovah.

9 Now it came about in the fifth year of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, in the ninth month, that all the people in Jerusalem and all the people that were coming in from the cities of Judah into Jerusalem proclaimed a fast before Jehovah. 10 And Bar′uch began to read aloud from the book the words of Jeremiah at the house of Jehovah, in the dining room of Gem·a·ri′ah the son of Sha′phan the copyist, in the upper courtyard, at the entrance of the new gate of the house of Jehovah, in the ears of all the people.

11 And Mi·cai′ah the son of Gem·a·ri′ah the son of Sha′phan got to hear all the words of Jehovah from out of the book. 12 At that he went down to the house of the king, to the dining room of the secretary, and, look! there is where all the princes were sitting, E·lish′a·ma the secretary and De·la′iah the son of She·mai′ah and El·na′than the son of Ach′bor and Gem·a·ri′ah the son of Sha′phan and Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Han·a·ni′ah and all the other princes. 13 And Mi·cai′ah proceeded to tell them all the words that he had heard when Bar′uch read aloud from the book in the ears of the people.

14 Then all the princes sent out to Bar′uch Je·hu′di the son of Neth·a·ni′ah the son of Shel·e·mi′ah the son of Cush′i, saying: “The roll from which you read aloud in the ears of the people—take it in your hand and come.” Accordingly Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah took the roll in his hand and came in to them. 15 Then they said to him: “Sit down, please, and read it aloud in our ears.” So Bar′uch read aloud in their ears.

16 Now it came about that as soon as they heard all the words, they looked at one another in dread; and they proceeded to say to Bar′uch: “We shall without fail tell the king all these words.” 17 And Bar′uch they asked, saying: “Tell us, please, How did you write all these words from his mouth?” 18 Then Bar′uch said to them: “Out of his mouth he kept declaring to me all these words, and I was writing in the book with ink.” 19 Finally the princes said to Bar′uch: “Go, conceal yourself, you and Jeremiah, so that no one at all will know where YOU men are.”

20 Then they came in to the king, to the courtyard, and the roll they entrusted to the dining room of E·lish′a·ma the secretary; and they began to tell all the words in the ears of the king.

21 So the king sent Je·hu′di out to get the roll. Accordingly he got it out of the dining room of E·lish′a·ma the secretary. And Je·hu′di began to read it aloud in the ears of the king and in the ears of all the princes standing by the king. 22 And the king was sitting in the winter house, in the ninth month, with a brazier burning before him. 23 Then it came about that as soon as Je·hu′di had read three or four page-columns, he proceeded to tear it apart with the secretary’s knife, pitching it also into the fire that was in the brazier until all the roll ended up in the fire that was in the brazier. 24 And they felt no dread; neither did the king and all his servants, who were listening to all these words, rip their garments apart. 25 And even El·na′than and De·la′iah and Gem·a·ri′ah themselves pleaded with the king not to burn the roll, but he did not listen to them. 26 Further, the king commanded Je·rah′me·el the son of the king and Se·rai′ah the son of Az′ri·el and Shel·e·mi′ah the son of Ab′de·el to get Bar′uch the secretary and Jeremiah the prophet. But Jehovah kept them concealed.

27 And the word of Jehovah occurred further to Jeremiah after the king had burned up the roll with the words that Bar′uch had written at the mouth of Jeremiah, saying: 28 “Take again for yourself a roll, another one, and write on it all the first words that proved to be on the first roll, which Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah burned up. 29 And against Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah you should say, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “You yourself have burned up this roll, saying, ‘Why is it that you have written on it, saying: “The king of Babylon will come without fail and will certainly bring this land to ruin and cause man and beast to cease from it”?’ 30 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said against Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah, ‘He will come to have no one sitting upon the throne of David, and his own dead body will become something thrown out to the heat by day and to the frost by night. 31 And I will call to account against him and against his offspring and against his servants their error, and I will bring upon them and upon the inhabitants of Jerusalem and upon the men of Judah all the calamity that I have spoken against them, and they did not listen.’”’”

32 And Jeremiah himself took another roll and then gave it to Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah, the secretary, who proceeded to write upon it at the mouth of Jeremiah all the words of the book that Je·hoi′a·kim the king of Judah had burned in the fire; and there were added to them many more words like those.

Jeremiah

38 And Sheph·a·ti′ah the son of Mat′tan and Ged·a·li′ah the son of Pash′hur and Ju′cal the son of Shel·e·mi′ah and Pash′hur the son of Mal·chi′jah got to hear the words that Jeremiah was speaking to all the people, saying: 2 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘The one continuing to dwell in this city is the one that will die by the sword, by the famine and by the pestilence. But the one going out to the Chal·de′ans is the one that will keep living and that will certainly come to have his soul as a spoil and alive.’ 3 This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Without fail this city will be given into the hand of the military force of the king of Babylon, and he will certainly capture it.’”

4 And the princes began to say to the king: “Let this man, please, be put to death, for that is how he is weakening the hands of the men of war who are left remaining in this city and the hands of all the people, by speaking to them according to these words. For this man is one seeking not for the peace of this people but for calamity.” 5 So King Zed·e·ki′ah said: “Look! He is in YOUR hands. For there is nothing at all in which the king himself can prevail against YOU.”

6 And they proceeded to take Jeremiah and throw him into the cistern of Mal·chi′jah the son of the king, which was in the Courtyard of the Guard. So they let Jeremiah down by means of ropes. Now in the cistern there was no water, but mire; and Jeremiah began to sink down into the mire.

7 And E′bed-mel′ech the E·thi·o′pi·an, a man who was a eunuch and who was in the house of the king, got to hear that they had put Jeremiah into the cistern; and the king was sitting in the Gate of Benjamin. 8 So E′bed-mel′ech went out of the house of the king and spoke to the king, saying: 9 “O my lord the king, these men have done bad in all that they have done to Jeremiah the prophet, whom they have thrown into the cistern, so that he will die where he is because of the famine. For there is no bread anymore in the city.”

10 Then the king commanded E′bed-mel′ech the E·thi·o′pi·an, saying: “Take in your charge from this place thirty men, and you must get Jeremiah the prophet up out of the cistern before he dies.” 11 Accordingly E′bed-mel′ech took the men in his charge and went into the house of the king to beneath the treasury and took from there worn-out rags and worn-out pieces of cloth and let them down to Jeremiah into the cistern by means of the ropes. 12 Then E′bed-mel′ech the E·thi·o′pi·an said to Jeremiah: “Put, please, the worn-out rags and the pieces of cloth under your armpits beneath the ropes.” Jeremiah now did so. 13 Finally they drew out Jeremiah by means of the ropes and brought him up out of the cistern. And Jeremiah continued to dwell in the Courtyard of the Guard.

14 And King Zed·e·ki′ah proceeded to send and take Jeremiah the prophet to him to the third entryway, which is in the house of Jehovah, and then the king said to Jeremiah: “I am asking something of you. Do not hide from me anything.” 15 At this Jeremiah said to Zed·e·ki′ah: “In case I should tell you, will you not without fail put me to death? And in case I advise you, you will not listen to me.” 16 At that King Zed·e·ki′ah swore to Jeremiah in the place of concealment, saying: “As Jehovah is alive, who has made for us this soul, I will not put you to death, and I will not give you into the hand of these men who are seeking for your soul.”

17 Jeremiah now said to Zed·e·ki′ah: “This is what Jehovah, the God of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘If you will without fail go out to the princes of the king of Babylon, your soul will also certainly keep living and this city itself will not be burned with fire, and you yourself and your household will certainly keep living. 18 But if you will not go out to the princes of the king of Babylon, this city must also be given into the hand of the Chal·de′ans, and they will actually burn it with fire, and you yourself will not escape out of their hand.’”

19 Then King Zed·e·ki′ah said to Jeremiah: “I am in fright of the Jews that have fallen away to the Chal·de′ans, for fear that they might give me into their hand and they might actually deal abusively with me.” 20 But Jeremiah said: “They will do no such giving. Obey, please, the voice of Jehovah in what I am speaking to you, and it will go well with you, and your soul will continue to live. 21 But if you are refusing to go out, this is the thing that Jehovah has caused me to see: 22 And, look! all the women that have been left remaining in the house of the king of Judah are being brought out to the princes of the king of Babylon, and they are saying,

‘The men at peace with you have allured you and prevailed over you.

They have caused your foot to sink down into the very ooze; they have retreated in the opposite direction.’

23 And all your wives and your sons they are bringing out to the Chal·de′ans, and you yourself will not escape out of their hand, but by the hand of the king of Babylon you will be seized, and because of you this city will be burned with fire.”

24 And Zed·e·ki′ah proceeded to say to Jeremiah: “May no man at all get to know about these things, so that you do not die. 25 And in case the princes hear that I have spoken with you and they actually come in to you and say to you, ‘Do tell us, please, What did you speak about to the king? Do not hide anything from us, and we shall not put you to death. And what did the king speak about to you?’ 26 you must also say to them, ‘I was letting my request for favor fall before the king, that he should not send me back to the house of Je·hon′a·than to die there.’”

27 In time all the princes came in to Jeremiah and began questioning him. In turn, he told them according to all these words that the king had commanded. So they became silent before him, for the matter was not heard. 28 And Jeremiah continued to dwell in the Courtyard of the Guard until the day that Jerusalem was captured. And it occurred just when Jerusalem was captured.

Jeremiah

39 In the ninth year of Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, in the tenth month, Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon and all his military force came to Jerusalem and began to lay siege to it.

2 In the eleventh year of Zed·e·ki′ah, in the fourth month, on the ninth day of the month, the city was broken through. 3 And all the princes of the king of Babylon proceeded to come in and sit down in the Middle Gate, namely, Ner′gal-shar·e′zer, Sam′gar-ne′bo, Sar′se·chim, Rab′sa·ris, Ner′gal-shar·e′zer the Rab′mag and all the rest of the princes of the king of Babylon.

4 Now it came about that as soon as Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and all the men of war saw them, they began to run away and to go out by night from the city by the way of the garden of the king, by the gate between the double wall; and they kept going out by the way of the Ar′a·bah. 5 And a military force of the Chal·de′ans went chasing after them, and they got to overtake Zed·e·ki′ah in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho. Then they took him and brought him up to Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math that he might pronounce upon him judicial decisions. 6 And the king of Babylon proceeded to slaughter the sons of Zed·e·ki′ah in Rib′lah before his eyes, and all the nobles of Judah the king of Babylon slaughtered. 7 And the eyes of Zed·e·ki′ah he blinded, after which he bound him with copper fetters, in order to bring him to Babylon.

8 And the house of the king and the houses of the people the Chal·de′ans burned with fire, and the walls of Jerusalem they pulled down. 9 And the rest of the people who were left remaining in the city, and the deserters that had fallen away to him, and the rest of the people who were left remaining Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard took into exile to Babylon.

10 And some of the people, the lowly ones who had nothing at all, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard let remain in the land of Judah; and he went on to give them vineyards and compulsory services on that day.

11 Furthermore, Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon gave command concerning Jeremiah by means of Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard, saying: 12 “Take him and keep your own eyes set upon him, and do not do to him anything bad at all. But just as he may speak to you, so do with him.”

13 Accordingly Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard and Neb·u·shaz′ban the Rab′sa·ris, and Ner′gal-shar·e′zer the Rab′mag and all the principal men of the king of Babylon sent; 14 they even proceeded to send and take Jeremiah out of the Courtyard of the Guard and give him over to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan, in order to bring him forth to his house, that he might dwell in the midst of the people.

15 And to Jeremiah the word of Jehovah occurred while he happened to be shut up in the Courtyard of the Guard, saying: 16 “Go, and you must say to E′bed-mel′ech the E·thi·o′pi·an, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “Here I am bringing true my words upon this city for calamity and not for good, and they will certainly happen before you in that day.”’

17 “‘And I will deliver you in that day,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and you will not be given into the hand of the men of whom you yourself are scared.’

18 “‘For I shall without fail furnish you an escape, and by the sword you will not fall; and you will certainly come to have your soul as a spoil, because you have trusted in me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

Jeremiah

40 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah after Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard sent him from Ra′mah, when he took him while he was bound with handcuffs in the midst of all the exiles of Jerusalem and of Judah, who were being taken into exile in Babylon. 2 Then the chief of the bodyguard took Jeremiah and said to him: “Jehovah your God himself spoke this calamity against this place, 3 that Jehovah might bring it true and do just as he has spoken, because YOU people have sinned against Jehovah and have not obeyed his voice. And this thing has happened to YOU. 4 And now, look! I have let you loose today from the handcuffs that were upon your hands. If it is good in your eyes to come with me to Babylon, come, and I shall keep my eye upon you. But if it is bad in your eyes to come with me to Babylon, refrain. See! The entire land is before you. To wherever it is good and right in your eyes to go, go there.”

5 And he was yet not one that would return, when Neb·u′zar·ad′an said: “Do return to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan, whom the king of Babylon has commissioned over the cities of Judah, and dwell with him in the midst of the people; or to wherever it is right in your eyes to go, go.”

And the chief of the bodyguard then gave him a food allowance and a present and let him go. 6 Accordingly Jeremiah came to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam at Miz′pah and took up dwelling with him in the midst of the people who were left remaining in the land.

7 In time all the chiefs of the military forces who were in the field, they and their men, got to hear that the king of Babylon had commissioned Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam over the land and that he had commissioned him over the men and women and little children and some of the lowly people of the land, who had not been taken into exile in Babylon. 8 So they came to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah, even Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and Jo·ha′nan and Jon′a·than, the sons of Ka·re′ah, and Se·rai′ah the son of Tan·hu′meth and the sons of E′phai the Ne·toph′a·thite and Jez·a·ni′ah the son of the Ma·ac′a·thite, they and their men. 9 And Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan proceeded to swear to them and to their men, saying: “Do not be afraid of serving the Chal·de′ans. Continue dwelling in the land and serve the king of Babylon, and it will go well with YOU. 10 And as for me, here I am dwelling in Miz′pah, in order to stand before the Chal·de′ans who will come to us. And as for YOU yourselves, gather wine and summer fruits and oil and put them in YOUR vessels and dwell in YOUR cities that YOU have seized.”

11 And all the Jews that were in Mo′ab and among the sons of Am′mon and in E′dom and those who were in all the other lands, they also heard that the king of Babylon had given a remnant to Judah and that he had commissioned over them Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan. 12 And all the Jews began to return from all the places to which they had been dispersed, and they kept coming into the land of Judah to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah. And they went gathering wine and summer fruits in very great quantity.

13 As for Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces who were in the field, they came to Ged·a·li′ah at Miz′pah. 14 And they proceeded to say to him: “Do you not at all know that Ba′a·lis, the king of the sons of Am′mon, himself has sent Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah to strike you to the soul?” But Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam did not believe them.

15 And Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah himself said to Ged·a·li′ah, in a place of concealment in Miz′pah: “I want to go, now, and strike down Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, as no one at all will know. Why should he strike you to the soul, and why must all those of Judah who are being collected together to you be scattered and the remnant of Judah perish?” 16 But Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam said to Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah: “Do not do this thing, for it is a falsehood that you are speaking concerning Ish′ma·el.”

Jeremiah

47 This is what proved to be the word of Jehovah to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the Phi·lis′tines before Phar′aoh proceeded to strike down Ga′za. 2 This is what Jehovah has said:

“Look! Waters are coming up from the north and have become a flooding torrent. And they will flood the land and what fills it, the city and those inhabiting it. And the men will certainly cry out, and everyone dwelling in the land must howl. 3 At the sound of the stamping of the hoofs of his stallions, at the rattling of his war chariots, the turmoil of his wheels, the fathers will actually not turn around to the sons, because of the dropping down of their hands, 4 on account of the day that is coming to despoil all the Phi·lis′tines, to cut off from Tyre and from Si′don every survivor that was helping. For Jehovah is despoiling the Phi·lis′tines, who are the remaining ones from the island of Caph′tor. 5 Baldness must come to Ga′za. Ash′ke·lon has been put to silence. O remnant of their low plain, how long will you keep making cuts upon yourself?

6 “Aha, the sword of Jehovah! How long will you not stay quiet? Be shoved into your sheath. Take your repose and keep silent.

7 “How can it stay quiet, when Jehovah himself has given a command to it? It is for Ash′ke·lon and for the coast of the sea. There is where he has designated it to be.”

Jeremiah

48 For Mo′ab this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “Woe to Ne′bo, for she has been despoiled! Kir·i·a·tha′im has been put to shame, has been captured. The secure height has been put to shame and been put in terror. 2 No more is there any praise of Mo′ab. In Hesh′bon they have thought out against her a calamity: ‘Come, men, and let us cut her off from being a nation.’

“You, too, O Mad′men, should keep silent. After you there walks a sword. 3 There is the sound of an outcry from Hor·o·na′im, a despoiling and great breaking down. 4 Mo′ab has been broken down. Her little ones have caused a cry to be heard. 5 For on the way up to Lu′hith it is with weeping that one goes up—there is a weeping. For on the way down from Hor·o·na′im there is a distressing outcry over the breakdown that people have heard.

6 “Take to flight; provide escape for YOUR souls, and YOU should become like a juniper tree in the wilderness. 7 Because your trust is in your works and in your treasures, you yourself will also be captured. And Che′mosh will certainly go forth into exile, his priests and his princes at the same time. 8 And the despoiler will come in on every city, and there will be no city that can make its escape. And the low plain will certainly perish and the level land be annihilated, a thing that Jehovah has said.

9 “Give a road mark to Mo′ab, YOU people, for at the falling in ruins she will go forth; and her very cities will become a mere object of astonishment, with no one dwelling in them.

10 “Cursed be the one that is carrying out the mission of Jehovah neglectfully; and cursed be the one that is holding back his sword from blood!

11 “The Mo′ab·ites have been at ease since their youth, and they are keeping undisturbed on their dregs. And they have not been emptied from one vessel into another vessel, and into exile they have not gone. That is why their taste has stood still within them, and their very scent has not been changed.

12 “‘Therefore, look! there are days coming,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and I will send to them vessel tilters, and they will certainly tilt them; and their vessels they will empty out, and their large jars they will dash to pieces. 13 And the Mo′ab·ites will have to be ashamed of Che′mosh, just as those of the house of Israel have become ashamed of Beth′el their confidence. 14 How dare YOU people say: “We are mighty men and men of vital energy for the war”?’

15 “‘Mo′ab has been despoiled, and one has gone up against her own cities. And their choicest young men themselves have gone down to the slaughtering,’ is the utterance of the King, whose name is Jehovah of armies.

16 “The disaster on the Mo′ab·ites is near to come, and their very calamity is actually hurrying up very much. 17 All those round about them will have to sympathize with them, even all those knowing their name. Say, YOU people, ‘O how the rod of strength has been broken, the staff of beauty!’

18 “Get down from glory, and sit down in thirst, O inhabitress of the daughter of Di′bon; for the despoiler of Mo′ab has come up against you. He will actually bring your fortified places to ruin.

19 “Stand still and look out for the way itself, O inhabitress of A·ro′er. Ask him that is fleeing and her that is making her escape. Say, ‘What has been brought about?’ 20 Mo′ab has been put to shame, for she has been struck with terror. Howl and cry out. Tell in Ar′non, O men, that Mo′ab has been despoiled. 21 And judgment itself has come to the land of level country, to Ho′lon and to Ja′haz and against Meph′a·ath, 22 and against Di′bon and against Ne′bo and against Beth-dib·la·tha′im, 23 and against Kir·i·a·tha′im and against Beth-ga′mul and against Beth-me′on 24 and against Ke′ri·oth and against Boz′rah and against all the cities of the land of Mo′ab, those far away and those near.

25 “‘The horn of Mo′ab has been cut down, and his own arm has been broken,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 26 ‘Make him drunk, O men, for he has put on great airs against Jehovah himself; and Mo′ab has slapped around in his vomit, and he has become an object of ridicule, even he himself.

27 “‘And did not Israel become a mere object of ridicule to you? Or was he found among outright thieves? For you would shake yourself just as often as you spoke against him.

28 “‘Leave the cities and reside on the crag, YOU inhabitants of Mo′ab, and become like the dove that makes its nest in the regions of the mouth of the hollow.’”

29 “We have heard of the pride of Mo′ab—he is very haughty—of his highness and of his pride and of his haughtiness and of the loftiness of his heart.”

30 “‘I myself have known his fury,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and that is not the way it will be; his empty talk—they will not actually do in just that way. 31 That is why it is over Mo′ab that I shall howl, and for Mo′ab in his entirety I shall cry out. For the men of Kir-he′res one shall moan.

32 “‘With more than the weeping for Ja′zer I shall weep for you, O vine of Sib′mah. Your own flourishing shoots have crossed over the sea. To the sea—to Ja′zer—they have reached. Upon your summer fruitage and upon your grape gathering the despoiler himself has fallen. 33 And rejoicing and joyfulness have been taken away from the orchard and from the land of Mo′ab. And from the winepresses I have caused the wine itself to cease. No one will be doing the treading with shouting. The shouting will be no shouting.’”

34 “‘From the cry in Hesh′bon clear to E·le·a′leh, clear to Ja′haz they have given forth their voice, from Zo′ar clear to Hor·o·na′im, to Eg′lath-she·li′shi·yah; for even the waters of Nim′rim themselves will become mere desolations. 35 And I will cause to cease from Mo′ab,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘the one bringing up an offering upon the high place and the one making sacrificial smoke to his god. 36 That is why my own heart will be boisterous for Mo′ab himself, just like flutes; and for the men of Kir-he′res my very heart will be boisterous, just like flutes. That is why the very abundance that he has produced will certainly perish. 37 For upon every head there is baldness, and every beard is clipped. Upon all hands there are cuts, and upon the hips there is sackcloth!’”

38 “‘On all the roofs of Mo′ab and in her public squares—all of it—there is wailing; for I have broken Mo′ab just like a vessel in which there is no delight,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 39 ‘O how she has become terrified! Howl, YOU people! O how Mo′ab has turned the back! He has become ashamed. And Mo′ab has become an object of ridicule and something terrifying to all those round about him.’”

40 “For this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Look! Just like an eagle that pounces, someone must also spread his wings over Mo′ab. 41 The towns will actually be captured, and her own strong places will certainly be seized. And the heart of the mighty men of Mo′ab must become in that day like the heart of a wife having childbirth distress.’”

42 “‘And Mo′ab will certainly be annihilated from being a people, for it is against Jehovah that he has put on great airs. 43 Dread and the hollow and the trap are upon you, O inhabitant of Mo′ab,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 44 ‘Anyone fleeing because of the dread will fall into the hollow; and anyone coming up out of the hollow will be caught in the trap.’

“‘For I shall bring upon her, upon Mo′ab, the year of their being given attention,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 45 ‘In the shadow of Hesh′bon those fleeing have stood still without power. For a very fire will certainly go forth out of Hesh′bon, and a flame from the midst of Si′hon; and it will devour the temples of Mo′ab and the crown of the head of the sons of uproar.’

46 “‘Woe to you, O Mo′ab! The people of Che′mosh have perished. For your sons have been taken as captives and your daughters as captives. 47 And I will gather the captive ones of Mo′ab in the final part of the days,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘Down to this point is the judgment upon Mo′ab.’”

Jeremiah

50 The word that Jehovah spoke concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chal·de′ans, by means of Jeremiah the prophet: 2 “Tell it among the nations and publish it. And lift up a signal; publish it. Hide nothing, O men. Say, ‘Babylon has been captured. Bel has been put to shame. Mer′o·dach has become terrified. Her images have been put to shame. Her dungy idols have become terrified.’ 3 For against her a nation has come up from the north. It is the one that makes her land an object of astonishment, so that there proves to be no one dwelling in her. Both man and domestic animal have taken flight. They have gone away.”

4 “In those days and at that time,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “the sons of Israel, they and the sons of Judah together, will come. They will walk, weeping as they walk, and for Jehovah their God they will seek. 5 To Zion they will keep asking the way, with their faces in that direction, saying, ‘Come and let us join ourselves to Jehovah in an indefinitely lasting covenant that will not be forgotten.’ 6 A flock of perishing creatures my people has become. Their own shepherds have caused them to wander about. On the mountains they have led them away. From mountain to hill they have gone. They have forgotten their resting-place. 7 All those finding them have eaten them up, and their own adversaries have said, ‘We shall not become guilty, due to the fact that they have sinned against Jehovah the abiding place of righteousness and the hope of their forefathers, Jehovah.’”

8 “Take YOUR flight out of the midst of Babylon, and go forth even out of the land of the Chal·de′ans, and become like the leading animals before the flock. 9 For here I am arousing and bringing up against Babylon a congregation of great nations from the land of the north, and they will certainly array themselves against her. From there she will be captured. One’s arrows are like those of a mighty man causing bereavement of children, who does not come back without results. 10 And Chal·de′a must become a spoil. All those making spoil of her will satisfy themselves,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

11 “For YOU men kept rejoicing, for YOU men kept exulting when pillaging my own inheritance. For YOU kept pawing like a heifer in the tender grass, and YOU kept neighing like stallions. 12 The mother of YOU men has become very much ashamed. She that gave YOU birth has been disappointed. Look! She is the least important of the nations, a waterless wilderness and a desert plain. 13 Because of the indignation of Jehovah she will not be inhabited, and she must become a desolate waste in her entirety. As for anyone passing along by Babylon, he will stare in astonishment and whistle on account of all her plagues.

14 “Array yourselves against Babylon on every side, all YOU who are treading the bow. Shoot at her. Spare no arrow, for it is against Jehovah that she has sinned. 15 Shout a war cry against her on every side. She has given her hand. Her pillars have fallen. Her walls have been torn down. For it is the vengeance of Jehovah. Take YOUR vengeance on her. Just as she has done, do to her. 16 Cut off the sower from Babylon, and the one handling the sickle in the time of harvest. Because of the maltreating sword they will turn each one to his own people, and they will flee each one to his own land.

17 “Israel is a scattered sheep. Lions themselves have done the dispersing. In the first instance the king of As·syr′i·a has devoured him, and in this latter instance Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon has gnawed on his bones. 18 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Here I am turning my attention upon the king of Babylon and upon his land in the same way that I turned my attention upon the king of As·syr′i·a. 19 And I will bring Israel back to his pasture ground, and he will certainly graze on Car′mel and on Ba′shan; and in the mountainous region of E′phra·im and of Gil′e·ad his soul will be satisfied.’”

20 “And in those days and at that time,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “the error of Israel will be searched for, but it will not be; and the sins of Judah, and they will not be found, for I shall forgive those whom I let remain.”

21 “Against the land of Mer·a·tha′im—come up against her and against the inhabitants of Pe′kod. Let there be a massacre and a devoting to destruction close upon them,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and do according to all that I have commanded you. 22 There is the sound of war in the land, and a great breakdown. 23 O how the forge hammer of all the earth has been cut down and gets broken! O how Babylon has become a mere object of astonishment among the nations! 24 I have laid a snare for you and you have also been caught, O Babylon, and you yourself did not know it. You were found and also taken hold of, for it was against Jehovah that you excited yourself.

25 “Jehovah has opened his storehouse, and he brings forth the weapons of his denunciation. For there is a work that the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has in the land of the Chal·de′ans. 26 Come in to her from the farthest part. Open up her granaries. Bank her up, just like those making heaps, and devote her to destruction. May she not come to have any remaining ones. 27 Massacre all her young bulls. May they go down to the slaughter. Woe to them, for their day has come, the time for their being given attention!

28 “There is the sound of those fleeing and those escaping from the land of Babylon to tell out in Zion the vengeance of Jehovah our God, the vengeance for his temple.

29 “SUMMON against Babylon archers, all who are treading the bow. Encamp against her all around. May there prove to be no escapees. Pay back to her according to her activity. According to all that she has done, do to her. For it is against Jehovah that she has acted presumptuously, against the Holy One of Israel. 30 Therefore her young men will fall in her public squares, and even all her men of war will be brought to silence in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

31 “Look! I am against you, O Presumptuousness,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, “for your day must come, the time that I must give you attention. 32 And Presumptuousness will certainly stumble and fall, and it will have no one to cause it to rise up. And I will set a fire ablaze in its cities, and it must devour all its surroundings.”

33 This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “The sons of Israel and the sons of Judah are being oppressed together, and all those taking them captive have laid hold on them. They have refused to let them go. 34 Their Repurchaser is strong, Jehovah of armies being his name. Without fail he will conduct their legal case, in order that he may actually give repose to the land and cause agitation to the inhabitants of Babylon.”

35 “There is a sword against the Chal·de′ans,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and against the inhabitants of Babylon and against her princes and against her wise ones. 36 There is a sword against the empty talkers, and they will certainly act foolishly. There is a sword against her mighty men, and they will actually become terrified. 37 There is a sword against their horses and against their war chariots and against all the mixed company that are in the midst of her, and they will certainly become women. There is a sword against her treasures, and they will actually be plundered. 38 There is a devastation upon her waters, and they must be dried up. For it is a land of graven images, and because of their frightful visions they keep acting crazy. 39 Therefore the haunters of waterless regions will dwell with the howling animals, and in her the ostriches must dwell; and she will nevermore be dwelt in, nor will she reside for generation after generation.”

40 “Just as with God’s overthrow of Sod′om and of Go·mor′rah and of her neighbor towns,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “no man will dwell there, nor will the son of mankind reside in her as an alien.

41 “Look! A people is coming in from the north; and a great nation and grand kings themselves will be roused up from the remotest parts of the earth. 42 Bow and javelin they handle. They are cruel and will show no mercy. The sound of them is like the sea that is boisterous, and upon horses they will ride; set in array as one man for war against you, O daughter of Babylon.

43 “The king of Babylon has heard the report about them, and his hands have dropped down. There is distress! Severe pains have seized hold of him, just like a woman giving birth.

44 “Look! Someone will come up just like a lion from the proud thickets along the Jordan to the durable abiding place, but in a moment I shall make them run away from her. And the one who is chosen I shall appoint over her. For who is like me, and who will challenge me, and who, now, is the shepherd that can stand before me? 45 Therefore hear, O men, the counsel of Jehovah that he has formulated against Babylon and his thoughts that he has thought out against the land of the Chal·de′ans. Surely the little ones of the flock will be dragged about. Surely on account of them he will cause their abiding place to be desolated. 46 At the sound when Babylon has been seized, the earth will certainly be set rocking, and among the nations an outcry itself be heard.”

Lamentations

א [ʼA′leph]

3 I am the able-bodied man that has seen affliction because of the staff of his fury.

2 It is I whom he has led and makes to walk in darkness and not in light.

3 Indeed, it is against me that he repeatedly turns his hand all day long.

ב [Behth]

4 He has caused my flesh and my skin to wear away. He has broken my bones.

5 He has built against me, that he may encircle me with poisonous plant and hardship.

6 In dark places he has made me sit like men dead for a long time.

ג [Gi′mel]

7 He has blocked me up as with a stone wall, that I may not go forth. He has made my copper fetters heavy.

8 Also, when I call for aid and cry for help, he actually hampers my prayer.

9 He has blocked up my ways with hewn stone. My roadways he has twisted.

ד [Da′leth]

10 As a bear lying in wait he is to me, as a lion in places of concealment.

11 My ways he has disarranged, and he makes me lie fallow. He has made me one laid desolate.

12 He has trodden his bow, and he sets me up as the target for the arrow.

ה [Heʼ]

13 He has brought into my kidneys the sons of his quiver.

14 I have become an object of laughter to all people against me, the theme of their song all day long.

15 He has given me a sufficiency of bitter things. He has saturated me with wormwood.

ו [Waw]

16 And with gravel he makes my teeth get broken. He has made me cower in the ashes.

17 You also do a casting off so that there is no peace for my soul. I have lost memory of what good is.

18 And I keep saying: “My excellency has perished, and my expectation from Jehovah.”

ז [Za′yin]

19 Remember my affliction and my homeless state, the wormwood and the poisonous plant.

20 Without fail your soul will remember and bow low over me.

21 This is what I shall bring back to my heart. That is why I shall show a waiting attitude.

ח [Chehth]

22 It is the acts of loving-kindness of Jehovah that we have not come to our finish, because his mercies will certainly not come to an end.

23 They are new each morning. Your faithfulness is abundant.

24 “Jehovah is my share,” my soul has said, “that is why I shall show a waiting attitude for him.”

ט [Tehth]

25 Good is Jehovah to the one hoping in him, to the soul that keeps seeking for him.

26 Good it is that one should wait, even silently, for the salvation of Jehovah.

27 Good it is for an able-bodied man that he should carry the yoke during his youth.

י [Yohdh]

28 Let him sit solitary and keep silent, because he has laid something upon him.

29 Let him put his mouth in the very dust. Perhaps there exists a hope.

30 Let him give his cheek to the very one striking him. Let him have his sufficiency of reproach.

כ [Kaph]

31 For not to time indefinite will Jehovah keep on casting off.

32 For although he has caused grief, he will also certainly show mercy according to the abundance of his loving-kindness.

33 For not out of his own heart has he afflicted or does he grieve the sons of men.

ל [La′medh]

34 For crushing beneath one’s feet all the prisoners of the earth,

35 For turning aside the judgment of an able-bodied man before the face of the Most High,

36 For making a man crooked in his legal case, Jehovah himself has had no countenance.

מ [Mem]

37 Who, now, has said that something should occur when Jehovah himself has not commanded?

38 From the mouth of the Most High bad things and what is good do not go forth.

39 How can a living man indulge in complaints, an able-bodied man on account of his sin?

נ [Nun]

40 Do let us search out our ways and explore them, and do let us return clear to Jehovah.

41 Let us raise our heart along with our palms to God in the heavens:

42 “We ourselves have transgressed, and we have behaved rebelliously. You yourself have not forgiven.

ס [Sa′mekh]

43 You have blocked approach with anger, and you keep pursuing us. You have killed; you have shown no compassion.

44 You have blocked approach to yourself with a cloud mass, that prayer may not pass through.

45 You make us mere offscouring and refuse in the midst of the peoples.”

פ [Peʼ]

46 Against us all our enemies have opened their mouth.

47 Dread and the hollow themselves have become ours, desolateness and breakdown.

48 With streams of water my eye keeps running down on account of the breakdown of the daughter of my people.

ע [ʽA′yin]

49 My very eye has been poured forth and will not keep still, so that there are no pauses,

50 Until Jehovah looks down and sees from heaven.

51 My own eye has dealt severely with my soul, because of all the daughters of my city.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

52 My enemies have positively hunted for me just as for a bird, for no cause.

53 They have silenced my life in the pit itself, and they kept hurling stones at me.

54 Waters have flowed over my head. I have said: “I shall certainly be cut off!”

ק [Qohph]

55 I have called out your name, O Jehovah, from a pit of the lowest sort.

56 My voice you must hear. Do not hide your ear to my relief, to my cry for help.

57 You have drawn near in the day that I kept calling you. You said: “Do not be afraid.”

ר [Rehsh]

58 You have taken up, O Jehovah, the contests of my soul. You have repurchased my life.

59 You have seen, O Jehovah, the wrong done to me. O do conduct the judgment for me.

60 You have seen all their vengeance, all their thoughts against me.

ש [Sin] or [Shin]

61 You have heard their reproach, O Jehovah, all their thoughts against me,

62 The lips of those rising up against me and their whispering against me all day long.

63 Do look at their very sitting down and their rising up. I am the subject of their song.

ת [Taw]

64 You will give back to them a treatment, O Jehovah, according to the work of their hands.

65 You will give to them the insolence of heart, your curse to them.

66 You will pursue in anger and annihilate them from under the heavens of Jehovah.

Ezekiel

1 Now it came about in the thirtieth year, in the fourth month, on the fifth day of the month, while I was in the midst of the exiled people by the river Che′bar, that the heavens were opened and I began to see visions of God. 2 On the fifth day of the month, that is, in the fifth year of the exile of King Je·hoi′a·chin, 3 the word of Jehovah occurred specifically to Ezekiel the son of Bu′zi the priest in the land of the Chal·de′ans by the river Che′bar, and upon him in that place the hand of Jehovah came to be.

4 And I began to see, and, look! there was a tempestuous wind coming from the north, a great cloud mass and quivering fire, and it had a brightness all around, and out of the midst of it there was something like the look of electrum, out of the midst of the fire. 5 And out of the midst of it there was the likeness of four living creatures, and this was how they looked: they had the likeness of earthling man. 6 And each one had four faces, and each one of them four wings. 7 And their feet were straight feet, and the sole of their feet was like the sole of the foot of a calf; and they were gleaming as with the glow of burnished copper. 8 And there were the hands of a man under their wings on their four sides, and the four of them had their faces and their wings. 9 Their wings were joining one to the other. They would not turn when they went; they would go each one straight forward.

10 And as for the likeness of their faces, the four of them had a man’s face with a lion’s face to the right, and the four of them had a bull’s face on the left; the four of them also had an eagle’s face. 11 That is the way their faces were. And their wings were spreading out upward. Each one had two joining to each other, and two were covering their bodies.

12 And they would go each one straight forward. To wherever the spirit would incline to go, they would go. They would not turn as they went. 13 And as for the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance was like burning coals of fire. Something like the appearance of torches was moving back and forth between the living creatures, and the fire was bright, and out of the fire there was lightning going forth. 14 And on the part of the living creatures there was a going forth and a returning as with the appearance of the lightning.

15 As I kept seeing the living creatures, why, look! there was one wheel on the earth beside the living creatures, by the four faces of each. 16 As for the appearance of the wheels and their structure, it was like the glow of chrys′o·lite; and the four of them had one likeness. And their appearance and their structure were just as when a wheel proved to be in the midst of a wheel. 17 When they went they would go on their four respective sides. They would not turn another way when they went. 18 And as for their rims, they had such height that they caused fearfulness; and their rims were full of eyes all around the four of them. 19 And when the living creatures went, the wheels would go beside them, and when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth, the wheels would be lifted up. 20 Wherever the spirit inclined to go, they would go, the spirit inclining to go there; and the wheels themselves would be lifted up close alongside them, for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels. 21 When they went, these would go; and when they stood still, these would stand still; and when they were lifted up from the earth, the wheels would be lifted up close alongside them, for the spirit of the living creature was in the wheels.

22 And over the heads of the living creatures there was the likeness of an expanse like the sparkle of awesome ice, stretched out over their heads up above. 23 And under the expanse their wings were straight, one to the other. Each one had two wings covering on this side and each one had two covering on that side their bodies. 24 And I got to hear the sound of their wings, a sound like that of vast waters, like the sound of the Almighty One, when they went, the sound of a tumult, like the sound of an encampment. When they stood still, they would let their wings down.

25 And there came to be a voice above the expanse that was over their head. (When they stood still, they would let their wings down.) 26 And above the expanse that was over their head there was something in appearance like sapphire stone, the likeness of a throne. And upon the likeness of the throne there was a likeness of someone in appearance like an earthling man upon it, up above. 27 And I got to see something like the glow of electrum, like the appearance of fire all around inside thereof, from the appearance of his hips and upward; and from the appearance of his hips and downward I saw something like the appearance of fire, and he had a brightness all around. 28 There was something like the appearance of the bow that occurs in a cloud mass on the day of a pouring rain. That is how the appearance was of the brightness round about. It was the appearance of the likeness of the glory of Jehovah. When I got to see it, then I fell upon my face, and I began to hear the voice of one speaking.

Ezekiel

12 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, in the midst of a rebellious house is where you are dwelling, that have eyes to see but they actually do not see, that have ears to hear but they actually do not hear, for they are a rebellious house. 3 As for you, O son of man, make up for yourself luggage for exile and go into exile in the daytime before their eyes, and you must go into exile from your place to another place before their eyes. Perhaps they will see, though they are a rebellious house. 4 And you must bring out your luggage like luggage for exile in the daytime before their eyes, and you yourself will go out in the evening before their eyes like those being brought forth for exile.

5 “Before their eyes, bore your way through the wall, and you must do the bringing out through it. 6 Before their eyes you will do the carrying on the shoulder itself. During the darkness you will do the bringing out. You will cover your very face that you may not see the earth, because a portent is what I have made you to the house of Israel.”

7 And I proceeded to do just the way that I had been commanded. My luggage I brought out, just like luggage for exile, in the daytime; and in the evening I bored my way through the wall by hand. During the darkness I did the bringing out. On my shoulder I did the carrying, before their eyes.

8 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me in the morning, saying: 9 “Son of man, did not those of the house of Israel, the rebellious house, say to you, ‘What are you doing?’ 10 Say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “As regards the chieftain, there is this pronouncement against Jerusalem and all the house of Israel who are in the midst of them.”’

11 “Say, ‘I am a portent for YOU. Just as I have done, that is the way it will be done to them. Into exile, into captivity they will go. 12 And as regards the chieftain who is in the midst of them, on the shoulder he will do carrying in the darkness and go out; through the wall they will bore in order to do the bringing forth through it. His face he will cover in order that he may not see with his own eye the earth.’ 13 And I shall certainly spread my net over him, and he must be caught in my hunting net; and I will bring him to Babylon, to the land of the Chal·de′ans, but it he will not see; and there he will die. 14 And all who are round about him as a help, and all his military bands, I shall scatter to every wind; and a sword I shall draw out after them. 15 And they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I disperse them among the nations and I actually scatter them among the lands. 16 And I will leave remaining from them a few men from the sword, from the famine and from the pestilence, in order that they may recount all their detestable things among the nations to whom they must come in; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.”

17 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 18 “Son of man, with quaking your bread you should eat, and with agitation and with anxious care your water you should drink. 19 And you must say to the people of the land, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to the inhabitants of Jerusalem upon the soil of Israel: “With anxious care their bread they will eat, and with horror their water they will drink, in order that its land may be laid desolate of its fullness because of the violence of all those dwelling in it. 20 And the inhabited cities themselves will be devastated, and the land itself will become a mere desolate waste; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah.”’”

21 And the word of Jehovah occurred further to me, saying: 22 “Son of man, what is this proverbial saying that YOU people have on the soil of Israel, saying, ‘The days are prolonged, and every vision has perished’? 23 Therefore say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “I shall certainly cause this proverbial saying to cease, and they will no more say it as a proverb in Israel.”’ But speak to them, ‘The days have drawn near, and the matter of every vision.’ 24 For there will no more prove to be any valueless vision nor double-faced divination in the midst of the house of Israel. 25 ‘“For I myself, Jehovah, shall speak what word I shall speak, and it will be done. There will be no postponement anymore, for in YOUR days, O rebellious house, I shall speak a word and certainly do it,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’”

26 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 27 “Son of man, look! those of the house of Israel are saying, ‘The vision that he is visioning is many days off, and respecting times far off he is prophesying.’ 28 Therefore say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “‘There will be no postponement anymore as to any words of mine. What word I shall speak, it will even be done,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’”

Ezekiel

15 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, in what way does the vine tree happen to be different from every other tree, the shoot, that has come to be among the trees of the forest? 3 Is there taken from it a pole with which to do some work? Or do people take from it a peg on which to hang any kind of utensil? 4 Look! Into the fire is where it must be put for fuel. Both ends of it the fire certainly devours, and the very middle of it does get scorched. Is it fit for any work? 5 Look! When it happens to be intact, it is not used for any work. How much less so, when fire itself has devoured it and it gets scorched, can it actually be used for any further work!”

6 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Just like the vine tree among the trees of the forest, that I have given to the fire as fuel, so I have given the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 7 And I have set my face against them. Out of the fire they have gone forth, but the fire itself will devour them. And YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah, when I direct my face against them.’”

8 “‘And I will make the land a desolate waste, for the reason that they have acted unfaithfully,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

16 And the word of Jehovah came further to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, make known to Jerusalem her detestable things. 3 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to Jerusalem: “Your origin and your birth were from the land of the Ca′naan·ite. Your father was the Am′or·ite, and your mother was a Hit′tite. 4 And as regards your birth, on the day of your being born your navel string had not been cut, and in water you had not been washed for cleansing, and with salt you had not at all been rubbed, and by no means had you been swaddled. 5 No eye felt sorry for you to do for you one of these things in compassion upon you, but you were thrown upon the surface of the field because there was an abhorring of your soul in the day of your being born.

6 “‘“And I came passing along by you and got to see you kicking about in your blood, and I proceeded to say to you in your blood, ‘Keep living!’ yes, to say to you in your blood, ‘Keep living!’ 7 A very big multitude like the sprouting of the field is what I made you so that you would grow big and become great and come in with the finest ornament. The two breasts themselves were firmly developed, and your own hair grew luxuriantly, when you had been naked and nude.”’

8 “‘And I came passing along by you and got to see you, and, look! your time was the time for love’s expressions. So I proceeded to spread my skirt over you and to cover your nudeness and to make a sworn statement to you and enter into a covenant with you,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and so you became mine. 9 Furthermore, I washed you with water and rinsed away your blood from off you and greased you with oil. 10 And I went on to clothe you with an embroidered garment and to shoe you with sealskin and to wrap you in fine linen and to cover you with costly material. 11 And I went on to deck you with ornaments and to put bracelets upon your hands and a necklace about your throat. 12 Furthermore, I put a nose ring in your nostril and earrings on your ears and a beautiful crown on your head. 13 And you kept decking yourself with gold and silver, and your attire was fine linen and costly material and an embroidered garment. Fine flour and honey and oil were what you ate, and you grew to be very, very pretty, and gradually you became fit for royal position.’”

14 “‘And for you a name began to go forth among the nations because of your prettiness, for it was perfect because of my splendor that I placed upon you,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

15 “‘But you began to trust in your prettiness and become a prostitute on account of your name and to pour out your acts of prostitution on every passerby; his it came to be. 16 And you proceeded to take some of your garments and make for yourself high places of varied colors and you would prostitute yourself on them—such things are not coming in, and it should not happen. 17 And you would take your beautiful articles from my gold and from my silver that I had given to you and you would make for yourself images of a male and prostitute yourself with them. 18 And you would take your embroidered garments and cover them; and my oil and my incense you would actually put before them. 19 And my bread that I had given to you—fine flour and oil and honey that I had had you eat—you also actually put it before them as a restful odor, and it continued to occur,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

20 “‘And you would take your sons and your daughters whom you had borne to me, and you would sacrifice these to them to be devoured—is that not enough of your acts of prostitution? 21 And you would slaughter my sons, and by making them pass through the fire you would give these to them. 22 And in all your detestable things and your acts of prostitution you did not remember the days of your youth when you happened to be naked and nude; kicking about in your blood you happened to be. 23 So it came about after all your badness (“woe, woe to you,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah) 24 that you went building for yourself a mound and making for yourself a height in every public square. 25 At every head of the way you built your height and you began to make your prettiness something detestable and sprawl out your feet to every passerby and multiply your acts of prostitution. 26 And you went prostituting yourself to the sons of Egypt, your neighbors great of flesh, and you continued making your prostitution abound in order to offend me. 27 And, look! I shall certainly stretch out my hand against you and I shall diminish your allowance and give you to the soulful desire of the women hating you, the daughters of the Phi·lis′tines, the women humiliated on account of your way as regards loose conduct.

28 “‘And you went on to prostitute yourself to the sons of As·syr′i·a because there was no satisfying of you, and you kept prostituting yourself with them and also did not get satisfaction. 29 So you kept making your prostitution abound toward the land of Ca′naan, toward the Chal·de′ans; and even in this you did not get satisfaction. 30 O how I am filled up with rage against you,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘by your doing all these things, the work of a woman, a domineering prostitute! 31 When you built your mound at the head of every way and you made your own height in every public square, yet you became unlike a prostitute in disdaining hire. 32 In the case of the wife that commits adultery, she takes strangers instead of her own husband. 33 To all prostitutes they are accustomed to give a present, but you—you have given your presents to all those passionately loving you, and you offer a bribe to them to come in to you from all around in your acts of prostitution. 34 And in your case the opposite thing takes place from that of other women in your acts of prostitution, and after your style no prostitution has been committed, even in your giving hire when no hire has been given to you, and so it occurs in the opposite way.’

35 “Therefore, O prostitute, hear the word of Jehovah. 36 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that your lustfulness has been poured out and your private parts are uncovered in your acts of prostitution toward those passionately loving you and toward all your detestable dungy idols, even with the blood of your sons whom you gave to them, 37 therefore here I am collecting together all those passionately loving you toward whom you were pleasurable and all those whom you loved along with all those whom you hated, and I will collect them together against you from all around and uncover your private parts to them, and they must see all your private parts.

38 “‘And I will judge you with the judgments of adulteresses and women shedding blood, and I will give you the blood of rage and jealousy. 39 And I will give you into their hand, and they will certainly tear down your mound and your heights will certainly be pulled down, and they must strip you of your garments and take your beautiful articles and leave you behind naked and nude. 40 And they must bring up against you a congregation and pelt you with stones and slaughter you with their swords. 41 And they must burn your houses with fire and execute in you acts of judgment before the eyes of many women; and I will cause you to cease from being a prostitute, and also no more hire will you give. 42 And I will bring my rage to its rest in you, and my jealousy must turn away from you; and I will stay quiet and I shall no more feel offended.’

43 “‘For the reason that you did not remember the days of your youth and you would cause me agitation because of all these things, even here I also, for my part, will put your own way upon your very head,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and you will certainly not carry on any loose conduct alongside all your detestable things.

44 “‘Look! Everyone using a proverb against you will use the proverb, saying: “Like mother is her daughter!” 45 You are the daughter of your mother, one abhorring her husband and her sons. And you are the sister of your sisters, who abhorred their husbands and their sons. The mother of YOU women was a Hit′tite, and YOUR father was an Am′or·ite.’”

46 “‘And your older sister is Sa·mar′i·a herself with her dependent towns, who is dwelling on your left, and your sister younger than you, who is dwelling on your right, is Sod′om with her dependent towns. 47 And it was not in their ways that you walked, nor according to their detestable things that you did. In a very little while you even began to act more ruinously than they did in all your ways. 48 As I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘Sod′om your sister, she with her dependent towns, has not done according to what you did, you and your dependent towns. 49 Look! This is what proved to be the error of Sod′om your sister: Pride, sufficiency of bread and the carefreeness of keeping undisturbed were what happened to belong to her and her dependent towns, and the hand of the afflicted one and the poor one she did not strengthen. 50 And they continued to be haughty and to carry on a detestable thing before me, and I finally removed them, just as I saw fit.

51 “‘And as for Sa·mar′i·a, she has not sinned even up to half of your sins, but you kept making your detestable things abound more than they did, so that you made your sisters appear righteous because of all your detestable things that you carried on. 52 You also, bear your humiliation when you must argue in favor of your sisters. Because of your sins in which you acted more detestably than they did, they are more righteous than you. And you also, be ashamed and bear your humiliation in that you make your sisters appear righteous.’

53 “‘And I will gather their captive ones, the captive ones of Sod′om and of her dependent towns, and the captive ones of Sa·mar′i·a and of her dependent towns; I will also gather your captive ones in the midst of them, 54 in order that you may bear your humiliation; and you must feel humiliated owing to all that you have done, in that you comforted them. 55 And your own sisters, Sod′om and her dependent towns, will return to their former state, and Sa·mar′i·a and her dependent towns will return to their former state, and you yourself and your own dependent towns will return to YOUR former state. 56 And Sod′om your sister did not prove to be anything worth hearing about from your mouth in the day of your pride, 57 before your own badness got to be exposed, just as at the time of the reproach of the daughters of Syria and of all round about her, the daughters of the Phi·lis′tines, those treating you with scorn on all sides. 58 Your loose conduct and your detestable things, you yourself must bear them,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

59 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I also must do with you just as you have done, because you despised the oath in breaking my covenant. 60 And I, I myself, must remember my covenant with you in the days of your youth, and I must establish for you an indefinitely lasting covenant. 61 And you will certainly remember your ways and feel humiliated when you receive your sisters, the ones older than you as well as the ones younger than you, and I shall certainly give them to you as daughters, but not owing to your covenant.’

62 “‘And I, I myself, will establish my covenant with you; and you will have to know that I am Jehovah, 63 in order that you may remember and actually be ashamed and you may no more come to have any reason to open your mouth because of your humiliation, when I make an atonement for you for all that you have done,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

20 Now it came about in the seventh year, in the fifth month, on the tenth day of the month, that men from the elderly ones of Israel came in to inquire of Jehovah, and they proceeded to sit down before me. 2 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 3 “Son of man, speak with the elderly men of Israel, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Is it in order to inquire of me that YOU men are coming? ‘As I am alive, I will not be inquired of by YOU,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’

4 “Will you judge them? Will you judge them, O son of man? Cause them to know the detestable things of their forefathers. 5 And you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “In the day of my choosing Israel, I also proceeded to lift up my hand in an oath to the seed of the house of Jacob and to make myself known to them in the land of Egypt. Yes, I proceeded to lift up my hand in an oath to them, saying, ‘I am Jehovah YOUR God.’ 6 In that day I lifted up my hand in an oath to them to bring them forth from the land of Egypt to a land that I had spied out for them, one flowing with milk and honey. It was the decoration of all the lands. 7 And I went on to say to them, ‘Throw away, each one of YOU, the disgusting things of his eyes, and with the dungy idols of Egypt do not defile yourselves. I am Jehovah YOUR God.’

8 “‘“And they began to rebel against me, and they did not consent to listen to me. The disgusting things of their eyes they did not individually throw away, and the dungy idols of Egypt they did not leave, so that I promised to pour out my rage upon them, in order to bring my anger to its finish upon them in the midst of the land of Egypt. 9 And I went acting for the sake of my own name that it might not be profaned before the eyes of the nations in among whom they were, because I had made myself known to them before their eyes on bringing them forth from the land of Egypt. 10 So I brought them forth from the land of Egypt and brought them into the wilderness.

11 “‘“And I proceeded to give them my statutes; and my judicial decisions I made known to them, in order that the man who keeps doing them might also keep living by them. 12 And my sabbaths I also gave to them, to become a sign between me and them, in order for them to know that I am Jehovah who is sanctifying them.

13 “‘“But they, the house of Israel, rebelled against me in the wilderness. In my statutes they did not walk, and my judicial decisions they rejected, which, should the man keep doing, he will also keep living by them. And my sabbaths they profaned very much, so that I promised to pour out my fury upon them in the wilderness, in order to exterminate them. 14 But I acted for the sake of my own name that it might not be profaned before the eyes of the nations, before whose eyes I had brought them forth. 15 And I myself also lifted up my hand in an oath to them in the wilderness, not to bring them into the land that I had given, one flowing with milk and honey, (it is the decoration of all the lands,) 16 for the reason that they rejected my own judicial decisions; and as regards my statutes, they did not walk in them, and my sabbaths they profaned, because it was after their dungy idols that their heart was going.

17 “‘“And my eye began to feel sorry for them to keep me from bringing them to ruin, and I did not make an extermination of them in the wilderness. 18 And I proceeded to say to their sons in the wilderness, ‘In the regulations of YOUR forefathers do not YOU walk, and their judgments do not YOU keep, and with their dungy idols do not YOU defile yourselves. 19 I am Jehovah YOUR God. Walk in my own statutes, and keep my own judicial decisions and do them. 20 And sanctify my own sabbaths, and they must serve as a sign between me and YOU, for YOU to know that I am Jehovah YOUR God.’

21 “‘“And the sons began to rebel against me. In my statutes they did not walk, and my judicial decisions they did not keep by doing them, which, should the man keep doing, he will also keep living by them. My sabbaths they profaned. So I promised to pour out my rage upon them, in order to bring my anger to its finish upon them in the wilderness. 22 And I drew back my hand and went acting for the sake of my own name, that it should not be profaned before the eyes of the nations, before whose eyes I had brought them out. 23 Also, I myself lifted up my hand in an oath to them in the wilderness, to scatter them among the nations and to disperse them among the lands, 24 for the reason that they did not carry out my own judicial decisions and they rejected my own statutes and they profaned my own sabbaths, and it was after the dungy idols of their forefathers that their eyes proved to be. 25 And I myself also let them have regulations that were not good and judicial decisions by which they could not keep living. 26 And I would let them become defiled by their gifts when they made every child opening the womb pass through the fire, in order that I might make them desolate, in order that they might know that I am Jehovah.”’

27 “Therefore speak to the house of Israel, O son of man, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Yet in this respect, YOUR forefathers spoke abusively of me, in their acting against me with unfaithfulness. 28 And I proceeded to bring them into the land that I had lifted up my hand in an oath to give them. When they got to see every exalted hill and every branchy tree, then they began sacrificing there their sacrifices and giving there their offensive offering, and presenting there their restful odors and pouring out there their drink offerings. 29 So I said to them, ‘What does the high place mean to which YOU are coming, that its name should be called a High Place down to this day?’”’

30 “Therefore say to the house of Israel, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “In the way of YOUR forefathers are YOU people defiling yourselves, and after their disgusting things are YOU going in immoral intercourse? 31 And in lifting up YOUR gifts by making YOUR sons pass through the fire, are YOU defiling yourselves for all YOUR dungy idols down till today? At the same time shall I myself be inquired of by YOU people, O house of Israel?”’

“‘As I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘I will not be inquired of by YOU. 32 And that which is coming up into YOUR spirit will itself positively not happen, in that YOU are saying: “Let us become like the nations, like the families of the lands, in ministering to wood and stone.”’”

33 “‘As I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘it will be with a strong hand and with a stretched-out arm and with outpoured rage that I will rule as king over YOU people. 34 And I will bring YOU forth from the peoples, and I will collect YOU together out of the lands to which YOU have been scattered with a strong hand and with a stretched-out arm and with outpoured rage. 35 And I will bring YOU into the wilderness of the peoples and put myself on judgment with YOU there face to face.

36 “‘Just as I put myself on judgment with YOUR forefathers in the wilderness of the land of Egypt, so I shall put myself on judgment with YOU,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 37 ‘And I will make YOU pass under the rod and bring YOU into the bond of the covenant. 38 And I will clean out from YOU the revolters and the transgressors against me, for out of the land of their alien residence I shall bring them forth, but onto the soil of Israel they will not come; and YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

39 “And YOU, O house of Israel, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Go serve each one of YOU his own dungy idols. And afterward if YOU are not listening to me, then my holy name YOU will no more profane by YOUR gifts and by YOUR dungy idols.’

40 “‘For in my holy mountain, in the mountain of the height of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘there is where they, the whole house of Israel in its entirety, will serve me, in the land. There I shall take pleasure in them, and there I shall require YOUR contributions and the firstfruits of YOUR presentations in all YOUR holy things. 41 Because of the restful odor I shall take pleasure in YOU, when I bring YOU forth from the peoples and I actually collect YOU together from the lands to which YOU have been scattered, and I will be sanctified in YOU before the eyes of the nations.’

42 “‘And YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah, when I bring YOU onto the soil of Israel, into the land that I lifted up my hand in an oath to give to YOUR forefathers. 43 And YOU will certainly remember there YOUR ways and all YOUR dealings by which YOU defiled yourselves, and YOU will actually feel a loathing at YOUR own faces because of all YOUR bad things that YOU did. 44 And YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah when I take action with YOU for the sake of my name, not according to YOUR bad ways or according to YOUR corrupted dealings, O house of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

45 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 46 “Son of man, set your face in the direction of the southern quarter and drip words to the south, and prophesy to the forest of the field of the south. 47 And you must say to the forest of the south, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah. This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am setting a fire ablaze against you, and it must devour in you every still-moist tree and every dry tree. The kindling flame will not be extinguished, and by it all faces must be scorched from the south to the north. 48 And all those of flesh must see that I myself, Jehovah, have set it afire, so that it will not be extinguished.”’”

49 And I proceeded to say: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! They are saying respecting me, ‘Is he not composing proverbial sayings?’”

Ezekiel

24 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me in the ninth year, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, saying: 2 “Son of man, write down for yourself the name of the day, this selfsame day. The king of Babylon has thrown himself against Jerusalem on this selfsame day. 3 And compose a proverbial saying concerning the rebellious house, and you must say concerning them,

“‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Put the widemouthed cooking pot on; put it on, and also pour water into it. 4 Gather pieces in it, every good piece, thigh and shoulder; fill it even with the choicest bones. 5 Let there be a taking of the choicest sheep, and also stack the logs in a circle under it. Boil its pieces, also cook its bones in the midst of it.”’”

6 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Woe to the city of deeds of bloodshed, the widemouthed cooking pot, the rust of which is in it, and the very rust of which has not gone forth from it! Piece by piece of it, bring it out; no lot must be cast over it. 7 For its very blood has come to be right in the midst of it. Upon the shining, bare surface of a crag she placed it. She did not pour it out upon the earth, in order to cover it over with dust. 8 In order to bring up rage for the executing of vengeance, I have put her blood upon the shining, bare surface of a crag, in order that it may not be covered over.’

9 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Woe to the city of deeds of bloodshed! I myself also shall make the pile great. 10 Make the logs many. Kindle the fire. Boil the flesh thoroughly. And empty out the broth, and let the bones themselves become piping hot. 11 Stand it empty upon its coals in order that it may get hot; and its copper must become heated up, and its uncleanness must be liquefied in the midst of it. Let its rust get consumed. 12 Troubles! It has made one tired, but the great amount of its rust does not go forth from it. Into the fire with its rust!’

13 “‘There was loose conduct in your uncleanness. For that reason I had to cleanse you, but you did not become clean from your uncleanness. You will become clean no more until I cause my rage to come to its rest in your case. 14 I myself, Jehovah, have spoken. It must come, and I will act. I shall not neglect, neither shall I feel sorry nor feel regret. According to your ways and according to your dealings they will certainly judge you,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

15 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 16 “Son of man, here I am taking away from you the thing desirable to your eyes by a blow, and you should not beat your breast, neither should you weep nor should your tears come on. 17 Sigh without words. For the dead ones no mourning should you make. Your headdress bind on yourself, and your sandals you should put upon your feet. And you should not cover over the mustache, and the bread of men you should not eat.”

18 And I proceeded to speak to the people in the morning, and my wife gradually died in the evening. So I did in the morning just as I had been commanded. 19 And the people kept saying to me: “Will you not tell us what these things have to do with us, that you are doing?” 20 Then I said to them: “The very word of Jehovah has occurred to me, saying, 21 ‘Say to the house of Israel: “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am profaning my sanctuary, the pride of YOUR strength, the thing desirable to YOUR eyes and the object of YOUR soul’s compassion, and YOUR sons and YOUR daughters whom YOU people have left behind—by the sword they will fall. 22 And YOU will have to do just as I have done. Mustaches YOU will not cover over, and the bread of men YOU will not eat. 23 And YOUR headdress will be on YOUR heads, and YOUR sandals be upon YOUR feet. YOU will not beat yourselves nor will YOU weep, and YOU will have to rot away in YOUR errors, and YOU will actually groan over one another. 24 And Ezekiel has become for YOU a portent. In accord with all that he has done, YOU will do. When it comes, YOU will also have to know that I am the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’”’”

25 “And as for you, O son of man, will it not be in the day of my taking away from them their fortress, the beautiful object of their exultation, the thing desirable to their eyes and the longing of their soul, their sons and their daughters, that 26 in that day there will come to you the escaped one for making the ears hear? 27 In that day your mouth will be opened to the escaped one, and you will speak and be mute no longer; and you will certainly become to them a portent, and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

25 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face toward the sons of Am′mon and prophesy against them. 3 And you must say concerning the sons of Am′mon, ‘Hear the word of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “For the reason that you have said Aha! against my sanctuary, because it has been profaned, and against the soil of Israel, because it has been laid desolate, and against the house of Judah, because they have gone into exile, 4 therefore here I am giving you to the Orientals as something to possess, and they will set up their walled camps in you and will certainly put in you their tabernacles. They themselves will eat your fruitage, and they themselves will drink your milk. 5 And I will make Rab′bah a pasture ground of camels and the sons of Am′mon a resting-place of a flock; and YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah.”’”

6 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you clapped the hands and you stamped with the feet and you kept rejoicing with all scorn on your part in your soul against the soil of Israel, 7 therefore here I am; I have stretched out my hand against you, and I will give you as something to plunder to the nations; and I will cut you off from the peoples and destroy you from the lands. I shall annihilate you, and you will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

8 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that Mo′ab and Se′ir have said: “Look! The house of Judah is like all the other nations,” 9 therefore here I am opening the slope of Mo′ab at the cities, at his cities to his frontier, the decoration of the land, Beth-jesh′i·moth, Ba′al-me′on, even to Kir·i·a·tha′im, 10 to the Orientals, alongside the sons of Am′mon; and I will make it something to possess, in order that it may not be remembered, that is, the sons of Am′mon, among the nations. 11 And in Mo′ab I shall execute acts of judgment; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

12 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that E′dom has acted in taking vengeance upon the house of Judah and they kept doing wrong extensively and avenged themselves on them, 13 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “I will also stretch out my hand against E′dom and cut off from it man and domestic animal, and I will make it a devastated place from Te′man, even to De′dan. By the sword they will fall. 14 ‘And I will bring my vengeance on E′dom by the hand of my people Israel; and they must do in E′dom according to my anger and according to my rage; and they will have to know what my vengeance is,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’

15 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that the Phi·lis′tines have acted with vengeance and they kept avenging themselves with a vengeance with scorn in the soul, in order to cause ruin, with an indefinitely lasting enmity, 16 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am stretching out my hand against the Phi·lis′tines, and I will cut off the Cher′e·thites and destroy the rest of the seacoast. 17 And I will execute in them great acts of vengeance, with raging reproofs; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I bring my vengeance on them.”’”

Ezekiel

28 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, say to the leader of Tyre, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said:

“‘“For the reason that your heart has become haughty, and you keep saying, ‘I am a god. In the seat of god I have seated myself, in the heart of the open sea,’ whereas an earthling man is what you are, and not a god, and you keep making your heart like the heart of god— 3 look! you are wiser than Daniel. There are no secrets that have proved a match for you. 4 By your wisdom and by your discernment you have made wealth for your own self, and you keep getting gold and silver in your storehouses. 5 By the abundance of your wisdom, by your sales goods, you have made your wealth abound, and your heart began to be haughty because of your wealth.”’

6 “‘Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “For the reason that you make your heart like the heart of god, 7 therefore here I am bringing upon you strangers, the tyrants of the nations, and they will certainly draw their swords against the beauty of your wisdom and profane your beaming splendor. 8 Down to the pit they will bring you, and you must die the death of someone slain in the heart of the open sea. 9 Will you without fail say, ‘I am god,’ before the one killing you, whereas you are a mere earthling man, and not a god, in the hand of those profaning you?”’

10 “‘The deaths of uncircumcised ones you will die by the hand of strangers, for I myself have spoken,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

11 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 12 “Son of man, lift up a dirge concerning the king of Tyre, and you must say to him, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said:

“‘“You are sealing up a pattern, full of wisdom and perfect in beauty. 13 In E′den, the garden of God, you proved to be. Every precious stone was your covering, ruby, topaz and jasper; chrys′o·lite, onyx and jade; sapphire, turquoise and emerald; and of gold was the workmanship of your settings and your sockets in you. In the day of your being created they were made ready. 14 You are the anointed cherub that is covering, and I have set you. On the holy mountain of God you proved to be. In the midst of fiery stones you walked about. 15 You were faultless in your ways from the day of your being created until unrighteousness was found in you.

16 “‘“Because of the abundance of your sales goods they filled the midst of you with violence, and you began to sin. And I shall put you as profane out of the mountain of God, and I shall destroy you, O cherub that is covering, from the midst of the fiery stones.

17 “‘“Your heart became haughty because of your beauty. You brought your wisdom to ruin on account of your beaming splendor. Onto the earth I will throw you. Before kings I will set you, for them to look upon you.

18 “‘“Owing to the abundance of your errors, because of the injustice of your sales goods, you have profaned your sanctuaries. And I shall bring forth a fire from the midst of you. It is what must devour you. And I shall make you ashes upon the earth before the eyes of all those seeing you. 19 As for all those knowing you among the peoples, they will certainly stare in amazement at you. Sudden terrors are what you must become, and you will be no more to time indefinite.”’”

20 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 21 “Son of man, set your face toward Si′don, and prophesy against her. 22 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O Si′don, and I shall certainly be glorified in the midst of you; and people will have to know that I am Jehovah when I execute acts of judgment in her and I am actually sanctified in her. 23 And I will send pestilence into her and blood into her streets. And the slain one must fall in the midst of her by the sword against her on every side; and people will have to know that I am Jehovah. 24 And no more will there prove to be to the house of Israel a malignant prickle or a painful thorn out of all those round about them, those who are treating them with scorn; and people will have to know that I am the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’

25 “‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “When I collect together the house of Israel out from the peoples among whom they have been scattered, I will also be sanctified among them in the eyes of the nations. And they will certainly dwell upon their soil that I gave to my servant, to Jacob. 26 And they will actually dwell upon it in security and build houses and plant vineyards, and they must dwell in security when I execute acts of judgment upon all those treating them with scorn all round about them; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah their God.”’”

Ezekiel

29 In the tenth year, in the tenth month, on the twelfth day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face against Phar′aoh the king of Egypt and prophesy against him and against Egypt in its entirety. 3 Speak, and you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O Phar′aoh, king of Egypt, the great sea monster lying stretched out in the midst of his Nile canals, that has said, ‘My Nile River belongs to me, and I—I have made it for myself.’ 4 And I will put hooks in your jaws and cause the fish of your Nile canals to cling to your scales. And I will bring you up out of the midst of your Nile canals and all the fish of your Nile canals that cling to your very scales. 5 And I will abandon you to the wilderness, you and all the fish of your Nile canals. Upon the surface of the field you will fall. You will not be gathered up nor be collected together. To the wild beasts of the earth and to the flying creatures of the heavens I will give you for food. 6 And all the inhabitants of Egypt will have to know that I am Jehovah, for the reason that they proved to be, as a support, a reed to the house of Israel. 7 When they took hold of you by the hand, you got to be crushed, and you caused a split in their entire shoulder. And when they supported themselves upon you, you got to be broken, and you caused all their hips to wobble.”

8 “‘Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am bringing upon you a sword, and I will cut off from you earthling man and domestic animal. 9 And the land of Egypt must become a desolate waste and a devastated place; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah, for the reason that he has said, ‘To me the Nile River belongs, and I myself have made it.’ 10 Therefore here I am against you and against your Nile canals, and I will make the land of Egypt devastated places, dryness, a desolated waste, from Mig′dol to Sy·e′ne and to the boundary of E·thi·o′pi·a. 11 There will not pass through it the foot of earthling man, nor will the foot of domestic animal pass through it, and for forty years it will not be inhabited. 12 And I will make the land of Egypt a desolate waste in the midst of desolated lands; and its own cities will become a desolate waste in the very midst of devastated cities for forty years; and I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations and disperse them among the lands.”

13 “‘For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “At the end of forty years I shall collect the Egyptians together out of the peoples among whom they will have been scattered, 14 and I will bring back the captive group of the Egyptians; and I will bring them back to the land of Path′ros, to the land of their origin, and there they must become a lowly kingdom. 15 Lower than the other kingdoms it will become, and it will no more lift itself up over the other nations, and I will make them so few as not to have the other nations in subjection. 16 And it will no more prove to be the house of Israel’s confidence, bringing error to remembrance by their turning after them. And they will have to know that I am the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’”

17 Now it came about in the twenty-seventh year, in the first month, on the first day of the month, that the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 18 “Son of man, Neb·u·chad·rez′zar himself, the king of Babylon, made his military force perform a great service against Tyre. Every head was one made bald, and every shoulder was one rubbed bare. But as for wages, there proved to be none for him and his military force from Tyre for the service that he had performed against her.

19 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am giving to Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon the land of Egypt, and he must carry off its wealth and make a big spoil of it and do a great deal of plundering of it; and it must become wages for his military force.’

20 “‘As his compensation for service that he did against her I have given him the land of Egypt, because they acted for me,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

21 “In that day I shall cause a horn to sprout for the house of Israel, and to you I shall give occasion to open the mouth in the midst of them; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

30 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, prophesy, and you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Howl, YOU people, ‘Alas for the day!’ 3 for a day is near, yes, a day belonging to Jehovah is near. A day of clouds, an appointed time of nations it will prove to be. 4 And a sword will certainly come into Egypt, and severe pains must occur in E·thi·o′pi·a when one falls slain in Egypt and they actually take its wealth and its foundations are actually torn down. 5 E·thi·o′pi·a and Put and Lud and all the mixed company and Chub and the sons of the land of the covenant—with them they will fall by the very sword.”’

6 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘The supporters of Egypt must also fall, and the pride of its strength must come down.’

“‘From Mig′dol to Sy·e′ne they will fall in it even by the sword,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 7 ‘They must also be made desolate in the midst of desolated lands, and its own cities will come to be right in the midst of devastated cities. 8 And they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I set a fire in Egypt and all its helpers are actually broken. 9 In that day messengers will go forth from before me in the ships, in order to drive self-confident E·thi·o′pi·a into trembling. And severe pains must occur among them in the day of Egypt, for, look! it must come.’

10 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I will also cause the crowd of Egypt to cease by the hand of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon. 11 He and his people with him, the tyrants of the nations, are being brought in to reduce the land to ruin. And they must draw their swords against Egypt and fill the land with the slain. 12 And I will make the Nile canals dry ground and will sell the land into the hand of bad men, and I will cause the land and its fullness to be desolated by the hand of strangers. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.’

13 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I will also destroy the dungy idols and cause the valueless gods to cease out of Noph, and there will no more prove to be a chieftain out of the land of Egypt; and I shall certainly put fear in the land of Egypt. 14 And I will bring Path′ros to desolation and set a fire in Zo′an and execute acts of judgment in No. 15 And I will pour out my rage upon Sin, the fortress of Egypt, and cut off the crowd of No. 16 And I will set a fire in Egypt. Sin will without fail be in severe pains, and No itself will come to be for capture by breaches; and as regards Noph—there will be adversaries during the daytime! 17 As for the young men of On and Pi·be′seth, by the sword they will fall, and into captivity the cities themselves will go. 18 And in Te·haph′ne·hes the day will actually grow dark, when I break there the yoke bars of Egypt. And in her the pride of her strength will actually be made to cease. As for her, clouds themselves will cover her, and into captivity her own dependent towns will go. 19 And I will execute acts of judgment in Egypt; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

20 And it occurred further that in the eleventh year, in the first month, on the seventh day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 21 “Son of man, the arm of Phar′aoh the king of Egypt I shall certainly break, and, look! it will not be bound up at all in order to give it healing by putting a bandage on for binding it up, for it to become strong to take hold of the sword.”

22 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am against Phar′aoh the king of Egypt, and I will break his arms, the strong one and the broken one, and I will cause the sword to fall out of his hand. 23 And I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations and disperse them among the lands. 24 And I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon and give my sword into his hand, and I will break the arms of Phar′aoh, and as a deadly wounded one he will certainly do a great deal of groaning before him. 25 And I will strengthen the arms of the king of Babylon, and the very arms of Phar′aoh will fall; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I give my sword into the hand of the king of Babylon and he actually extends it out against the land of Egypt. 26 And I will scatter the Egyptians among the nations and disperse them among the lands; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

Ezekiel

33 And the word of Jehovah proceeded to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, speak to the sons of your people, and you must say to them,

“‘As regards a land, in case I bring upon it a sword and the people of the land, one and all, actually take a man and set him as their watchman, 3 and he really sees the sword coming upon the land and blows the horn and warns the people, 4 and the hearer actually hears the sound of the horn but he takes no warning at all, and a sword comes and takes him away, his own blood will come to be upon his own head. 5 The sound of the horn he heard, but he took no warning. His own blood will come to be upon his own self. And had he himself taken warning, his own soul would have escaped.

6 “‘Now as regards the watchman, in case he sees the sword coming and he actually does not blow the horn and the people itself gets no warning at all and a sword comes and takes away from them soul, for its own error it itself must be taken away, but its blood I shall ask back from the hand of the watchman himself.’

7 “Now as regards you, O son of man, a watchman is what I have made you to the house of Israel, and at my mouth you must hear the word and give them warning from me. 8 When I say to someone wicked, ‘O wicked one, you will positively die!’ but you actually do not speak out to warn the wicked one from his way, he himself as a wicked one will die in his own error, but his blood I shall ask back at your own hand. 9 But as regards you, in case you actually warn someone wicked from his way for him to turn back from it but he actually does not turn back from his way, he himself will die in his own error, whereas you yourself will certainly deliver your own soul.

10 “Now as regards you, O son of man, say to the house of Israel, ‘Thus YOU people have said: “Because our revolts and our sins are upon us and in them we are rotting away, how, then, shall we keep living?”’ 11 Say to them, ‘“As I am alive,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, “I take delight, not in the death of the wicked one, but in that someone wicked turns back from his way and actually keeps living. Turn back, turn back from YOUR bad ways, for why is it that YOU should die, O house of Israel?”’

12 “And as for you, O son of man, say to the sons of your people, ‘The righteousness of the righteous one will not itself deliver him in the day of his revolt. But as regards the wickedness of the wicked one, he will not be made to stumble by it in the day of his turning back from his wickedness. Nor will even anyone having righteousness be able to keep living because of it in the day of his sinning. 13 When I say to the righteous one: “You will positively keep living,” and he himself actually trusts in his own righteousness and does injustice, all his own righteous acts will not be remembered, but for his injustice that he has done—for this he will die.

14 “‘And when I say to the wicked one: “You will positively die,” and he actually turns back from his sin and carries on justice and righteousness, 15 and the wicked one returns the very thing pledged, pays back the very things taken by robbery, and actually walks in the very statutes of life by not doing injustice, he will positively keep living. He will not die. 16 None of his sins with which he has sinned will be remembered against him. Justice and righteousness are what he has carried on. He will positively keep living.’

17 “And the sons of your people have said, ‘The way of Jehovah is not adjusted right,’ but, as for them, it is their way that is not adjusted right.

18 “When someone righteous turns back from his righteousness and actually does injustice, he must also die for them. 19 And when someone wicked turns back from his wickedness and actually carries on justice and righteousness, it will be on account of them that he himself will keep living.

20 “And YOU people have said, ‘The way of Jehovah is not adjusted right.’ It will be each one according to his ways that I shall judge YOU, O house of Israel.”

21 At length it occurred in the twelfth year, in the tenth month, on the fifth day of the month of our exile, that there came to me the escaped one from Jerusalem, saying: “The city has been struck down!”

22 Now the very hand of Jehovah had come to be upon me in the evening before the coming of the escaped one, and He proceeded to open my mouth prior to that one’s coming to me in the morning, and my mouth was opened and I proved to be speechless no longer.

23 And the word of Jehovah began to occur to me, saying: 24 “Son of man, the inhabitants of these devastated places are saying even concerning the soil of Israel, ‘Abraham happened to be just one and yet he took possession of the land. And we are many; to us the land has been given as something to possess.’

25 “Therefore say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “With the blood YOU keep eating, and YOUR eyes YOU keep lifting to YOUR dungy idols, and blood YOU keep pouring out. So should YOU possess the land? 26 YOU have depended upon YOUR sword. YOU have done a detestable thing, and YOU have defiled each one the wife of his companion. So should YOU possess the land?”’

27 “This is what you should say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “As I am alive, surely the ones who are in the devastated places will fall by the sword itself; and the one who is upon the surface of the field, to the wild beast I shall certainly give him for food; and those who are in the strong places and in the caves will die by the pestilence itself. 28 And I shall actually make the land a desolate waste, even a desolation, and the pride of its strength must be made to cease and the mountains of Israel must be laid desolate, with no one passing through. 29 And they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I make the land a desolate waste, even a desolation, on account of all their detestable things that they have done.”’

30 “And as for you, O son of man, the sons of your people are speaking with one another about you beside the walls and in the entrances of the houses, and the one has spoken with the other, each one with his brother, saying, ‘COME, please, and hear what the word is that is going forth from Jehovah.’ 31 And they will come in to you, like the coming in of people, and sit before you as my people; and they will certainly hear your words but these they will not do, for with their mouth they are expressing lustful desires and after their unjust gain is where their heart is going. 32 And, look! you are to them like a song of sensuous loves, like one with a pretty voice and playing a stringed instrument well. And they will certainly hear your words, but there are none doing them. 33 And when it comes true—look! it must come true—they will also have to know that a prophet himself had proved to be in the midst of them.”

Ezekiel

35 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face against the mountainous region of Se′ir and prophesy against it. 3 And you must say to it, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O mountainous region of Se′ir, and I will stretch out my hand against you and make you a desolate waste, even a desolation. 4 Your cities I shall set as a devastated place, and you yourself will become a sheer desolate waste; and you will have to know that I am Jehovah, 5 for the reason that you proved to have an indefinitely lasting enmity and you kept delivering the sons of Israel over to the power of the sword, in the time of their disaster, in the time of their final error.”’

6 “‘Therefore as I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘because it was for blood that I was preparing you, blood itself will also pursue you. Surely it was blood that you hated, and blood itself will pursue you. 7 And I shall certainly make the mountainous region of Se′ir a desolate waste, even a desolation, and I will cut off from it the one passing through and the one returning. 8 And I will fill its mountains with its slain ones; as for your hills and your valleys and all your streambeds, the very ones slain by the sword will fall in them. 9 Indefinitely lasting desolate wastes are what I shall make you, and your own cities will not be inhabited; and YOU people will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

10 “By reason of your saying, ‘These two nations and these two lands—they will become my own, and we shall certainly take possession of each land,’ whereas Jehovah himself happened to be right there, 11 ‘therefore as I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘I will act also according to your anger and according to your jealousy that you have expressed owing to your feelings of hatred toward them; and I will make myself known among them when I judge you. 12 And you will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have heard all your disrespectful things that you have said concerning the mountains of Israel, saying: “They have been laid desolate. To us they have been given for food.” 13 And YOU people kept acting in great style against me with YOUR mouths, and YOU have multiplied against me YOUR words. I myself have heard them.’

14 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘At the same time that all the earth rejoices, a desolate waste is what I shall make of you. 15 Just as there was rejoicing on your part at the inheritance of the house of Israel because it was laid desolate, the same thing I shall make of you. A desolate waste is what you will become, O mountainous region of Se′ir, even all E′dom, all of it; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

Ezekiel

46 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘As regards the gate of the inner courtyard that is facing east, it should continue shut for the six workdays, and on the sabbath day it should be opened, and on the day of the new moon it should be opened. 2 And the chieftain must come in by the way of the porch of the gate, from outside, and stand by the doorpost of the gate; and the priests must render up his whole burnt offering and his communion sacrifices, and he must bow down upon the threshold of the gate, and he must go out, but the gate itself should not be shut until the evening. 3 And the people of the land must bow down at the entrance of that gate on the sabbaths and on the new moons, before Jehovah.

4 “‘And the whole burnt offering that the chieftain should present to Jehovah on the sabbath day should be six sound male lambs and a sound ram; 5 and as a grain offering an e′phah for the ram, and for the male lambs a grain offering as he is able to give, and, as regards oil, a hin to the e′phah. 6 And on the day of the new moon there should be a young bull, the son of the herd, a sound one, and six male lambs and a ram; sound ones they should prove to be. 7 And an e′phah for the young bull and an e′phah for the ram he should render up as a grain offering, and for the male lambs according to what he is able to afford; and, as regards oil, a hin to the e′phah.

8 “‘And when the chieftain comes in, by the way of the porch of the gate he should come in, and by the way of it he should go out. 9 And when the people of the land come in before Jehovah in the festal seasons, the one coming in by the way of the north gate in order to bow down should go out by the way of the south gate; and the one coming in by the way of the south gate should go out by the way of the gate to the north. No one should go back by the way of the gate by which he came in, for he should go out straight ahead of him. 10 And as regards the chieftain in their midst, when they come in, he should come in; and when they go out, he should go out. 11 And in the festivals and in the festal seasons the grain offering should prove to be an e′phah for the young bull and an e′phah for the ram, and for the male lambs as he is able to give; and, as regards oil, a hin to the e′phah.

12 “‘And in case the chieftain should provide as a voluntary offering a whole burnt offering, or communion sacrifices as a voluntary offering to Jehovah, one must also open to him the gate that is facing east, and he must provide his whole burnt offering and his communion sacrifices just as he does on the sabbath day. And he must go out, and one must shut the gate after his going out.

13 “‘And a sound male lamb, in its first year, you should provide as a whole burnt offering daily to Jehovah. Morning by morning you should provide it. 14 And as a grain offering you should provide with it morning by morning the sixth of an e′phah and, as regards oil, the third of a hin for sprinkling the fine flour. The grain offering to Jehovah is an indefinitely lasting statute, constantly. 15 And they must provide the male lamb and the grain offering and the oil morning by morning as a constant whole burnt offering.’

16 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘In case the chieftain should give a gift to each one of his sons as his inheritance, it itself will become the property of his sons themselves. It is their possession by inheritance. 17 And in case he should give a gift from his inheritance to one of his servants, it must also become his until the year of liberty; and it must return to the chieftain. Only his inheritance—as regards his sons—is what should continue to belong to their own selves. 18 And the chieftain should not take any of the inheritance of the people so as to force them out of their possession. From his own possession he should give his sons an inheritance, to the end that my people may not be scattered each one from his possession.’”

19 And he proceeded to bring me in by the entryway that was by the side of the gate to the holy dining rooms, those belonging to the priests, that were facing to the north, and, look! there was a place there on both rear sides to the west. 20 And he proceeded to say to me: “This is the place where the priests will boil the guilt offering and the sin offering, and where they will bake the grain offering, in order to carry nothing out to the outer courtyard so as to sanctify the people.”

21 And he proceeded to bring me out to the outer courtyard and make me pass along to the four corner posts of the courtyard, and, look! there was a courtyard by this corner post of the courtyard, a courtyard by that corner post of the courtyard. 22 At the four corner posts of the courtyard there were small courtyards, forty cubits in length and thirty in width. The four of them with corner structures had the same measurement. 23 And there was a row round about them, round about the four of them, and there were boiling places made beneath the rows round about. 24 Then he said to me: “These are the houses of those doing the boiling, where the ministers of the House boil the sacrifice of the people.”

Ezekiel

47 And gradually he brought me back to the entrance of the House, and, look! there was water going forth from under the threshold of the House eastward, for the front of the House was east. And the water was going down from under, from the right-hand side of the House, south of the altar.

2 And he gradually brought me forth by the way of the north gate and took me around by the way outside to the outer gate that is facing toward the east, and, look! water was trickling from the right-hand side.

3 When the man went forth eastward with a measuring line in his hand, he also proceeded to measure a thousand in cubits and to make me pass through the water, water up to the ankles.

4 And he continued measuring a thousand and then made me pass through the water, water up to the knees.

And he continued measuring a thousand and now made me pass through—water up to the hips.

5 And he continued measuring a thousand. It was a torrent that I was not able to pass through, for the water had got high, water permitting swimming, a torrent that could not be passed through.

6 At that he said to me: “Have you seen this, O son of man?”

Then he had me walk and had me return to the bank of the torrent. 7 When I returned, why, look! on the bank of the torrent there were very many trees, on this side and on that side. 8 And he went on to say to me: “This water is going forth to the eastern region and must go down through the Ar′a·bah. And it must come to the sea. It being brought forth into the sea itself, its water is also actually healed. 9 And it must occur that every living soul that swarms, in every place to which the double-size torrent comes, will get life. And it must occur that there will be very many fish, because there is where this water will certainly come, and the seawater will be healed, and everything will be alive where the torrent comes.

10 “And it must occur that fishers will actually stand alongside it from En-ge′di even up to En-eg′la·im. There will come to be a drying yard for dragnets. In their kinds their fish will prove to be, like the fish of the Great Sea, very many.

11 “There are its swampy places and its marshy places, and they will not be healed. To salt they will certainly be given.

12 “And alongside the torrent there will come up, along its bank on this side and on that side, all sorts of trees for food. Their leafage will not wither, nor will their fruitage be consumed. In their months they will bear new fruit, because the water for them—it is coming forth from the very sanctuary. And their fruitage must prove to be for food and their leafage for healing.”

13 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “This is the territory that YOU will assign to yourselves for inheritance as the land for the twelve tribes of Israel, with two pieces of field to Joseph. 14 And YOU people must inherit it, each one the same as his brother, which land I raised my hand in an oath to give to YOUR forefathers; and this land must fall to YOU by lot for inheritance.

15 “And this is the boundary of the land to the northern side, from the Great Sea by the way to Heth′lon, as one comes to Ze′dad, 16 Ha′math, Be·ro′thah, Sib′ra·im, which is between the boundary of Damascus and the boundary of Ha′math; Ha′zer-hat′ti·con, which is toward the boundary of Ha·u·ran′. 17 And the boundary from the sea must prove to be Ha′zar-e′non, the boundary of Damascus and north—northward, and the boundary of Ha′math. This is the northern side.

18 “And the eastern side is from between Ha·u·ran′ and Damascus and between Gil′e·ad and the land of Israel; the Jordan, from the boundary to the eastern sea YOU people should measure. This is the eastern side.

19 “And the southern side is to the south, from Ta′mar to the waters of Mer′i·bath-ka′desh, the torrent valley to the Great Sea. This is the side to the south, toward the Neg′eb.

20 “And the western side is the Great Sea, from the boundary straight ahead to the entering in to Ha′math. This is the western side.”

21 “And YOU must apportion this land to yourselves, to the twelve tribes of Israel. 22 And it must occur that YOU should allot it for inheritance to yourselves and to the alien residents who are residing as aliens in YOUR midst, who have become father to sons in the midst of YOU. And they must become to YOU like a native among the sons of Israel. With YOU people they will fall by lot into an inheritance in the midst of the tribes of Israel. 23 And it must occur that in the tribe with which the alien resident has taken up residence as an alien, there is where YOU should give his inheritance,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

Daniel

4 “Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king, to all the peoples, national groups and languages that are dwelling in all the earth: May YOUR peace grow great. 2 The signs and wonders that the Most High God has performed with me, it has seemed good to me to declare. 3 How grand his signs are, and how mighty his wonders are! His kingdom is a kingdom to time indefinite, and his rulership is for generation after generation.

4 “I, Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, happened to be at ease in my house and flourishing in my palace. 5 There was a dream that I beheld, and it began to make me afraid. And there were mental images upon my bed and visions of my head that began to frighten me. 6 And from me an order was being put through to bring in before me all the wise men of Babylon, that they might make known to me the very interpretation of the dream.

7 “At that time the magic-practicing priests, the conjurers, the Chal·de′ans and the astrologers were entering; and I was saying before them what the dream was, but its interpretation they were not making known to me. 8 And at last there came in before me Daniel, whose name is Bel·te·shaz′zar according to the name of my god and in whom there is the spirit of the holy gods; and before him I said what the dream was:

9 “‘O Bel·te·shaz′zar the chief of the magic-practicing priests, because I myself well know that the spirit of the holy gods is in you and that there is no secret at all that is troubling you, tell me the visions of my dream that I have beheld and its interpretation.

10 “‘Now the visions of my head upon my bed I happened to be beholding, and, look! a tree in the midst of the earth, the height of which was immense. 11 The tree grew up and became strong, and its very height finally reached the heavens, and it was visible to the extremity of the whole earth. 12 Its foliage was fair, and its fruit was abundant, and there was food for all on it. Under it the beast of the field would seek shade, and on its boughs the birds of the heavens would dwell, and from it all flesh would feed itself.

13 “‘I continued beholding in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, look! a watcher, even a holy one, coming down from the heavens themselves. 14 He was calling out loudly, and this is what he was saying: “CHOP the tree down, and cut off its boughs. SHAKE off its foliage, and scatter its fruitage. Let the beast flee from under it, and the birds from its boughs. 15 However, LEAVE its rootstock itself in the earth, even with a banding of iron and of copper, among the grass of the field; and with the dew of the heavens let it be wet, and with the beast let its portion be among the vegetation of the earth. 16 Let its heart be changed from that of mankind, and let the heart of a beast be given to it, and let seven times pass over it. 17 By the decree of watchers the thing is, and by the saying of holy ones the request is, to the intent that people living may know that the Most High is Ruler in the kingdom of mankind and that to the one whom he wants to, he gives it and he sets up over it even the lowliest one of mankind.”

18 “‘This was the dream that I myself, King Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, beheld; and you yourself, O Bel·te·shaz′zar, say what the interpretation is, forasmuch as all the other wise men of my kingdom are unable to make known to me the interpretation itself. But you are competent, because the spirit of holy gods is in you.’

19 “At that time Daniel himself, whose name is Bel·te·shaz′zar, was astonished for a moment, and his very thoughts began to frighten him.

“The king was answering and saying, ‘O Bel·te·shaz′zar, do not let the dream and the interpretation themselves frighten you.’

“Bel·te·shaz′zar was answering and saying, ‘O my lord, may the dream apply to those hating you, and its interpretation to your adversaries.

20 “‘The tree that you beheld, that grew great and became strong and the height of which finally reached the heavens and which was visible to all the earth, 21 and the foliage of which was fair, and the fruit of which was abundant, and on which there was food for all; under which the beasts of the field would dwell, and on the boughs of which the birds of the heavens would reside, 22 it is you, O king, because you have grown great and become strong, and your grandeur has grown great and reached to the heavens, and your rulership to the extremity of the earth.

23 “‘And because the king beheld a watcher, even a holy one, coming down from the heavens, who was also saying: “CHOP the tree down, and RUIN it. However, LEAVE its rootstock itself in the earth, but with a banding of iron and of copper, among the grass of the field, and with the dew of the heavens let it become wet, and with the beasts of the field let its portion be until seven times themselves pass over it,” 24 this is the interpretation, O king, and the decree of the Most High is that which must befall my lord the king. 25 And you they will be driving away from men, and with the beasts of the field your dwelling will come to be, and the vegetation is what they will give even to you to eat just like bulls; and with the dew of the heavens you yourself will be getting wet, and seven times themselves will pass over you, until you know that the Most High is Ruler in the kingdom of mankind, and that to the one whom he wants to he gives it.

26 “‘And because they said to leave the rootstock of the tree, your kingdom will be sure to you after you know that the heavens are ruling. 27 Therefore, O king, may my counsel seem good to you, and remove your own sins by righteousness, and your iniquity by showing mercy to the poor ones. Maybe there will occur a lengthening of your prosperity.’”

28 All this befell Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king.

29 At the end of twelve lunar months he happened to be walking upon the royal palace of Babylon. 30 The king was answering and saying: “Is not this Babylon the Great, that I myself have built for the royal house with the strength of my might and for the dignity of my majesty?”

31 While the word was yet in the king’s mouth, there was a voice that fell from the heavens: “To you it is being said, O Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king, ‘The kingdom itself has gone away from you, 32 and from mankind they are driving even you away, and with the beasts of the field your dwelling will be. Vegetation they will give even to you to eat just like bulls, and seven times themselves will pass over you, until you know that the Most High is Ruler in the kingdom of mankind, and that to the one whom he wants to he gives it.’”

33 At that moment the word itself was fulfilled upon Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, and from mankind he was being driven away, and vegetation he began to eat just like bulls, and with the dew of the heavens his own body got to be wet, until his very hair grew long just like eagles’ feathers and his nails like birds’ claws.

34 “And at the end of the days I, Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, lifted up to the heavens my eyes, and my own understanding began to return to me; and I blessed the Most High himself, and the One living to time indefinite I praised and glorified, because his rulership is a rulership to time indefinite and his kingdom is for generation after generation. 35 And all the inhabitants of the earth are being considered as merely nothing, and he is doing according to his own will among the army of the heavens and the inhabitants of the earth. And there exists no one that can check his hand or that can say to him, ‘What have you been doing?’

36 “At the same time my understanding itself began to return to me, and for the dignity of my kingdom my majesty and my brightness themselves began to return to me; and for me even my high royal officers and my grandees began eagerly searching, and I was reestablished upon my own kingdom, and greatness extraordinary was added to me.

37 “Now I, Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, am praising and exalting and glorifying the King of the heavens, because all his works are truth and his ways are justice, and because those who are walking in pride he is able to humiliate.”

Daniel

10 In the third year of Cyrus the king of Persia there was a matter revealed to Daniel, whose name was called Bel·te·shaz′zar; and the matter was true, and there was a great military service. And he understood the matter, and he had understanding in the thing seen.

2 In those days I myself, Daniel, happened to be mourning for three full weeks. 3 Dainty bread I did not eat, and no flesh or wine entered into my mouth, and in no way did I grease myself until the completing of the three full weeks. 4 And on the twenty-fourth day of the first month, while I myself happened to be on the bank of the great river, that is, Hid′de·kel, 5 I also proceeded to raise my eyes and see, and here was a certain man clothed in linen, with his hips girded with gold of U′phaz. 6 And his body was like chrys′o·lite, and his face like the appearance of lightning, and his eyes like fiery torches, and his arms and the place of his feet were like the sight of burnished copper, and the sound of his words was like the sound of a crowd. 7 And I saw, I Daniel by myself, the appearance; but as for the men that happened to be with me, they did not see the appearance. However, there was a great trembling that fell upon them, so that they went running away in hiding themselves.

8 And I—I was left remaining by myself, so that I saw this great appearance. And there was left remaining in me no power, and my own dignity became changed upon me to ruination, and I retained no power. 9 And I began hearing the sound of his words; and while I was hearing the sound of his words, I myself also happened to be fast asleep upon my face, with my face to the earth. 10 And, look! there was a hand that touched me, and it gradually stirred me up to get upon my knees and the palms of my hands. 11 And he proceeded to say to me:

“O Daniel, you very desirable man, have understanding in the words that I am speaking to you, and stand up where you were standing, for now I have been sent to you.”

And when he spoke with me this word, I did stand up, shivering.

12 And he went on to say to me: “Do not be afraid, O Daniel, for from the first day that you gave your heart to understanding and humbling yourself before your God your words have been heard, and I myself have come because of your words. 13 But the prince of the royal realm of Persia was standing in opposition to me for twenty-one days, and, look! Mi′cha·el, one of the foremost princes, came to help me; and I, for my part, remained there beside the kings of Persia. 14 And I have come to cause you to discern what will befall your people in the final part of the days, because it is a vision yet for the days to come.”

15 Now when he spoke with me words like these, I had set my face to the earth and had become speechless. 16 And, look! one similar to the likeness of the sons of mankind was touching my lips, and I began to open my mouth and speak and say to the one who was standing in front of me: “O my lord, because of the appearance my convulsions were turned within me, and I did not retain any power. 17 So how was the servant of this my lord able to speak with this my lord? And as for me, up to now there kept standing in me no power, and no breath at all was left remaining in me.”

18 And the one like the appearance of an earthling man proceeded to touch me again and strengthen me. 19 Then he said: “Do not be afraid, O very desirable man. May you have peace. Be strong, yes, be strong.” And as soon as he spoke with me I exerted my strength and finally said: “Let my lord speak, because you have strengthened me.” 20 So he went on to say:

“Do you really know why I have come to you? And now I shall go back to fight with the prince of Persia. When I am going forth, look! also the prince of Greece is coming. 21 However, I shall tell you the things noted down in the writing of truth, and there is no one holding strongly with me in these things but Mi′cha·el, the prince of YOU people.

Daniel

11 “And as for me, in the first year of Da·ri′us the Mede I stood up as a strengthener and as a fortress to him. 2 And now what is truth I shall tell to you:

“Look! There will yet be three kings standing up for Persia, and the fourth one will amass greater riches than all others. And as soon as he has become strong in his riches, he will rouse up everything against the kingdom of Greece.

3 “And a mighty king will certainly stand up and rule with extensive dominion and do according to his will. 4 And when he will have stood up, his kingdom will be broken and be divided toward the four winds of the heavens, but not to his posterity and not according to his dominion with which he had ruled; because his kingdom will be uprooted, even for others than these.

5 “And the king of the south will become strong, even one of his princes; and he will prevail against him and will certainly rule with extensive dominion greater than that one’s ruling power.

6 “And at the end of some years they will ally themselves with each other, and the very daughter of the king of the south will come to the king of the north in order to make an equitable arrangement. But she will not retain the power of her arm; and he will not stand, neither his arm; and she will be given up, she herself, and those bringing her in, and he who caused her birth, and the one making her strong in those times. 7 And one from the sprout of her roots will certainly stand up in his position, and he will come to the military force and come against the fortress of the king of the north and will certainly act against them and prevail. 8 And also with their gods, with their molten images, with their desirable articles of silver and of gold, and with the captives he will come to Egypt. And he himself will for some years stand off from the king of the north.

9 “And he will actually come into the kingdom of the king of the south and go back to his own soil.

10 “Now as for his sons, they will excite themselves and actually gather together a crowd of large military forces. And in coming he will certainly come and flood over and pass through. But he will go back, and he will excite himself all the way to his fortress.

11 “And the king of the south will embitter himself and will have to go forth and fight with him, that is, with the king of the north; and he will certainly have a large crowd stand up, and the crowd will actually be given into the hand of that one. 12 And the crowd will certainly be carried away. His heart will become exalted, and he will actually cause tens of thousands to fall; but he will not use his strong position.

13 “And the king of the north must return and set up a crowd larger than the first; and at the end of the times, some years, he will come, doing so with a great military force and with a great deal of goods. 14 And in those times there will be many who will stand up against the king of the south.

“And the sons of the robbers belonging to your people will, for their part, be carried along to try making a vision come true; and they will have to stumble.

15 “And the king of the north will come and throw up a siege rampart and actually capture a city with fortifications. And as for the arms of the south, they will not stand, neither the people of his picked ones; and there will be no power to keep standing. 16 And the one coming against him will do according to his will, and there will be no one standing before him. And he will stand in the land of the Decoration, and there will be extermination in his hand. 17 And he will set his face to come with the forcefulness of his entire kingdom, and there will be equitable terms with him; and he will act effectively. And as regards the daughter of womankind, it will be granted to him to bring her to ruin. And she will not stand, and she will not continue to be his. 18 And he will turn his face back to the coastlands and will actually capture many. And a commander will have to make the reproach from him cease for himself, so that his reproach will not be. He will make it turn back upon that one. 19 And he will turn his face back to the fortresses of his own land, and he will certainly stumble and fall, and he will not be found.

20 “And there must stand up in his position one who is causing an exactor to pass through the splendid kingdom, and in a few days he will be broken, but not in anger nor in warfare.

21 “And there must stand up in his position one who is to be despised, and they will certainly not set upon him the dignity of the kingdom; and he will actually come in during a freedom from care and take hold of the kingdom by means of smoothness. 22 And as regards the arms of the flood, they will be flooded over on account of him, and they will be broken; as will also the Leader of the covenant. 23 And because of their allying themselves with him he will carry on deception and actually come up and become mighty by means of a little nation. 24 During freedom from care, even into the fatness of the jurisdictional district he will enter in and actually do what his fathers and the fathers of his fathers have not done. Plunder and spoil and goods he will scatter among them; and against fortified places he will scheme out his schemes, but only until a time.

25 “And he will arouse his power and his heart against the king of the south with a great military force; and the king of the south, for his part, will excite himself for the war with an exceedingly great and mighty military force. And he will not stand, because they will scheme out against him schemes. 26 And the very ones eating his delicacies will bring his breakdown.

“And as for his military force, it will be flooded away, and many will certainly fall down slain.

27 “And as regards these two kings, their heart will be inclined to doing what is bad, and at one table a lie is what they will keep speaking. But nothing will succeed, because the end is yet for the time appointed.

28 “And he will go back to his land with a great amount of goods, and his heart will be against the holy covenant. And he will act effectively and certainly go back to his land.

29 “At the time appointed he will go back, and he will actually come against the south; but it will not prove to be at the last the same as at the first. 30 And there will certainly come against him the ships of Kit′tim, and he will have to become dejected.

“And he will actually go back and hurl denunciations against the holy covenant and act effectively; and he will have to go back and will give consideration to those leaving the holy covenant. 31 And there will be arms that will stand up, proceeding from him; and they will actually profane the sanctuary, the fortress, and remove the constant feature.

“And they will certainly put in place the disgusting thing that is causing desolation.

32 “And those who are acting wickedly against the covenant, he will lead into apostasy by means of smooth words. But as regards the people who are knowing their God, they will prevail and act effectively. 33 And as regards those having insight among the people, they will impart understanding to the many. And they will certainly be made to stumble by sword and by flame, by captivity and by plundering, for some days. 34 But when they are made to stumble they will be helped with a little help; and many will certainly join themselves to them by means of smoothness. 35 And some of those having insight will be made to stumble, in order to do a refining work because of them and to do a cleansing and to do a whitening, until the time of the end; because it is yet for the time appointed.

36 “And the king will actually do according to his own will, and he will exalt himself and magnify himself above every god; and against the God of gods he will speak marvelous things. And he will certainly prove successful until the denunciation will have come to a finish; because the thing decided upon must be done. 37 And to the God of his fathers he will give no consideration; and to the desire of women and to every other god he will give no consideration, but over everyone he will magnify himself. 38 But to the god of fortresses, in his position he will give glory; and to a god that his fathers did not know he will give glory by means of gold and by means of silver and by means of precious stone and by means of desirable things. 39 And he will act effectively against the most fortified strongholds, along with a foreign god. Whoever has given him recognition he will make abound with glory, and he will actually make them rule among many; and the ground he will apportion out for a price.

40 “And in the time of the end the king of the south will engage with him in a pushing, and against him the king of the north will storm with chariots and with horsemen and with many ships; and he will certainly enter into the lands and flood over and pass through. 41 He will also actually enter into the land of the Decoration, and there will be many lands that will be made to stumble. But these are the ones that will escape out of his hand, E′dom and Mo′ab and the main part of the sons of Am′mon. 42 And he will keep thrusting out his hand against the lands; and as regards the land of Egypt, she will not prove to be an escapee. 43 And he will actually rule over the hidden treasures of the gold and the silver and over all the desirable things of Egypt. And the Lib′y·ans and the E·thi·o′pi·ans will be at his steps.

44 “But there will be reports that will disturb him, out of the sunrising and out of the north, and he will certainly go forth in a great rage in order to annihilate and to devote many to destruction. 45 And he will plant his palatial tents between the grand sea and the holy mountain of Decoration; and he will have to come all the way to his end, and there will be no helper for him.

Daniel

12 “And during that time Mi′cha·el will stand up, the great prince who is standing in behalf of the sons of your people. And there will certainly occur a time of distress such as has not been made to occur since there came to be a nation until that time. And during that time your people will escape, every one who is found written down in the book. 2 And there will be many of those asleep in the ground of dust who will wake up, these to indefinitely lasting life and those to reproaches and to indefinitely lasting abhorrence.

3 “And the ones having insight will shine like the brightness of the expanse; and those who are bringing the many to righteousness, like the stars to time indefinite, even forever.

4 “And as for you, O Daniel, make secret the words and seal up the book, until the time of the end. Many will rove about, and the true knowledge will become abundant.”

5 And I saw, I Daniel, and, look! there were two others standing, one on the bank here of the stream and the other on the bank there of the stream. 6 Then one said to the man clothed with the linen, who was up above the waters of the stream: “How long will it be to the end of the wonderful things?” 7 And I began to hear the man clothed with the linen, who was up above the waters of the stream, as he proceeded to raise his right hand and his left hand to the heavens and to swear by the One who is alive for time indefinite: “It will be for an appointed time, appointed times and a half. And as soon as there will have been a finishing of the dashing of the power of the holy people to pieces, all these things will come to their finish.”

8 Now as for me, I heard, but I could not understand; so that I said: “O my lord, what will be the final part of these things?”

9 And he went on to say: “Go, Daniel, because the words are made secret and sealed up until the time of the end. 10 Many will cleanse themselves and whiten themselves and will be refined. And the wicked ones will certainly act wickedly, and no wicked ones at all will understand; but the ones having insight will understand.

11 “And from the time that the constant feature has been removed and there has been a placing of the disgusting thing that is causing desolation, there will be one thousand two hundred and ninety days.

12 “Happy is the one who is keeping in expectation and who arrives at the one thousand three hundred and thirty-five days!

13 “And as for you yourself, go toward the end; and you will rest, but you will stand up for your lot at the end of the days.”

Hosea

2 “SAY to YOUR brothers, ‘My people!’ and to YOUR sisters, ‘O woman shown mercy!’ 2 Carry on a legal case with YOUR mother; carry on a legal case, for she is not my wife and I am not her husband. And she should put away her fornication from before herself and her acts of adultery from between her breasts, 3 that I may not strip her naked and actually place her as in the day of her being born, and actually set her like a wilderness and place her like a waterless land and put her to death with thirst. 4 And to her sons I shall not show mercy, for they are the sons of fornication. 5 For their mother has committed fornication. She that was pregnant with them has acted shamefully, for she has said, ‘I want to go after those passionately loving me, those giving my bread and my water, my wool and my linen, my oil and my drink.’

6 “Therefore here I am hedging your way about with thorns; and I will heap up a stone wall against her, so that her own roadways she will not find. 7 And she will actually chase after her passionate lovers, but she will not overtake them; and she will certainly look for them, but she will not find them. And she will have to say, ‘I want to go and return to my husband, the first one, for I had it better at that time than now.’ 8 But she herself did not recognize that it was I who had given to her the grain and the sweet wine and the oil, and that I had made silver itself abound for her, and gold, which they made use of for Ba′al.

9 “‘Therefore I shall turn back and certainly take away my grain in its time and my sweet wine in its season, and I will snatch away my wool and my linen for covering her nakedness. 10 And now I shall uncover her private parts to the eyes of her passionate lovers, and there will be no man to snatch her out of my hand. 11 And I shall certainly cause all her exultation, her festival, her new moon and her sabbath and her every festal season to cease. 12 And I will lay desolate her vine and her fig tree, of which she has said: “They are a gift to me, which my passionate lovers have given to me”; and I will set them as a forest, and the wild beast of the field will certainly devour them. 13 And I will hold an accounting against her for the days of the Ba′al images to which she kept making sacrificial smoke, when she kept decking herself with her ring and her ornament and kept going after her passionate lovers, and I was the one that she forgot,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

14 “‘Therefore here I am prevailing upon her, and I will cause her to go into the wilderness, and I will speak to her heart. 15 And I will give her her vineyards from then onward, and the low plain of A′chor as an entrance to hope; and she will certainly answer there as in the days of her youth and as in the day of her coming up out of the land of Egypt. 16 And it must occur in that day,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘that you will call me My husband, and you will no longer call me My owner.’

17 “‘And I will remove the names of the Ba′al images from her mouth, and they will no longer be remembered by their name. 18 And for them I shall certainly conclude a covenant in that day in connection with the wild beast of the field and with the flying creature of the heavens and the creeping thing of the ground, and the bow and the sword and war I shall break out of the land, and I will make them lie down in security. 19 And I will engage you to me for time indefinite, and I will engage you to me in righteousness and in justice and in loving-kindness and in mercies. 20 And I will engage you to me in faithfulness; and you will certainly know Jehovah.’

21 “‘And it must occur in that day that I shall answer,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘I shall answer the heavens, and they, for their part, will answer the earth; 22 and the earth, for its part, will answer the grain and the sweet wine and the oil; and they, for their part, will answer Jez′re·el [‘God will sow seed’]. 23 And I shall certainly sow her like seed for me in the earth, and I will show mercy to her who was not shown mercy, and I will say to those not my people: “You are my people”; and they, for their part, will say: “You are my God.”’”

Hosea

12 “E′phra·im is feeding on wind and chasing after the east wind all day long. Lying and despoiling are what he multiplies. And a covenant with As·syr′i·a they conclude, and to Egypt oil itself is brought.

2 “And Jehovah has a legal case with Judah, even to hold an accounting against Jacob according to his ways; according to his dealings he will repay him. 3 In the belly he seized his brother by the heel, and with his dynamic energy he contended with God. 4 And he kept contending with an angel and gradually prevailed. He wept, that he might implore favor for himself.”

At Beth′el He got to find him, and there He began talking with us. 5 And Jehovah the God of the armies, Jehovah is his memorial.

6 “And as respects you, to your God you should return, keeping loving-kindness and justice; and let there be a hoping in your God constantly. 7 As regards the tradesman, in his hand are the scales of deception; to defraud is what he has loved. 8 And E′phra·im keeps saying, ‘Indeed, I have become rich; I have found valuable things for myself. As regards all my toiling, they will find, on my part, no error that is sin.’

9 “But I am Jehovah your God from the land of Egypt. Yet I shall make you dwell in the tents as in the days of an appointed time. 10 And I spoke to the prophets, and visions I myself multiplied, and by the hand of the prophets I kept making likenesses.

11 “With Gil′e·ad what is uncanny, also untruth, have occurred. In Gil′gal they have sacrificed even bulls. Moreover, their altars are like piles of stones in the furrows of the open field. 12 And Jacob proceeded to run away to the field of Syria, and Israel kept serving for a wife, and for a wife he guarded sheep. 13 And by a prophet Jehovah brought up Israel out of Egypt, and by a prophet he was guarded. 14 E′phra·im caused offense to bitterness, and his deeds of bloodshed he leaves upon his own self, and his reproach his Grand Master will repay to him.”

Hosea

14 “Do come back, O Israel, to Jehovah your God, for you have stumbled in your error. 2 Take with yourselves words and come back to Jehovah. Say to him, all YOU people, ‘May you pardon error; and accept what is good, and we will offer in return the young bulls of our lips. 3 As·syr′i·a itself will not save us. Upon horses we shall not ride. And no more shall we say: “O our God!” to the work of our hands, because it is by you that a fatherless boy is shown mercy.’

4 “I shall heal their unfaithfulness. I shall love them of my own free will, because my anger has turned back from him. 5 I shall become like the dew to Israel. He will blossom like the lily, and will strike his roots like Leb′a·non. 6 His twigs will go forth, and his dignity will become like that of the olive tree, and his fragrance will be like that of Leb′a·non. 7 They will again be dwellers in his shadow. They will grow grain, and will bud like the vine. His memorial will be like the wine of Leb′a·non.

8 “E′phra·im will say, ‘What do I have to do any longer with the idols?’

“I myself shall certainly give an answer and I shall keep looking on him. I am like a luxuriant juniper tree. From me must fruit for you be found.”

9 Who is wise, that he may understand these things? Discreet, that he may know them? For the ways of Jehovah are upright, and the righteous are the ones who will walk in them; but the transgressors are the ones who will stumble in them.

Amos

2 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘“On account of three revolts of Mo′ab, and on account of four, I shall not turn it back, on account of his burning the bones of the king of E′dom for lime. 2 And I will send a fire into Mo′ab, and it must devour the dwelling towers of Ke′ri·oth; and with noise Mo′ab must die, with an alarm signal, with the sound of a horn. 3 And I will cut off the judge from the midst of her, and all her princes I shall kill with him,” Jehovah has said.’

4 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘On account of three revolts of Judah, and on account of four, I shall not turn it back, on account of their rejecting the law of Jehovah, and because they did not keep his own regulations; but their lies, after which their forefathers had walked, kept making them wander. 5 And I will send a fire into Judah, and it must devour the dwelling towers of Jerusalem.’

6 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘On account of three revolts of Israel, and on account of four, I shall not turn it back, on account of their selling someone righteous for mere silver, and someone poor for the price of a pair of sandals. 7 They are panting for the dust of the earth on the head of lowly persons; and the way of meek people they turn aside; and a man and his own father have gone to the same girl, for the purpose of profaning my holy name. 8 And on garments seized as a pledge they stretch themselves out beside every altar; and the wine of those who have been fined they drink at the house of their gods.’

9 “‘But as for me, I had annihilated the Am′or·ite on account of them, whose height was like the height of cedars, and who was vigorous like the massive trees; and I went annihilating his fruitage above and his roots below. 10 And I myself brought YOU people up out of the land of Egypt, and I kept making YOU walk through the wilderness forty years, in order to take possession of the land of the Am′or·ite. 11 And I kept raising up some of YOUR sons as prophets and some of YOUR young men as Naz′i·rites. Should this really not be, O sons of Israel?’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

12 “‘But YOU kept giving the Naz′i·rites wine to drink, and upon the prophets YOU laid a command, saying: “YOU must not prophesy.” 13 Here I am making what is under YOU sway, just as the wagon sways that is full up with a row of newly cut grain. 14 And a place to which to flee must perish from the swift one, and no one strong will reinforce his power, and no mighty man will provide his soul with escape. 15 And no one handling the bow will stand, and no one swift on his feet will escape, and no rider of the horse will provide his soul with escape. 16 And as for one strong in his heart among the mighty men, naked is how he will flee in that day,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

Amos

4 “Hear this word, YOU cows of Ba′shan, who are on the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a, who are defrauding the lowly ones, who are crushing the poor ones, who are saying to their masters, ‘Do bring, and let us drink!’ 2 The Sovereign Lord Jehovah has sworn by his holiness, ‘“Look! There are days coming upon YOU, and he will certainly lift YOU up with butcher hooks and the last part of YOU with fishhooks. 3 And by breaches YOU will go forth, each one straight ahead; and YOU will certainly be thrown out to Har′mon,” is the utterance of Jehovah.’

4 “‘Come, YOU people, to Beth′el and commit transgression. At Gil′gal be frequent in committing transgression, and bring YOUR sacrifices in the morning; on the third day, YOUR tenth parts. 5 And from what is leavened make a thanksgiving sacrifice to smoke, and proclaim voluntary offerings; publish it, for that is the way YOU have loved, O sons of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

6 “‘And I also, for my part, gave YOU people cleanness of teeth in all YOUR cities and want of bread in all YOUR places; but YOU did not come back to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

7 “‘And as for me, I also withheld from YOU people the downpour when there were yet three months to the harvest; and I made it rain on one city, but on another city I would not make it rain. There was one tract of land that would be rained on, but a tract of land on which I would not make it rain would be dried up. 8 And two or three cities staggered to one city in order to drink water, and they would not get satisfied; but YOU did not come back to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

9 “‘I struck YOU people with scorching and mildew. There was a multiplying of YOUR gardens and of YOUR vineyards, but YOUR fig trees and YOUR olive trees the caterpillar would devour; yet YOU did not come back to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

10 “‘I sent among YOU people a pestilence in the nature of that of Egypt. With the sword I killed YOUR young men, along with the taking captive of YOUR horses. And I kept making the stink of YOUR camps ascend even into YOUR nostrils; but YOU did not come back to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

11 “‘I caused an overthrow among YOU people, like God’s overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah. And YOU came to be like a log snatched out of the burning; but YOU did not come back to me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

12 “Therefore that is what I shall do to you, O Israel. As a consequence of the fact that I shall do this very thing to you, get ready to meet your God, O Israel. 13 For, look! the Former of the mountains and the Creator of the wind, and the One telling to earthling man what his mental concern is, the One making dawn into obscurity, and the One treading on earth’s high places, Jehovah the God of armies is his name.”

Amos

5 “Hear this word that I am taking up over YOU people as a dirge, O house of Israel:

2 “The virgin, Israel, has fallen;

She cannot get up again.

She has been forsaken upon her own ground;

There is no one raising her up.

3 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘The very city that was going forth with a thousand will have a hundred left; and the one going forth with a hundred will have ten left, for the house of Israel.’

4 “For this is what Jehovah has said to the house of Israel, ‘Search for me, and keep living. 5 And do not search for Beth′el, and to Gil′gal YOU must not come, and to Be′er-she′ba YOU must not pass over; because Gil′gal itself will without fail go into exile; and as regards Beth′el, it will become something uncanny. 6 Search for Jehovah, and keep living, that he may not become operative just like fire, O house of Joseph, and it may not actually devour, and Beth′el may not be with no one to extinguish it, 7 O YOU who are turning justice into mere wormwood, and the ones who have cast righteousness itself to the earth. 8 The Maker of the Ki′mah constellation and the Ke′sil constellation, and the One turning deep shadow into the morning itself, and the One who has made day itself dark as night, the One calling for the waters of the sea, that he may pour them out upon the surface of the earth—Jehovah is his name; 9 he who is causing a despoiling to flash forth upon someone strong, that despoiling itself may come upon even a fortified place.

10 “‘In the gate they have hated a reprover, and a speaker of perfect things they detest. 11 Therefore, for the reason that YOU are extracting farm rent from someone lowly, and the tribute of grain YOU keep taking from him; houses of hewn stone YOU have built, but YOU will not keep dwelling in them; and desirable vineyards YOU have planted, but YOU will not keep drinking the wine of them. 12 For I have known how many YOUR revolts are and how mighty YOUR sins are, O YOU who are showing hostility toward someone righteous, YOU who are taking hush money, and the ones who have turned aside poor people even in the gate. 13 Therefore the very one having insight will in that time keep silent, for it will be a calamitous time.

14 “‘Search for what is good, and not what is bad, to the end that YOU people may keep living; and that thus Jehovah the God of armies may come to be with YOU, just as YOU have said. 15 Hate what is bad, and love what is good, and give justice a place in the gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

16 “Therefore this is what Jehovah the God of armies, Jehovah, has said, ‘In all the public squares there will be wailing, and in all the streets people will be saying: “Ah! Ah!” And they will have to call a farmer to mourning, and to wailing those experienced in lamentation.’ 17 ‘And in all vineyards there will be wailing; for I shall pass through the midst of you,’ Jehovah has said.

18 “‘Woe to those who are craving the day of Jehovah! What, then, will the day of Jehovah mean to YOU people? It will be darkness, and no light, 19 just as when a man flees because of the lion, and the bear actually meets him; and as when he went into the house and supported his hand against the wall, and the serpent bit him. 20 Will not the day of Jehovah be darkness, and not light; and will it not have gloom, and not brightness? 21 I have hated, I have rejected YOUR festivals, and I shall not enjoy the smell of YOUR solemn assemblies. 22 But if YOU people offer up to me whole burnt offerings, even in YOUR gift offerings I shall find no pleasure, and on YOUR communion sacrifices of fatlings I shall not look. 23 Remove from me the turmoil of your songs; and the melodious sound of your stringed instruments may I not hear. 24 And let justice roll forth just like waters, and righteousness like a constantly flowing torrent. 25 Was it sacrifices and gift offerings that YOU people brought near to me in the wilderness for forty years, O house of Israel? 26 And YOU will certainly carry Sak′kuth YOUR king and Kai′wan, YOUR images, the star of YOUR god, whom YOU made for yourselves. 27 And I will cause YOU to go into exile beyond Damascus,’ he whose name is Jehovah the God of armies has said.”

Amos

8 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah caused me to see, and, look! there was a basket of summer fruit. 2 Then he said: “What are you seeing, A′mos?” So I said: “A basket of summer fruit.” And Jehovah went on to say to me: “The end has come to my people Israel. I shall no more do any further excusing of them. 3 ‘And the songs of the temple will actually be a howling in that day,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘There will be many a carcass. In every place one will certainly throw them out—hush!’

4 “Hear this, YOU men snapping at someone poor, even in order to cause the meek ones of the earth to cease, 5 saying, ‘How long will it be before the new moon passes and we may sell cereals? Also, the sabbath, and we may offer grain for sale; in order to make the e′phah small and to make the shekel great and to falsify the scales of deception; 6 in order to buy lowly people for mere silver and someone poor for the price of a pair of sandals, and that we may sell mere refuse of grain?’

7 “Jehovah has sworn by the Superiority of Jacob, ‘Never will I forget all their works. 8 Will it not be on this account that the land will be agitated, and every inhabitant in it will have to mourn; and it will, all of it, certainly come up just like the Nile and be tossed and sink down like the Nile of Egypt?’

9 “‘And it must occur in that day,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘that I will make the sun go down at high noon, and I will cause darkness for the land on a bright day. 10 And I will turn YOUR festivals into mourning and all YOUR songs into a dirge, and I will bring up upon all hips sackcloth and upon every head baldness; and I will make the situation like the mourning for an only son, and the end result of it as a bitter day.’

11 “‘Look! There are days coming,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and I will send a famine into the land, a famine, not for bread, and a thirst, not for water, but for hearing the words of Jehovah. 12 And they will certainly stagger from sea all the way to sea, and from north even to the sunrise. They will keep roving about while searching for the word of Jehovah, but they will not find it. 13 In that day the pretty virgins will swoon away, also the young men, because of the thirst; 14 those who are swearing by the guiltiness of Sa·mar′i·a, and who actually say: “As your god is alive, O Dan!” and, “As the way of Be′er-she′ba is alive!” And they will certainly fall, and they will rise up no more.’”

Amos

9 I saw Jehovah stationed above the altar, and he proceeded to say: “Strike the pillar head, so that the thresholds will rock. And cut them off at the head, all of them. And the last part of them I shall kill with the sword itself. No one fleeing of them will make good his flight, and no one escaping of them will make his getaway. 2 If they dig down into She′ol, from there my own hand will take them; and if they go up to the heavens, from there I shall bring them down. 3 And if they hide themselves on the top of Car′mel, from there I shall carefully search and be certain to take them. And if they conceal themselves from in front of my eyes on the floor of the sea, down there I shall command the serpent, and it must bite them. 4 And if they go into captivity before their enemies, from there I shall command the sword, and it must kill them; and I will set my eyes upon them for bad, and not for good. 5 And the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of the armies, is the One touching the land, so that it melts; and all the inhabitants in it will have to mourn; and it will certainly come up like the Nile, all of it, and sink down like the Nile of Egypt.

6 “‘He who is building in the heavens his stairs, and his structure over the earth that he founded; he who is calling for the waters of the sea, that he may pour them out upon the surface of the earth—Jehovah is his name.’

7 “‘Are YOU not like the sons of the Cush′ites to me, O sons of Israel?’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘Did I not bring Israel itself up out of the land of Egypt, and the Phi·lis′tines out of Crete, and Syria out of Kir?’

8 “‘Look! The eyes of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah are upon the sinful kingdom, and he will certainly annihilate it from upon the surface of the ground. Nevertheless, I shall not completely annihilate the house of Jacob,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 9 ‘For, look! I am commanding, and I will jiggle the house of Israel among all the nations, just as one jiggles the sieve, so that not a pebble falls to the earth. 10 By the sword they will die—all the sinners of my people, those who are saying: “The calamity will not come near or reach as far as us.”’

11 “‘In that day I shall raise up the booth of David that is fallen, and I shall certainly repair their breaches. And its ruins I shall raise up, and I shall certainly build it up as in the days of long ago, 12 to the end that they may take possession of what is left remaining of E′dom, and all the nations upon whom my name has been called,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, who is doing this.

13 “‘Look! There are days coming,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and the plowman will actually overtake the harvester, and the treader of grapes, the carrier of the seed; and the mountains must drip with sweet wine, and the very hills will all find themselves melting. 14 And I will gather back the captive ones of my people Israel, and they will actually build the desolated cities and inhabit them, and plant vineyards and drink the wine of them, and make gardens and eat the fruit of them.’

15 “‘And I shall certainly plant them upon their ground, and they will no more be uprooted from their ground that I have given them,’ Jehovah your God has said.”

Jonah

1 And the word of Jehovah began to occur to Jo′nah the son of A·mit′tai, saying: 2 “Get up, go to Nin′e·veh the great city, and proclaim against her that their badness has come up before me.”

3 And Jo′nah proceeded to get up and run away to Tar′shish from before Jehovah; and he finally came down to Jop′pa and found a ship going to Tar′shish. So he paid its fare and went down into it, in order to go with them to Tar′shish from before Jehovah.

4 And Jehovah himself hurled forth a great wind at the sea, and there came to be a great tempest on the sea; and as for the ship, it was about to be wrecked. 5 And the mariners began to fear and to call for aid, each one to his god. And they kept hurling out the articles that were in the ship to the sea, in order to lighten it of them. But Jo′nah himself had gone down to the innermost parts of the decked vessel, and he proceeded to lie down and go fast asleep. 6 At length the ship captain came near to him and said to him: “What is the matter with you, sleeper? Get up, call out to your god! Perhaps the true God will show himself caring about us, and we shall not perish.”

7 And they began to say to one another: “Come, and let us cast lots, that we may know on whose account we have this calamity.” And they kept casting lots, and finally the lot fell upon Jo′nah. 8 So they said to him: “Do tell us, please, on whose account it is that we are having this calamity? What is your work, and from where do you come? What is your country, and from which people are you?”

9 At that he said to them: “I am a Hebrew, and Jehovah the God of the heavens I am fearing, the One who made the sea and the dry land.”

10 And the men began to fear greatly, and they went on to say to him: “What is this that you have done?” For the men had come to know that it was from before Jehovah that he was running away, because he had told them. 11 Finally they said to him: “What should we do to you, in order that the sea may become still for us?” For the sea was continually growing more tempestuous. 12 So he said to them: “Lift me up and hurl me into the sea, and the sea will become still for YOU; because I am aware that it is on my account that this great tempest is upon YOU.” 13 But the men tried to work their way through, in order to bring the ship back to the dry land; yet they were unable, because the sea was continually growing more tempestuous against them.

14 And they proceeded to call out to Jehovah and to say: “Ah, now, O Jehovah, may we, please, not perish because of the soul of this man! And do not put upon us innocent blood, since you yourself, O Jehovah, have done according to what you have delighted in!” 15 Then they lifted up Jo′nah and hurled him into the sea; and the sea began to halt from its raging. 16 At that the men began to fear Jehovah greatly, and so they offered a sacrifice to Jehovah and made vows.

17 Now Jehovah appointed a great fish to swallow Jo′nah, so that Jo′nah came to be in the inward parts of the fish three days and three nights.

Jonah

4 To Jo′nah, though, it was highly displeasing, and he got to be hot with anger. 2 Hence he prayed to Jehovah and said: “Ah, now, O Jehovah, was not this an affair of mine, while I happened to be on my own ground? That is why I went ahead and ran away to Tar′shish; for I knew that you are a God gracious and merciful, slow to anger and abundant in loving-kindness, and feeling regret over the calamity. 3 And now, O Jehovah, take away, please, my soul from me, for my dying is better than my being alive.”

4 In turn Jehovah said: “Have you rightly become hot with anger?”

5 Then Jo′nah went out of the city and sat down east of the city; and gradually he made for himself there a booth, that he might sit under it in the shade until he would see what would become of the city. 6 Accordingly Jehovah God appointed a bottle-gourd plant, that it should come up over Jo′nah, in order to become a shade over his head, to deliver him from his calamitous state. And Jo′nah began to rejoice greatly over the bottle-gourd plant.

7 But the true God appointed a worm at the ascending of the dawn on the next day, that it should strike the bottle-gourd plant; and it gradually dried up. 8 And it came about that, as soon as the sun shone forth, God also went on to appoint a parching east wind, and the sun kept striking upon the head of Jo′nah, so that he was swooning away; and he kept asking that his soul might die, and he repeatedly said: “My dying off is better than my being alive.”

9 And God proceeded to say to Jo′nah: “Have you rightly become hot with anger over the bottle-gourd plant?”

At that he said: “I have rightly become hot with anger, to the point of death.” 10 But Jehovah said: “You, for your part, felt sorry for the bottle-gourd plant, which you did not toil upon or make get big, which proved to be a mere growth of a night and perished as a mere growth of a night. 11 And, for my part, ought I not to feel sorry for Nin′e·veh the great city, in which there exist more than one hundred and twenty thousand men who do not at all know the difference between their right hand and their left, besides many domestic animals?”

Nahum

1 The pronouncement against Nin′e·veh: The book of the vision of Na′hum the El′kosh·ite:

2 Jehovah is a God exacting exclusive devotion and taking vengeance; Jehovah is taking vengeance and is disposed to rage. Jehovah is taking vengeance against his adversaries, and he is resentful toward his enemies.

3 Jehovah is slow to anger and great in power, and by no means will Jehovah hold back from punishing.

In destructive wind and in storm is his way, and the cloud mass is the powder of his feet.

4 He is rebuking the sea, and he dries it up; and all the rivers he actually makes run dry.

Ba′shan and Car′mel have withered, and the very blossom of Leb′a·non has withered.

5 Mountains themselves have rocked because of him, and the very hills found themselves melting.

And the earth will be upheaved because of his face; the productive land also, and all those dwelling in it.

6 In the face of his denunciation who can stand? And who can rise up against the heat of his anger?

His own rage will certainly be poured out like fire, and the very rocks will actually be pulled down because of him.

7 Jehovah is good, a stronghold in the day of distress.

And he is cognizant of those seeking refuge in him.

8 And by the flood that is passing along he will make an outright extermination of her place, and darkness will pursue his very enemies.

9 What will YOU men think up against Jehovah? He is causing an outright extermination.

Distress will not rise up a second time.

10 Although they are being interwoven even as thorns and they are drunken as with their wheat beer, they will certainly be devoured like stubble fully dry.

11 Out of you there will actually go forth one who is thinking up against Jehovah what is bad, counseling what is not worth while.

12 This is what Jehovah has said: “Although they were in complete form and there were many in that state, even in that state they must be cut down; and one must pass through. And I shall certainly afflict you, so that I shall not afflict you anymore. 13 And now I shall break his carrying bar from upon you, and the bands upon you I shall tear in two. 14 And concerning you Jehovah has commanded, ‘Nothing of your name will be sown anymore. Out of the house of your gods I shall cut off carved image and molten statue. I shall make a burial place for you, because you have been of no account.’

15 “Look! Upon the mountains the feet of one bringing good news, one publishing peace. O Judah, celebrate your festivals. Pay your vows; because no more will any good-for-nothing person pass again through you. In his entirety he will certainly be cut off.”

Nahum

2 One that does a scattering has come up before your face. Let there be a safeguarding of the fortified place. Watch the way. Strengthen the hips. Reinforce power very much.

2 For Jehovah will certainly gather the pride of Jacob, like the pride of Israel, because those emptying out have emptied them out; and the shoots of them they have ruined.

3 The shield of his mighty men is dyed red; his men of vital energy are dressed in crimson stuff. With the fire of iron fittings is the war chariot in the day of his getting ready, and the juniper tree spears have been made to quiver. 4 In the streets the war chariots keep driving madly. They keep rushing up and down in the public squares. Their appearances are like torches. Like the lightnings they keep running.

5 He will remember his majestic ones. They will stumble in their walking. They will hasten to her wall, and the barricade will have to be firmly established. 6 The very gates of the rivers will certainly be opened, and the palace itself will actually be dissolved. 7 And it has been fixed; she has been uncovered; she will certainly be carried away, and her slave girls will be moaning, like the sound of doves, beating repeatedly upon their hearts. 8 And Nin′e·veh, from the days that she has been, was like a pool of waters; but they are fleeing. “Stand still, YOU men! Stand still!” But there is no one turning back.

9 Plunder silver, YOU men; plunder gold; as there is no limit to the things in arrangement. There is a heavy amount of all sorts of desirable articles.

10 Emptiness and voidness, and a city laid waste! And the heart is melting, and there is a tottering of the knees, and severe pains are in all hips; and as for the faces of all of them, they have collected a glow of excitement. 11 Where is the lair of lions, and the cave that belongs to the maned young lions, where the lion walked and entered, where the lion’s cub was, and no one was making them tremble? 12 The lion was tearing to pieces enough for his whelps, and was strangling for his lionesses. And he kept his holes filled with prey and his hiding places with animals torn to pieces.

13 “Look! I am against you,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, “and I will burn up her war chariot in the smoke. And a sword will devour your own maned young lions. And I will cut off from the earth your prey, and no more will the voice of your messengers be heard.”

Zephaniah

1 The word of Jehovah that occurred to Zeph·a·ni′ah the son of Cush′i the son of Ged·a·li′ah the son of Am·a·ri′ah the son of Hez·e·ki′ah in the days of Jo·si′ah the son of A′mon the king of Judah:

2 “I shall without fail finish everything off the surface of the ground,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

3 “I shall finish off earthling man and beast. I shall finish off the flying creature of the heavens and the fishes of the sea, and the stumbling blocks with the wicked ones; and I will cut off mankind from the surface of the ground,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 4 “And I will stretch out my hand against Judah and against all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and I will cut off from this place the remaining ones of the Ba′al, the name of the foreign-god priests along with the priests, 5 and those who are bowing down upon the roofs to the army of the heavens, and those who are bowing down, making sworn oaths to Jehovah and making sworn oaths by Mal′cam; 6 and those who are drawing back from following Jehovah and who have not sought Jehovah and have not inquired of him.”

7 Keep silence before the Sovereign Lord Jehovah; for the day of Jehovah is near, for Jehovah has prepared a sacrifice; he has sanctified his invited ones.

8 “And it must occur on the day of Jehovah’s sacrifice that I will give attention to the princes, and to the sons of the king, and to all those wearing foreign attire. 9 And I will give attention to everyone that is climbing upon the platform in that day, those who are filling the house of their masters with violence and deception. 10 And there must occur on that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “the sound of an outcry from the Fish Gate, and a howling from the second quarter, and a great crashing from the hills. 11 Howl, YOU inhabitants of Mak′tesh, for all the people who are tradesmen have been silenced; all those weighing out silver have been cut off.

12 “And it must occur at that time that I shall carefully search Jerusalem with lamps, and I will give attention to the men who are congealing upon their dregs and who are saying in their heart, ‘Jehovah will not do good, and he will not do bad.’ 13 And their wealth must come to be for pillage and their houses for a desolate waste. And they will build houses, but they will not have occupancy; and they will plant vineyards, but they will not drink the wine of them.

14 “The great day of Jehovah is near. It is near, and there is a hurrying of it very much. The sound of the day of Jehovah is bitter. There a mighty man is letting out a cry. 15 That day is a day of fury, a day of distress and of anguish, a day of storm and of desolation, a day of darkness and of gloominess, a day of clouds and of thick gloom, 16 a day of horn and of alarm signal, against the fortified cities and against the high corner towers. 17 And I will cause distress to mankind, and they will certainly walk like blind men; because it is against Jehovah that they have sinned. And their blood will actually be poured out like dust, and their bowels like the dung. 18 Neither their silver nor their gold will be able to deliver them in the day of Jehovah’s fury; but by the fire of his zeal the whole earth will be devoured, because he will make an extermination, indeed a terrible one, of all the inhabitants of the earth.”

Haggai

1 In the second year of Da·ri′us the king, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred by means of Hag′gai the prophet to Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el, the governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Je·hoz′a·dak the high priest, saying:

2 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘As regards this people, they have said: “The time has not come, the time of the house of Jehovah, for it to be built.”’”

3 And the word of Jehovah continued to come by means of Hag′gai the prophet, saying: 4 “Is it the time for YOU yourselves to dwell in YOUR paneled houses, while this house is waste? 5 And now this is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Set YOUR heart upon YOUR ways. 6 YOU have sown much seed, but there is a bringing of little in. There is an eating, but it is not to satisfaction. There is a drinking, but not to the point of getting intoxicated. There is a putting on of clothes, but it is not with anyone’s getting warm; and he that is hiring himself out is hiring himself out for a bag having holes.’”

7 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Set YOUR heart upon YOUR ways.’

8 “‘Go up to the mountain, and YOU must bring in lumber. And build the house, that I may take pleasure in it and I may be glorified,’ Jehovah has said.”

9 “‘There was a looking for much, but here there was just a little; and YOU have brought it into the house, and I blew upon it—for what reason?’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies. ‘By reason of my house that is waste, while YOU are on the run, each one in behalf of his own house. 10 Therefore over YOU the heavens kept back their dew, and the earth itself kept back its yield. 11 And I kept calling for dryness upon the earth, and upon the mountains, and upon the grain, and upon the new wine, and upon the oil, and upon what the ground would bring forth, and upon earthling man, and upon domestic animal, and upon all the toil of the hands.’”

12 And Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el, and Joshua the son of Je·hoz′a·dak the high priest, and all the remaining ones of the people began to listen to the voice of Jehovah their God, and to the words of Hag′gai the prophet, as Jehovah their God had sent him; and the people began to fear because of Jehovah.

13 And Hag′gai the messenger of Jehovah went on to say to the people according to the messenger’s commission from Jehovah, saying: “‘I am with YOU people,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

14 And Jehovah proceeded to rouse up the spirit of Ze·rub′ba·bel the son of She·al′ti·el, the governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Je·hoz′a·dak the high priest, and the spirit of all the remaining ones of the people; and they began to enter in and to do the work in the house of Jehovah of armies their God. 15 It was on the twenty-fourth day of the sixth month in the second year of Da·ri′us the king.

Zechariah

4 And the angel who was speaking with me proceeded to come back and wake me up, like a man that is awakened from his sleep. 2 Then he said to me: “What are you seeing?”

So I said: “I have seen, and, look! there is a lampstand, all of it of gold, with a bowl on top of it. And its seven lamps are upon it, even seven; and the lamps that are at the top of it have seven pipes. 3 And there are two olive trees alongside it, one on the right side of the bowl and one on its left side.”

4 Then I answered and said to the angel who was speaking with me, saying: “What do these things mean, my lord?” 5 So the angel who was speaking with me answered and said to me: “Do you not really know what these things mean?”

In turn I said: “No, my lord.”

6 Accordingly he answered and said to me: “This is the word of Jehovah to Ze·rub′ba·bel, saying, ‘“Not by a military force, nor by power, but by my spirit,” Jehovah of armies has said. 7 Who are you, O great mountain? Before Ze·rub′ba·bel you will become a level land. And he will certainly bring forth the headstone. There will be shoutings to it: “How charming! How charming!”’”

8 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 9 “The very hands of Ze·rub′ba·bel have laid the foundation of this house, and his own hands will finish it. And you will have to know that Jehovah of armies himself has sent me to YOU people. 10 For who has despised the day of small things? And they will certainly rejoice and see the plummet in the hand of Ze·rub′ba·bel. These seven are the eyes of Jehovah. They are roving about in all the earth.”

11 And I proceeded to answer and say to him: “What do these two olive trees on the right side of the lampstand and on its left side mean?” 12 Then I answered the second time and said to him: “What are the two bunches of twigs of the olive trees that, by means of the two golden tubes, are pouring forth from within themselves the golden liquid?”

13 So he said to me: “Do you not really know what these things mean?”

In turn I said: “No, my lord.”

14 Accordingly he said: “These are the two anointed ones who are standing alongside the Lord of the whole earth.”

Zechariah

5 Then I raised my eyes again and saw; and, look! a flying scroll. 2 So he said to me: “What are you seeing?”

In turn I said: “I am seeing a flying scroll, the length of which is twenty cubits, and the breadth of which is ten cubits.”

3 Then he said to me: “This is the curse that is going forth over the surface of all the earth, because everyone that is stealing, according to it on this side, has gone free of punishment; and everyone making a sworn oath, according to it on that side, has gone free of punishment. 4 ‘I have caused it to go forth,’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, ‘and it must enter into the house of the thief and into the house of the one making a sworn oath in my name falsely; and it must lodge in the midst of his house and exterminate it and its timbers and its stones.’”

5 Then the angel who was speaking with me went forth and said to me: “Raise your eyes, please, and see what this is that is going forth.”

6 So I said: “What is it?”

In turn he said: “This is the e′phah measure that is going forth.” And he went on to say: “This is their aspect in all the earth.” 7 And, look! the circular lid of lead was lifted up; and this is a certain woman sitting in the midst of the e′phah. 8 So he said: “This is Wickedness.” And he proceeded to throw her back into the midst of the e′phah, after which he threw the lead weight upon its mouth.

9 Then I raised my eyes and saw, and here there were two women coming forth, and wind was in their wings. And they had wings like the wings of the stork. And they gradually raised the e′phah up between the earth and the heavens. 10 So I said to the angel who was speaking with me: “Where are they taking the e′phah?”

11 In turn he said to me: “In order to build for her a house in the land of Shi′nar; and it must be firmly established, and she must be deposited there upon her proper place.”

Zechariah

6 Then I raised my eyes again and saw; and, look! there were four chariots coming forth from between two mountains, and the mountains were copper mountains. 2 In the first chariot there were red horses; and in the second chariot, black horses. 3 And in the third chariot there were white horses; and in the fourth chariot, horses speckled, parti-colored.

4 And I proceeded to answer and say to the angel who was speaking with me: “What are these, my lord?”

5 So the angel answered and said to me: “These are the four spirits of the heavens that are going forth after having taken their station before the Lord of the whole earth. 6 As for the one in which the black horses are, they are going forth to the land of the north; and as for the white ones, they must go forth to behind the sea; and as for the speckled ones, they must go forth to the land of the south. 7 And as for the parti-colored ones, they must go forth and keep seeking where to go, in order to walk about in the earth.” Then he said: “Go, walk about in the earth.” And they began walking about in the earth.

8 And he proceeded to cry out to me and speak to me, saying: “See, those going forth to the land of the north are the ones that have caused the spirit of Jehovah to rest in the land of the north.”

9 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 10 “Let there be a taking of something from the exiled people, even from Hel′dai and from To·bi′jah and from Je·da′iah; and you yourself must come in that day, and you must come into the house of Jo·si′ah the son of Zeph·a·ni′ah with these who have come from Babylon. 11 And you must take silver and gold and make a grand crown and put it upon the head of Joshua the son of Je·hoz′a·dak the high priest. 12 And you must say to him,

“‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Here is the man whose name is Sprout. And from his own place he will sprout, and he will certainly build the temple of Jehovah. 13 And he himself will build the temple of Jehovah, and he, for his part, will carry the dignity; and he must sit down and rule on his throne, and he must become a priest upon his throne, and the very counsel of peace will prove to be between both of them. 14 And the grand crown itself will come to belong to He′lem and to To·bi′jah and to Je·da′iah and to Hen the son of Zeph·a·ni′ah as a memorial in the temple of Jehovah. 15 And those who are far away will come and actually build in the temple of Jehovah.” And YOU people will have to know that Jehovah of armies himself has sent me to YOU. And it must occur—if YOU will without fail listen to the voice of Jehovah YOUR God.’”

Zechariah

11 “Open up your doors, O Leb′a·non, that a fire may devour among your cedars. 2 Howl, O juniper tree, for the cedar has fallen; because the majestic ones themselves have been despoiled! Howl, YOU massive trees of Ba′shan, for the impenetrable forest has come down! 3 Listen! The howling of shepherds, for their majesty has been despoiled. Listen! The roaring of maned young lions, for the proud thickets along the Jordan have been despoiled.

4 “This is what Jehovah my God has said, ‘Shepherd the flock meant for the killing, 5 the buyers of which proceed to kill them although they are not held guilty. And those who are selling them say: “May Jehovah be blessed, while I shall gain riches.” And their own shepherds do not show any compassion upon them.’

6 “‘For I shall show compassion no more upon the inhabitants of the land,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘So here I am causing mankind to find themselves, each one in the hand of his companion and in the hand of his king; and they will certainly crush to pieces the land, and I shall do no delivering out of their hand.’”

7 And I proceeded to shepherd the flock meant for the killing, in YOUR behalf, O afflicted ones of the flock. So I took for myself two staffs. The one I called Pleasantness, and the other I called Union, and I went shepherding the flock. 8 And I finally effaced three shepherds in one lunar month, as my soul gradually became impatient with them, and also their own soul felt a loathing toward me. 9 At length I said: “I shall not keep shepherding YOU. The one that is dying, let her die. And the one that is being effaced, let her be effaced. And as for the ones left remaining, let them devour, each one the flesh of her companion.” 10 So I took my staff Pleasantness and cut it to pieces, in order to break my covenant that I had concluded with all the peoples. 11 And it came to be broken in that day, and the afflicted ones of the flock who were watching me got to know in this way that it was the word of Jehovah.

12 Then I said to them: “If it is good in YOUR eyes, give me my wages; but if not, refrain.” And they proceeded to pay my wages, thirty pieces of silver.

13 At that, Jehovah said to me: “Throw it to the treasury—the majestic value with which I have been valued from their standpoint.” Accordingly I took the thirty pieces of silver and threw it into the treasury at the house of Jehovah.

14 Then I cut in pieces my second staff, the Union, in order to break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel.

15 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Take yet for yourself the implements of a useless shepherd. 16 For here I am letting a shepherd rise up in the land. To the sheep being effaced he will give no attention. The young one he will not seek, and the broken sheep he will not heal. The one stationing herself he will not supply with food, and the flesh of the fat one he will eat, and the hoofs of the sheep he will tear off. 17 Woe to my valueless shepherd, who is leaving the flock! A sword will be upon his arm and upon his right eye. His own arm will without fail dry up, and his own right eye will without fail grow dim.”

Malachi

2 “And now this commandment is to YOU, O priests. 2 If YOU will not listen, and if YOU will not lay it to heart to give glory to my name,” Jehovah of armies has said, “I shall also certainly send upon YOU the curse, and I will curse YOUR blessings. Yes, I have even cursed the blessing, because YOU are not laying it to heart.”

3 “Look! I am rebuking on YOUR account the sown seed, and I will scatter dung upon YOUR faces, the dung of YOUR festivals; and someone will actually carry YOU away to it. 4 And YOU will have to know that I have sent to YOU this commandment, in order that my covenant with Le′vi may continue,” Jehovah of armies has said.

5 “As for my covenant, it proved to be with him, one of life and of peace, and I kept giving them to him, with fear. And he continued fearing me; yes, because of my name he himself was struck with terror. 6 The very law of truth proved to be in his mouth, and there was no unrighteousness to be found on his lips. In peace and in uprightness he walked with me, and many were those whom he turned back from error. 7 For the lips of a priest are the ones that should keep knowledge, and the law is what people should seek from his mouth; for he is the messenger of Jehovah of armies.

8 “But YOU men—YOU have turned aside from the way. YOU have caused many to stumble in the law. YOU have ruined the covenant of Le′vi,” Jehovah of armies has said. 9 “And I also, for my part, shall certainly make YOU to be despised and low to all the people, according as YOU were not keeping my ways, but were showing partiality in the law.”

10 “Is it not one father that all of us have? Is it not one God that has created us? Why is it that we deal treacherously with one another, in profaning the covenant of our forefathers? 11 Judah has dealt treacherously, and a detestable thing has been committed in Israel and in Jerusalem; for Judah has profaned the holiness of Jehovah, which He has loved, and he has taken possession of the daughter of a foreign god as a bride. 12 Jehovah will cut off each one that does it, one who is awake and one who is answering, from the tents of Jacob, and one who is presenting a gift offering to Jehovah of armies.”

13 “And this is the second thing that YOU people do, this resulting in covering with tears the altar of Jehovah, with weeping and sighing, so that there is no more a turning toward the gift offering or a taking of pleasure in anything from YOUR hand. 14 And YOU have said, ‘On what account?’ On this account, that Jehovah himself has borne witness between you and the wife of your youth, with whom you yourself have dealt treacherously, although she is your partner and the wife of your covenant. 15 And there was one who did not do it, as he had what was remaining of the spirit. And what was that one seeking? The seed of God. And YOU people must guard yourselves respecting YOUR spirit, and with the wife of your youth may no one deal treacherously. 16 For he has hated a divorcing,” Jehovah the God of Israel has said; “and the one who with violence has covered over his garment,” Jehovah of armies has said. “And YOU must guard yourselves respecting YOUR spirit, and YOU must not deal treacherously.

17 “YOU people have made Jehovah weary by YOUR words, and YOU have said, ‘In what way have we made him weary?’ By YOUR saying, ‘Everyone that is doing bad is good in the eyes of Jehovah, and in such ones he himself has taken delight’; or, ‘Where is the God of justice?’”

Matthew

2 After Jesus had been born in Beth′le·hem of Ju·de′a in the days of Herod the king, look! astrologers from eastern parts came to Jerusalem, 2 saying: “Where is the one born king of the Jews? For we saw his star when we were in the east, and we have come to do him obeisance.” 3 At hearing this King Herod was agitated, and all Jerusalem along with him; 4 and on gathering together all the chief priests and scribes of the people he began to inquire of them where the Christ was to be born. 5 They said to him: “In Beth′le·hem of Ju·de′a; for this is how it has been written through the prophet, 6 ‘And you, O Beth′le·hem of the land of Judah, are by no means the most insignificant city among the governors of Judah; for out of you will come forth a governing one, who will shepherd my people, Israel.’”

7 Then Herod secretly summoned the astrologers and carefully ascertained from them the time of the star’s appearing; 8 and, when sending them to Beth′le·hem, he said: “Go make a careful search for the young child, and when YOU have found it report back to me, that I too may go and do it obeisance.” 9 When they had heard the king, they went their way; and, look! the star they had seen when they were in the east went ahead of them, until it came to a stop above where the young child was. 10 On seeing the star they rejoiced very much indeed. 11 And when they went into the house they saw the young child with Mary its mother, and, falling down, they did obeisance to it. They also opened their treasures and presented it with gifts, gold and frankincense and myrrh. 12 However, because they were given divine warning in a dream not to return to Herod, they withdrew to their country by another way.

13 After they had withdrawn, look! Jehovah’s angel appeared in a dream to Joseph, saying: “Get up, take the young child and its mother and flee into Egypt, and stay there until I give you word; for Herod is about to search for the young child to destroy it.” 14 So he got up and took along the young child and its mother by night and withdrew into Egypt, 15 and he stayed there until the decease of Herod, for that to be fulfilled which was spoken by Jehovah through his prophet, saying: “Out of Egypt I called my son.”

16 Then Herod, seeing he had been outwitted by the astrologers, fell into a great rage, and he sent out and had all the boys in Beth′le·hem and in all its districts done away with, from two years of age and under, according to the time that he had carefully ascertained from the astrologers. 17 Then that was fulfilled which was spoken through Jeremiah the prophet, saying: 18 “A voice was heard in Ra′mah, weeping and much wailing; it was Rachel weeping for her children, and she was unwilling to take comfort, because they are no more.”

19 When Herod had deceased, look! Jehovah’s angel appeared in a dream to Joseph in Egypt 20 and said: “Get up, take the young child and its mother and be on your way into the land of Israel, for those who were seeking the soul of the young child are dead.” 21 So he got up and took the young child and its mother and entered into the land of Israel. 22 But hearing that Ar·che·la′us ruled as king of Ju·de′a instead of his father Herod, he became afraid to depart for there. Moreover, being given divine warning in a dream, he withdrew into the territory of Gal′i·lee, 23 and came and dwelt in a city named Naz′a·reth, that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through the prophets: “He will be called a Naz·a·rene′.”

Matthew

3 In those days John the Baptist came preaching in the wilderness of Ju·de′a, 2 saying: “REPENT, for the kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.” 3 This, in fact, is the one spoken of through Isaiah the prophet in these words: “Listen! Someone is crying out in the wilderness, ‘Prepare the way of Jehovah, YOU people! Make his roads straight.’” 4 But this very John had his clothing of camel’s hair and a leather girdle around his loins; his food too was insect locusts and wild honey. 5 Then Jerusalem and all Ju·de′a and all the country around the Jordan made their way out to him, 6 and people were baptized by him in the Jordan River, openly confessing their sins.

7 When he caught sight of many of the Pharisees and Sadducees coming to the baptism, he said to them: “YOU offspring of vipers, who has intimated to YOU to flee from the coming wrath? 8 So then produce fruit that befits repentance; 9 and do not presume to say to yourselves, ‘As a father we have Abraham.’ For I say to YOU that God is able to raise up children to Abraham from these stones. 10 Already the ax is lying at the root of the trees; every tree, then, that does not produce fine fruit is to be cut down and thrown into the fire. 11 I, for my part, baptize YOU with water because of YOUR repentance; but the one coming after me is stronger than I am, whose sandals I am not fit to take off. That one will baptize YOU people with holy spirit and with fire. 12 His winnowing shovel is in his hand, and he will completely clean up his threshing floor, and will gather his wheat into the storehouse, but the chaff he will burn up with fire that cannot be put out.”

13 Then Jesus came from Gal′i·lee to the Jordan to John, in order to be baptized by him. 14 But the latter tried to prevent him, saying: “I am the one needing to be baptized by you, and are you coming to me?” 15 In reply Jesus said to him: “Let it be, this time, for in that way it is suitable for us to carry out all that is righteous.” Then he quit preventing him. 16 After being baptized Jesus immediately came up from the water; and, look! the heavens were opened up, and he saw descending like a dove God’s spirit coming upon him. 17 Look! Also, there was a voice from the heavens that said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.”

Matthew

8 After he had come down from the mountain great crowds followed him. 2 And, look! a leprous man came up and began doing obeisance to him, saying: “Lord, if you just want to, you can make me clean.” 3 And so, stretching out his hand, he touched him, saying: “I want to. Be made clean.” And immediately his leprosy was cleansed away. 4 Then Jesus said to him: “See that you tell no one, but go, show yourself to the priest, and offer the gift that Moses appointed, for the purpose of a witness to them.”

5 When he entered into Ca·per′na·um, an army officer came to him, entreating him 6 and saying: “Sir, my manservant is laid up in the house with paralysis, being terribly tormented.” 7 He said to him: “When I get there I will cure him.” 8 In reply the army officer said: “Sir, I am not a fit man for you to enter under my roof, but just say the word and my manservant will be healed. 9 For I too am a man placed under authority, having soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Be on your way!’ and he is on his way, and to another, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does it.” 10 Hearing that, Jesus became amazed and said to those following him: “I tell YOU the truth, With no one in Israel have I found so great a faith. 11 But I tell YOU that many from eastern parts and western parts will come and recline at the table with Abraham and Isaac and Jacob in the kingdom of the heavens; 12 whereas the sons of the kingdom will be thrown into the darkness outside. There is where their weeping and the gnashing of their teeth will be.” 13 Then Jesus said to the army officer: “Go. Just as it has been your faith, so let it come to pass for you.” And the manservant was healed in that hour.

14 And Jesus, on coming into Peter’s house, saw his mother-in-law lying down and sick with fever. 15 So he touched her hand, and the fever left her, and she got up and began ministering to him. 16 But after it became evening, people brought him many demon-possessed persons; and he expelled the spirits with a word, and he cured all who were faring badly; 17 that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying: “He himself took our sicknesses and carried our diseases.”

18 When Jesus saw a crowd around him, he gave the command to shove off for the other side. 19 And a certain scribe came up and said to him: “Teacher, I will follow you wherever you are about to go.” 20 But Jesus said to him: “Foxes have dens and birds of heaven have roosts, but the Son of man has nowhere to lay down his head.” 21 Then another of the disciples said to him: “Lord, permit me first to leave and bury my father.” 22 Jesus said to him: “Keep following me, and let the dead bury their dead.”

23 And when he got aboard a boat, his disciples followed him. 24 Now, look! a great agitation arose in the sea, so that the boat was being covered by the waves; he, however, was sleeping. 25 And they came and woke him up, saying: “Lord, save us, we are about to perish!” 26 But he said to them: “Why are YOU fainthearted, YOU with little faith?” Then, getting up, he rebuked the winds and the sea, and a great calm set in. 27 So the men became amazed and said: “What sort of person is this, that even the winds and the sea obey him?”

28 When he got to the other side, into the country of the Gad·a·renes′, there met him two demon-possessed men coming out from among the memorial tombs, unusually fierce, so that nobody had the courage to pass by on that road. 29 And, look! they screamed, saying: “What have we to do with you, Son of God? Did you come here to torment us before the appointed time?” 30 But a long way off from them a herd of many swine was at pasture. 31 So the demons began to entreat him, saying: “If you expel us, send us forth into the herd of swine.” 32 Accordingly he said to them: “Go!” They came out and went off into the swine; and, look! the entire herd rushed over the precipice into the sea and died in the waters. 33 But the herders fled and, going into the city, they reported everything, including the affair of the demon-possessed men. 34 And, look! all the city turned out to meet Jesus; and after having seen him, they earnestly urged him to move out from their districts.

Matthew

9 So, boarding the boat, he proceeded across and went into his own city. 2 And, look! they were bringing him a paralyzed man lying on a bed. On seeing their faith Jesus said to the paralytic: “Take courage, child; your sins are forgiven.” 3 And, look! certain of the scribes said to themselves: “This fellow is blaspheming.” 4 And Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said: “Why are YOU thinking wicked things in YOUR hearts? 5 For instance, which is easier, to say, Your sins are forgiven, or to say, Get up and walk? 6 However, in order for YOU to know that the Son of man has authority on earth to forgive sins—” then he said to the paralytic: “Get up, pick up your bed, and go to your home.” 7 And he got up and went off to his home. 8 At the sight of this the crowds were struck with fear, and they glorified God, who gave such authority to men.

9 Next, while passing along from there, Jesus caught sight of a man named Matthew seated at the tax office, and he said to him: “Be my follower.” Thereupon he did rise up and follow him. 10 Later, while he was reclining at the table in the house, look! many tax collectors and sinners came and began reclining with Jesus and his disciples. 11 But on seeing this the Pharisees began to say to his disciples: “Why is it that YOUR teacher eats with tax collectors and sinners?” 12 Hearing them, he said: “Persons in health do not need a physician, but the ailing do. 13 Go, then, and learn what this means, ‘I want mercy, and not sacrifice.’ For I came to call, not righteous people, but sinners.”

14 Then John’s disciples came to him and asked: “Why is it that we and the Pharisees practice fasting but your disciples do not fast?” 15 At this Jesus said to them: “The friends of the bridegroom have no reason to mourn as long as the bridegroom is with them, do they? But days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast. 16 Nobody sews a patch of unshrunk cloth upon an old outer garment; for its full strength would pull from the outer garment and the tear would become worse. 17 Neither do people put new wine into old wineskins; but if they do, then the wineskins burst and the wine spills out and the wineskins are ruined. But people put new wine into new wineskins, and both things are preserved.”

18 While he was telling them these things, look! a certain ruler who had approached began to do obeisance to him, saying: “By now my daughter must be dead; but come and lay your hand upon her and she will come to life.”

19 Then Jesus, getting up, began to follow him; also his disciples did. 20 And, look! a woman suffering twelve years from a flow of blood came up behind and touched the fringe of his outer garment; 21 for she kept saying to herself: “If I only touch his outer garment I shall get well.” 22 Jesus turned around and, noticing her, said: “Take courage, daughter; your faith has made you well.” And from that hour the woman became well.

23 When, now, he came into the ruler’s house and caught sight of the flute players and the crowd in noisy confusion, 24 Jesus began to say: “Leave the place, for the little girl did not die, but she is sleeping.” At this they began to laugh at him scornfully. 25 As soon as the crowd had been sent outside, he went in and took hold of her hand, and the little girl got up. 26 Of course, the talk about this spread out into all that region.

27 As Jesus was passing along from there, two blind men followed him, crying out and saying: “Have mercy on us, Son of David.” 28 After he had gone into the house, the blind men came to him, and Jesus asked them: “Do YOU have faith that I can do this?” They answered him: “Yes, Lord.” 29 Then he touched their eyes, saying: “According to YOUR faith let it happen to YOU.” 30 And their eyes received sight. Moreover, Jesus sternly charged them, saying: “See that nobody gets to know it.” 31 But they, after getting outside, made it public about him in all that region.

32 Now when they were leaving, look! people brought him a dumb man possessed of a demon; 33 and after the demon had been expelled the dumb man spoke. Well, the crowds felt amazement and said: “Never was anything like this seen in Israel.” 34 But the Pharisees began to say: “It is by the ruler of the demons that he expels the demons.”

35 And Jesus set out on a tour of all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues and preaching the good news of the kingdom and curing every sort of disease and every sort of infirmity. 36 On seeing the crowds he felt pity for them, because they were skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd. 37 Then he said to his disciples: “Yes, the harvest is great, but the workers are few. 38 Therefore, beg the Master of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest.”

Matthew

11 Now when Jesus had finished giving instructions to his twelve disciples, he set out from there to teach and preach in their cities.

2 But John, having heard in jail about the works of the Christ, sent by means of his own disciples 3 and said to him: “Are you the Coming One, or are we to expect a different one?” 4 In reply Jesus said to them: “Go YOUR way and report to John what YOU are hearing and seeing: 5 The blind are seeing again, and the lame are walking about, the lepers are being cleansed and the deaf are hearing, and the dead are being raised up, and the poor are having the good news declared to them; 6 and happy is he that finds no cause for stumbling in me.”

7 While these were on their way, Jesus started to say to the crowds respecting John: “What did YOU go out into the wilderness to behold? A reed being tossed by a wind? 8 What, then, did YOU go out to see? A man dressed in soft garments? Why, those wearing soft garments are in the houses of kings. 9 Really, then, why did YOU go out? To see a prophet? Yes, I tell YOU, and far more than a prophet. 10 This is he concerning whom it is written, ‘Look! I myself am sending forth my messenger before your face, who will prepare your way ahead of you!’ 11 Truly I say to YOU people, Among those born of women there has not been raised up a greater than John the Baptist; but a person that is a lesser one in the kingdom of the heavens is greater than he is. 12 But from the days of John the Baptist until now the kingdom of the heavens is the goal toward which men press, and those pressing forward are seizing it. 13 For all, the Prophets and the Law, prophesied until John; 14 and if YOU want to accept it, He himself is ‘E·li′jah who is destined to come.’ 15 Let him that has ears listen.

16 “With whom shall I compare this generation? It is like young children sitting in the marketplaces who cry out to their playmates, 17 saying, ‘We played the flute for YOU, but YOU did not dance; we wailed, but YOU did not beat yourselves in grief.’ 18 Correspondingly, John came neither eating nor drinking, yet people say, ‘He has a demon’; 19 the Son of man did come eating and drinking, still people say, ‘Look! A man gluttonous and given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.’ All the same, wisdom is proved righteous by its works.”

20 Then he started to reproach the cities in which most of his powerful works had taken place, because they did not repent: 21 “Woe to you, Cho·ra′zin! Woe to you, Beth·sa′i·da! because if the powerful works had taken place in Tyre and Si′don that took place in YOU, they would long ago have repented in sackcloth and ashes. 22 Consequently I say to YOU, It will be more endurable for Tyre and Si′don on Judgment Day than for YOU. 23 And you, Ca·per′na·um, will you perhaps be exalted to heaven? Down to Ha′des you will come; because if the powerful works that took place in you had taken place in Sod′om, it would have remained until this very day. 24 Consequently I say to YOU people, It will be more endurable for the land of Sod′om on Judgment Day than for you.”

25 At that time Jesus said in response: “I publicly praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have hidden these things from the wise and intellectual ones and have revealed them to babes. 26 Yes, O Father, because to do thus came to be the way approved by you. 27 All things have been delivered to me by my Father, and no one fully knows the Son but the Father, neither does anyone fully know the Father but the Son and anyone to whom the Son is willing to reveal him. 28 Come to me, all YOU who are toiling and loaded down, and I will refresh YOU. 29 Take my yoke upon YOU and learn from me, for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and YOU will find refreshment for YOUR souls. 30 For my yoke is kindly and my load is light.”

Matthew

12 At that season Jesus went through the grainfields on the sabbath. His disciples got hungry and started to pluck heads of grain and to eat. 2 At seeing this the Pharisees said to him: “Look! Your disciples are doing what it is not lawful to do on the sabbath.” 3 He said to them: “Have YOU not read what David did when he and the men with him got hungry? 4 How he entered into the house of God and they ate the loaves of presentation, something that it was not lawful for him to eat, nor for those with him, but for the priests only? 5 Or, have YOU not read in the Law that on the sabbaths the priests in the temple treat the sabbath as not sacred and continue guiltless? 6 But I tell YOU that something greater than the temple is here. 7 However, if YOU had understood what this means, ‘I want mercy, and not sacrifice,’ YOU would not have condemned the guiltless ones. 8 For Lord of the sabbath is what the Son of man is.”

9 After departing from that place he went into their synagogue; 10 and, look! a man with a withered hand! So they asked him, “Is it lawful to cure on the sabbath?” that they might get an accusation against him. 11 He said to them: “Who will be the man among YOU that has one sheep and, if this falls into a pit on the sabbath, will not get hold of it and lift it out? 12 All considered, of how much more worth is a man than a sheep! So it is lawful to do a fine thing on the sabbath.” 13 Then he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and it was restored sound like the other hand. 14 But the Pharisees went out and took counsel against him that they might destroy him. 15 Having come to know this, Jesus withdrew from there. Many also followed him, and he cured them all, 16 but he strictly charged them not to make him manifest; 17 that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, who said:

18 “Look! My servant whom I chose, my beloved, whom my soul approved! I will put my spirit upon him, and what justice is he will make clear to the nations. 19 He will not wrangle, nor cry aloud, nor will anyone hear his voice in the broad ways. 20 No bruised reed will he crush, and no smoldering flaxen wick will he extinguish, until he sends out justice with success. 21 Indeed, in his name nations will hope.”

22 Then they brought him a demon-possessed man, blind and dumb; and he cured him, so that the dumb man spoke and saw. 23 Well, all the crowds were simply carried away and began to say: “May this not perhaps be the Son of David?” 24 At hearing this, the Pharisees said: “This fellow does not expel the demons except by means of Be·el′ze·bub, the ruler of the demons.” 25 Knowing their thoughts, he said to them: “Every kingdom divided against itself comes to desolation, and every city or house divided against itself will not stand. 26 In the same way, if Satan expels Satan, he has become divided against himself; how, then, will his kingdom stand? 27 Moreover, if I expel the demons by means of Be·el′ze·bub, by means of whom do YOUR sons expel them? This is why they will be judges of YOU. 28 But if it is by means of God’s spirit that I expel the demons, the kingdom of God has really overtaken YOU. 29 Or how can anyone invade the house of a strong man and seize his movable goods, unless first he binds the strong man? And then he will plunder his house. 30 He that is not on my side is against me, and he that does not gather with me scatters.

31 “On this account I say to YOU, Every sort of sin and blasphemy will be forgiven men, but the blasphemy against the spirit will not be forgiven. 32 For example, whoever speaks a word against the Son of man, it will be forgiven him; but whoever speaks against the holy spirit, it will not be forgiven him, no, not in this system of things nor in that to come.

33 “Either YOU people make the tree fine and its fruit fine or make the tree rotten and its fruit rotten; for by its fruit the tree is known. 34 Offspring of vipers, how can YOU speak good things, when YOU are wicked? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks. 35 The good man out of his good treasure sends out good things, whereas the wicked man out of his wicked treasure sends out wicked things. 36 I tell YOU that every unprofitable saying that men speak, they will render an account concerning it on Judgment Day; 37 for by your words you will be declared righteous, and by your words you will be condemned.”

38 Then as an answer to him some of the scribes and Pharisees said: “Teacher, we want to see a sign from you.” 39 In reply he said to them: “A wicked and adulterous generation keeps on seeking for a sign, but no sign will be given it except the sign of Jo′nah the prophet. 40 For just as Jo′nah was in the belly of the huge fish three days and three nights, so the Son of man will be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights. 41 Men of Nin′e·veh will rise up in the judgment with this generation and will condemn it; because they repented at what Jo′nah preached, but, look! something more than Jo′nah is here. 42 The queen of the south will be raised up in the judgment with this generation and will condemn it; because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Sol′o·mon, but, look! something more than Sol′o·mon is here.

43 “When an unclean spirit comes out of a man, it passes through parched places in search of a resting-place, and finds none. 44 Then it says, ‘I will go back to my house out of which I moved’; and on arriving it finds it unoccupied but swept clean and adorned. 45 Then it goes its way and takes along with it seven different spirits more wicked than itself, and, after getting inside, they dwell there; and the final circumstances of that man become worse than the first. That is how it will be also with this wicked generation.”

46 While he was yet speaking to the crowds, look! his mother and brothers took up a position outside seeking to speak to him. 47 So someone said to him: “Look! Your mother and your brothers are standing outside, seeking to speak to you.” 48 As an answer he said to the one telling him: “Who is my mother, and who are my brothers?” 49 And extending his hand toward his disciples, he said: “Look! My mother and my brothers! 50 For whoever does the will of my Father who is in heaven, the same is my brother, and sister, and mother.”

Matthew

13 On that day Jesus, having left the house, was sitting by the sea; 2 and great crowds gathered to him, so that he went aboard a boat and sat down, and all the crowd was standing on the beach. 3 Then he told them many things by illustrations, saying: “Look! A sower went out to sow; 4 and as he was sowing, some seeds fell alongside the road, and the birds came and ate them up. 5 Others fell upon the rocky places where they did not have much soil, and at once they sprang up because of not having depth of soil. 6 But when the sun rose they were scorched, and because of not having root they withered. 7 Others, too, fell among the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked them. 8 Still others fell upon the fine soil and they began to yield fruit, this one a hundredfold, that one sixty, the other thirty. 9 Let him that has ears listen.”

10 So the disciples came up and said to him: “Why is it you speak to them by the use of illustrations?” 11 In reply he said: “To YOU it is granted to understand the sacred secrets of the kingdom of the heavens, but to those people it is not granted. 12 For whoever has, more will be given him and he will be made to abound; but whoever does not have, even what he has will be taken from him. 13 This is why I speak to them by the use of illustrations, because, looking, they look in vain, and hearing, they hear in vain, neither do they get the sense of it; 14 and toward them the prophecy of Isaiah is having fulfillment, which says, ‘By hearing, YOU will hear but by no means get the sense of it; and, looking, YOU will look but by no means see. 15 For the heart of this people has grown unreceptive, and with their ears they have heard without response, and they have shut their eyes; that they might never see with their eyes and hear with their ears and get the sense of it with their hearts and turn back, and I heal them.’

16 “However, happy are YOUR eyes because they behold, and YOUR ears because they hear. 17 For I truly say to YOU, Many prophets and righteous men desired to see the things YOU are beholding and did not see them, and to hear the things YOU are hearing and did not hear them.

18 “YOU, then, listen to the illustration of the man that sowed. 19 Where anyone hears the word of the kingdom but does not get the sense of it, the wicked one comes and snatches away what has been sown in his heart; this is the one sown alongside the road. 20 As for the one sown upon the rocky places, this is the one hearing the word and at once accepting it with joy. 21 Yet he has no root in himself but continues for a time, and after tribulation or persecution has arisen on account of the word he is at once stumbled. 22 As for the one sown among the thorns, this is the one hearing the word, but the anxiety of this system of things and the deceptive power of riches choke the word, and he becomes unfruitful. 23 As for the one sown upon the fine soil, this is the one hearing the word and getting the sense of it, who really does bear fruit and produces, this one a hundredfold, that one sixty, the other thirty.”

24 Another illustration he set before them, saying: “The kingdom of the heavens has become like a man that sowed fine seed in his field. 25 While men were sleeping, his enemy came and oversowed weeds in among the wheat, and left. 26 When the blade sprouted and produced fruit, then the weeds appeared also. 27 So the slaves of the householder came up and said to him, ‘Master, did you not sow fine seed in your field? How, then, does it come to have weeds?’ 28 He said to them, ‘An enemy, a man, did this.’ They said to him, ‘Do you want us, then, to go out and collect them?’ 29 He said, ‘No; that by no chance, while collecting the weeds, YOU uproot the wheat with them. 30 Let both grow together until the harvest; and in the harvest season I will tell the reapers, First collect the weeds and bind them in bundles to burn them up, then go to gathering the wheat into my storehouse.’”

31 Another illustration he set before them, saying: “The kingdom of the heavens is like a mustard grain, which a man took and planted in his field; 32 which is, in fact, the tiniest of all the seeds, but when it has grown it is the largest of the vegetables and becomes a tree, so that the birds of heaven come and find lodging among its branches.”

33 Another illustration he spoke to them: “The kingdom of the heavens is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three large measures of flour, until the whole mass was fermented.”

34 All these things Jesus spoke to the crowds by illustrations. Indeed, without an illustration he would not speak to them; 35 that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through the prophet who said: “I will open my mouth with illustrations, I will publish things hidden since the founding.”

36 Then after dismissing the crowds he went into the house. And his disciples came to him and said: “Explain to us the illustration of the weeds in the field.” 37 In response he said: “The sower of the fine seed is the Son of man; 38 the field is the world; as for the fine seed, these are the sons of the kingdom; but the weeds are the sons of the wicked one, 39 and the enemy that sowed them is the Devil. The harvest is a conclusion of a system of things, and the reapers are angels. 40 Therefore, just as the weeds are collected and burned with fire, so it will be in the conclusion of the system of things. 41 The Son of man will send forth his angels, and they will collect out from his kingdom all things that cause stumbling and persons who are doing lawlessness, 42 and they will pitch them into the fiery furnace. There is where their weeping and the gnashing of their teeth will be. 43 At that time the righteous ones will shine as brightly as the sun in the kingdom of their Father. Let him that has ears listen.

44 “The kingdom of the heavens is like a treasure hidden in the field, which a man found and hid; and for the joy he has he goes and sells what things he has and buys that field.

45 “Again the kingdom of the heavens is like a traveling merchant seeking fine pearls. 46 Upon finding one pearl of high value, away he went and promptly sold all the things he had and bought it.

47 “Again the kingdom of the heavens is like a dragnet let down into the sea and gathering up fish of every kind. 48 When it got full they hauled it up onto the beach and, sitting down, they collected the fine ones into vessels, but the unsuitable they threw away. 49 That is how it will be in the conclusion of the system of things: the angels will go out and separate the wicked from among the righteous 50 and will cast them into the fiery furnace. There is where their weeping and the gnashing of their teeth will be.

51 “Did YOU get the sense of all these things?” They said to him: “Yes.” 52 Then he said to them: “That being the case, every public instructor, when taught respecting the kingdom of the heavens, is like a man, a householder, who brings out of his treasure store things new and old.”

53 Now when Jesus had finished these illustrations he went across country from there. 54 And after coming into his home territory he began to teach them in their synagogue, so that they were astounded and said: “Where did this man get this wisdom and these powerful works? 55 Is this not the carpenter’s son? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brothers James and Joseph and Simon and Judas? 56 And his sisters, are they not all with us? Where, then, did this man get all these things?” 57 So they began to stumble at him. But Jesus said to them: “A prophet is not unhonored except in his home territory and in his own house.” 58 And he did not do many powerful works there on account of their lack of faith.

Matthew

14 At that particular time Herod, the district ruler, heard the report about Jesus 2 and said to his servants: “This is John the Baptist. He was raised up from the dead, and this is why the powerful works are operating in him.” 3 For Herod had arrested John and bound him and put him away in prison on account of He·ro′di·as the wife of Philip his brother. 4 For John had been saying to him: “It is not lawful for you to be having her.” 5 However, although he wanted to kill him, he feared the crowd, because they took him for a prophet. 6 But when Herod’s birthday was being celebrated the daughter of He·ro′di·as danced at it and pleased Herod so much 7 that he promised with an oath to give her whatever she asked. 8 Then she, under her mother’s coaching, said: “Give me here upon a platter the head of John the Baptist.” 9 Grieved though he was, the king out of regard for his oaths and for those reclining with him commanded it to be given; 10 and he sent and had John beheaded in the prison. 11 And his head was brought on a platter and given to the maiden, and she brought it to her mother. 12 Finally his disciples came up and removed the corpse and buried him and came and reported to Jesus. 13 At hearing this Jesus withdrew from there by boat into a lonely place for isolation; but the crowds, getting to hear of it, followed him on foot from the cities.

14 Now when he came forth he saw a great crowd; and he felt pity for them, and he cured their sick ones. 15 But when evening fell his disciples came to him and said: “The place is lonely and the hour is already far advanced; send the crowds away, that they may go into the villages and buy themselves things to eat.” 16 However, Jesus said to them: “They do not have to leave: YOU give them something to eat.” 17 They said to him: “We have nothing here but five loaves and two fishes.” 18 He said: “BRING them here to me.” 19 Next he commanded the crowds to recline on the grass and took the five loaves and two fishes, and, looking up to heaven, he said a blessing and, after breaking the loaves, he distributed them to the disciples, the disciples in turn to the crowds. 20 So all ate and were satisfied, and they took up the surplus of fragments, twelve baskets full. 21 Yet those eating were about five thousand men, besides women and young children. 22 Then, without delay, he compelled his disciples to board the boat and go ahead of him to the other side, while he sent the crowds away.

23 Eventually, having sent the crowds away, he went up into the mountain by himself to pray. Though it became late, he was there alone. 24 By now the boat was many hundreds of yards away from land, being hard put to it by the waves, because the wind was against them. 25 But in the fourth watch period of the night he came to them, walking over the sea. 26 When they caught sight of him walking on the sea, the disciples were troubled, saying: “It is an apparition!” And they cried out in their fear. 27 But at once Jesus spoke to them with the words: “Take courage, it is I; have no fear.” 28 In reply Peter said to him: “Lord, if it is you, command me to come to you over the waters.” 29 He said: “Come!” Thereupon Peter, getting down off the boat, walked over the waters and went toward Jesus. 30 But looking at the windstorm, he got afraid and, after starting to sink, he cried out: “Lord, save me!” 31 Immediately stretching out his hand Jesus caught hold of him and said to him: “You with little faith, why did you give way to doubt?” 32 And after they got up into the boat, the windstorm abated. 33 Then those in the boat did obeisance to him, saying: “You are really God’s Son.” 34 And they got across and came to land in Gen·nes′a·ret.

35 Upon recognizing him the men of that place sent forth into all that surrounding country, and people brought him all those who were ill. 36 And they went entreating him that they might just touch the fringe of his outer garment; and all those who touched it were made completely well.

Matthew

15 Then there came to Jesus from Jerusalem Pharisees and scribes, saying: 2 “Why is it your disciples overstep the tradition of the men of former times? For example, they do not wash their hands when about to eat a meal.”

3 In reply he said to them: “Why is it YOU also overstep the commandment of God because of YOUR tradition? 4 For example, God said, ‘Honor your father and your mother’; and, ‘Let him that reviles father or mother end up in death.’ 5 But YOU say, ‘Whoever says to his father or mother: “Whatever I have by which you might get benefit from me is a gift dedicated to God,” 6 he must not honor his father at all.’ And so YOU have made the word of God invalid because of YOUR tradition. 7 YOU hypocrites, Isaiah aptly prophesied about YOU, when he said, 8 ‘This people honor me with their lips, yet their heart is far removed from me. 9 It is in vain that they keep worshiping me, because they teach commands of men as doctrines.’” 10 With that he called the crowd near and said to them: “Listen and get the sense of it: 11 Not what enters into his mouth defiles a man; but it is what proceeds out of his mouth that defiles a man.”

12 Then the disciples came up and said to him: “Do you know that the Pharisees stumbled at hearing what you said?” 13 In reply he said: “Every plant that my heavenly Father did not plant will be uprooted. 14 LET them be. Blind guides is what they are. If, then, a blind man guides a blind man, both will fall into a pit.” 15 By way of response Peter said to him: “Make the illustration plain to us.” 16 At this he said: “Are YOU also yet without understanding? 17 Are YOU not aware that everything entering into the mouth passes along into the intestines and is discharged into the sewer? 18 However, the things proceeding out of the mouth come out of the heart, and those things defile a man. 19 For example, out of the heart come wicked reasonings, murders, adulteries, fornications, thieveries, false testimonies, blasphemies. 20 These are the things defiling a man; but to take a meal with unwashed hands does not defile a man.”

21 Leaving there, Jesus now withdrew into the parts of Tyre and Si′don. 22 And, look! a Phoe·ni′cian woman from those regions came out and cried aloud, saying: “Have mercy on me, Lord, Son of David. My daughter is badly demonized.” 23 But he did not say a word in answer to her. So his disciples came up and began to request him: “Send her away; because she keeps crying out after us.” 24 In answer he said: “I was not sent forth to any but to the lost sheep of the house of Israel.” 25 When the woman came she began doing obeisance to him, saying: “Lord, help me!” 26 In answer he said: “It is not right to take the bread of the children and throw it to little dogs.” 27 She said: “Yes, Lord; but really the little dogs do eat of the crumbs falling from the table of their masters.” 28 Then Jesus said in reply to her: “O woman, great is your faith; let it happen to you as you wish.” And her daughter was healed from that hour on.

29 Crossing country from there, Jesus next came near the sea of Gal′i·lee, and, after going up into the mountain, he was sitting there. 30 Then great crowds approached him, having along with them people that were lame, maimed, blind, dumb, and many otherwise, and they fairly threw them at his feet, and he cured them; 31 so that the crowd felt amazement as they saw the dumb speaking and the lame walking and the blind seeing, and they glorified the God of Israel.

32 But Jesus called his disciples to him and said: “I feel pity for the crowd, because it is already three days that they have stayed with me and they have nothing to eat; and I do not want to send them away fasting. They may possibly give out on the road.” 33 However, the disciples said to him: “Where are we in this lonely place going to get sufficient loaves to satisfy a crowd of this size?” 34 At this Jesus said to them: “How many loaves have YOU?” They said: “Seven, and a few little fishes.” 35 So, after instructing the crowd to recline upon the ground, 36 he took the seven loaves and the fishes and, after offering thanks, he broke them and began distributing to the disciples, the disciples in turn to the crowds. 37 And all ate and were satisfied, and as a surplus of fragments they took up seven provision baskets full. 38 Yet those eating were four thousand men, besides women and young children. 39 Finally, after sending the crowds away, he got into the boat and came into the regions of Mag′a·dan.

Matthew

16 Here the Pharisees and Sadducees approached him and, to tempt him, they asked him to display to them a sign from heaven. 2 In reply he said to them: “[[When evening falls YOU are accustomed to say, ‘It will be fair weather, for the sky is fire-red’; 3 and at morning, ‘It will be wintry, rainy weather today, for the sky is fire-red, but gloomy-looking.’ YOU know how to interpret the appearance of the sky, but the signs of the times YOU cannot interpret.]] 4 A wicked and adulterous generation keeps on seeking for a sign, but no sign will be given it except the sign of Jo′nah.” With that he went away, leaving them behind.

5 Now the disciples crossed to the other side and forgot to take loaves along. 6 Jesus said to them: “Keep YOUR eyes open and watch out for the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees.” 7 So they began to reason among themselves, saying: “We did not take any loaves along.” 8 Knowing this, Jesus said: “Why are YOU doing this reasoning among yourselves, because YOU have no loaves, YOU with little faith? 9 Do YOU not yet see the point, or do YOU not remember the five loaves in the case of the five thousand and how many baskets YOU took up? 10 Or the seven loaves in the case of the four thousand and how many provision baskets YOU took up? 11 How is it YOU do not discern that I did not talk to YOU about loaves? But watch out for the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees.” 12 Then they grasped that he said to watch out, not for the leaven of the loaves, but for the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees.

13 Now when he had come into the parts of Caes·a·re′a Phi·lip′pi, Jesus went asking his disciples: “Who are men saying the Son of man is?” 14 They said: “Some say John the Baptist, others E·li′jah, still others Jeremiah or one of the prophets.” 15 He said to them: “YOU, though, who do YOU say I am?” 16 In answer Simon Peter said: “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.” 17 In response Jesus said to him: “Happy you are, Simon son of Jo′nah, because flesh and blood did not reveal it to you, but my Father who is in the heavens did. 18 Also, I say to you, You are Peter, and on this rock-mass I will build my congregation, and the gates of Ha′des will not overpower it. 19 I will give you the keys of the kingdom of the heavens, and whatever you may bind on earth will be the thing bound in the heavens, and whatever you may loose on earth will be the thing loosed in the heavens.” 20 Then he sternly charged the disciples not to say to anybody that he was the Christ.

21 From that time forward Jesus Christ commenced showing his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things from the older men and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and on the third day be raised up. 22 At this Peter took him aside and commenced rebuking him, saying: “Be kind to yourself, Lord; you will not have this destiny at all.” 23 But, turning his back, he said to Peter: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”

24 Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and continually follow me. 25 For whoever wants to save his soul will lose it; but whoever loses his soul for my sake will find it. 26 For what benefit will it be to a man if he gains the whole world but forfeits his soul? or what will a man give in exchange for his soul? 27 For the Son of man is destined to come in the glory of his Father with his angels, and then he will recompense each one according to his behavior. 28 Truly I say to YOU that there are some of those standing here that will not taste death at all until first they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.”

Matthew

17 Six days later Jesus took Peter and James and John his brother along and brought them up into a lofty mountain by themselves. 2 And he was transfigured before them, and his face shone as the sun, and his outer garments became brilliant as the light. 3 And, look! there appeared to them Moses and E·li′jah, conversing with him. 4 Responsively Peter said to Jesus: “Lord, it is fine for us to be here. If you wish, I will erect three tents here, one for you and one for Moses and one for E·li′jah.” 5 While he was yet speaking, look! a bright cloud overshadowed them, and, look! a voice out of the cloud, saying: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved; listen to him.” 6 At hearing this the disciples fell upon their faces and became very much afraid. 7 Then Jesus came near and, touching them, said: “Get up and have no fear.” 8 When they raised their eyes, they saw no one but Jesus himself only. 9 And as they were descending from the mountain, Jesus commanded them, saying: “Tell the vision to no one until the Son of man is raised up from the dead.”

10 However, the disciples put the question to him: “Why, then, do the scribes say that E·li′jah must come first?” 11 In reply he said: “E·li′jah, indeed, is coming and will restore all things. 12 However, I say to YOU that E·li′jah has already come and they did not recognize him but did with him the things they wanted. In this way also the Son of man is destined to suffer at their hands.” 13 Then the disciples perceived that he spoke to them about John the Baptist.

14 And when they came toward the crowd, a man approached him, kneeling down to him and saying: 15 “Lord, have mercy on my son, because he is an epileptic and is ill, for he falls often into the fire and often into the water; 16 and I brought him to your disciples, but they could not cure him.” 17 In reply Jesus said: “O faithless and twisted generation, how long must I continue with YOU? How long must I put up with YOU? Bring him here to me.” 18 Then Jesus rebuked it, and the demon came out of him; and the boy was cured from that hour. 19 Thereupon the disciples came up to Jesus privately and said: “Why is it we could not expel it?” 20 He said to them: “Because of YOUR little faith. For truly I say to YOU, If YOU have faith the size of a mustard grain, YOU will say to this mountain, ‘Transfer from here to there,’ and it will transfer, and nothing will be impossible for YOU.” 21 ——

22 It was while they were gathered together in Gal′i·lee that Jesus said to them: “The Son of man is destined to be betrayed into men’s hands, 23 and they will kill him, and the third day he will be raised up.” Consequently they were very much grieved.

24 After they arrived in Ca·per′na·um the men collecting the two drachmas tax approached Peter and said: “Does YOUR teacher not pay the two drachmas tax?” 25 He said: “Yes.” However, when he entered the house Jesus got ahead of him by saying: “What do you think, Simon? From whom do the kings of the earth receive duties or head tax? From their sons or from the strangers?” 26 When he said: “From the strangers,” Jesus said to him: “Really, then, the sons are tax-free. 27 But that we do not cause them to stumble, you go to the sea, cast a fishhook, and take the first fish coming up and, when you open its mouth, you will find a stater coin. Take that and give it to them for me and you.”

Matthew

21 Well, when they got close to Jerusalem and arrived at Beth′pha·ge on the Mount of Olives, then Jesus sent forth two disciples, 2 saying to them: “Be on YOUR way into the village that is within sight of YOU, and YOU will at once find an ass tied, and a colt with her; untie them and bring them to me. 3 And if someone says anything to YOU, YOU must say, ‘The Lord needs them.’ At that he will immediately send them forth.”

4 This actually took place that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through the prophet, saying: 5 “TELL the daughter of Zion, ‘Look! Your King is coming to you, mild-tempered, and mounted upon an ass, yes, upon a colt, the offspring of a beast of burden.’”

6 So the disciples got on their way and did just as Jesus ordered them. 7 And they brought the ass and its colt, and they put upon these their outer garments, and he seated himself upon them. 8 Most of the crowd spread their outer garments on the road, while others began cutting down branches from the trees and spreading them on the road. 9 As for the crowds, those going ahead of him and those following kept crying out: “Save, we pray, the Son of David! Blessed is he that comes in Jehovah’s name! Save him, we pray, in the heights above!”

10 Now when he entered into Jerusalem, the whole city was set in commotion, saying: “Who is this?” 11 The crowds kept telling: “This is the prophet Jesus, from Naz′a·reth of Gal′i·lee!”

12 And Jesus entered into the temple and threw out all those selling and buying in the temple, and overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves. 13 And he said to them: “It is written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer,’ but YOU are making it a cave of robbers.” 14 Also, blind and lame persons came up to him in the temple, and he cured them.

15 When the chief priests and the scribes saw the marvelous things he did and the boys that were crying out in the temple and saying: “Save, we pray, the Son of David!” they became indignant 16 and said to him: “Do you hear what these are saying?” Jesus said to them: “Yes. Did YOU never read this, ‘Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings you have furnished praise’?” 17 And leaving them behind he went outside the city to Beth′a·ny and passed the night there.

18 While returning to the city early in the morning, he got hungry. 19 And he caught sight of a fig tree by the road and went to it, but he found nothing on it except leaves only, and he said to it: “Let no fruit come from you anymore forever.” And the fig tree withered instantly. 20 But when the disciples saw this, they wondered, saying: “How is it that the fig tree withered instantly?” 21 In answer Jesus said to them: “Truly I say to YOU, If only YOU have faith and do not doubt, not only will YOU do what I did to the fig tree, but also if YOU say to this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and cast into the sea,’ it will happen. 22 And all the things YOU ask in prayer, having faith, YOU will receive.”

23 Now after he went into the temple, the chief priests and the older men of the people came up to him while he was teaching and said: “By what authority do you do these things? And who gave you this authority?” 24 In reply Jesus said to them: “I, also, will ask YOU one thing. If YOU tell it to me, I also will tell YOU by what authority I do these things: 25 The baptism by John, from what source was it? From heaven or from men?” But they began to reason among themselves, saying: “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say to us, ‘Why, then, did YOU not believe him?’ 26 If, though, we say, ‘From men,’ we have the crowd to fear, for they all hold John as a prophet.” 27 So in answer to Jesus they said: “We do not know.” He, in turn, said to them: “Neither am I telling YOU by what authority I do these things.

28 “What do YOU think? A man had two children. Going up to the first, he said, ‘Child, go work today in the vineyard.’ 29 In answer this one said, ‘I will, sir,’ but did not go out. 30 Approaching the second, he said the same. In reply this one said, ‘I will not.’ Afterwards he felt regret and went out. 31 Which of the two did the will of his father?” They said: “The latter.” Jesus said to them: “Truly I say to YOU that the tax collectors and the harlots are going ahead of YOU into the kingdom of God. 32 For John came to YOU in a way of righteousness, but YOU did not believe him. However, the tax collectors and the harlots believed him, and YOU, although YOU saw this, did not feel regret afterwards so as to believe him.

33 “Hear another illustration: There was a man, a householder, who planted a vineyard and put a fence around it and dug a winepress in it and erected a tower, and let it out to cultivators, and traveled abroad. 34 When the season of the fruits came around, he dispatched his slaves to the cultivators to get his fruits. 35 However, the cultivators took his slaves, and one they beat up, another they killed, another they stoned. 36 Again he dispatched other slaves, more than the first, but they did the same to these. 37 Lastly he dispatched his son to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ 38 On seeing the son the cultivators said among themselves, ‘This is the heir; come, let us kill him and get his inheritance!’ 39 So they took him and threw him out of the vineyard and killed him. 40 Therefore, when the owner of the vineyard comes, what will he do to those cultivators?” 41 They said to him: “Because they are evil, he will bring an evil destruction upon them and will let out the vineyard to other cultivators, who will render him the fruits when they become due.”

42 Jesus said to them: “Did YOU never read in the Scriptures, ‘The stone that the builders rejected is the one that has become the chief cornerstone. From Jehovah this has come to be, and it is marvelous in our eyes’? 43 This is why I say to YOU, The kingdom of God will be taken from YOU and be given to a nation producing its fruits. 44 Also, the person falling upon this stone will be shattered. As for anyone upon whom it falls, it will pulverize him.”

45 Now when the chief priests and the Pharisees had heard his illustrations, they took note that he was speaking about them. 46 But, although they were seeking to seize him, they feared the crowds, because these held him to be a prophet.

Matthew

25 “Then the kingdom of the heavens will become like ten virgins that took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom. 2 Five of them were foolish, and five were discreet. 3 For the foolish took their lamps but took no oil with them, 4 whereas the discreet took oil in their receptacles with their lamps. 5 While the bridegroom was delaying, they all nodded and went to sleep. 6 Right in the middle of the night there arose a cry, ‘Here is the bridegroom! Be on YOUR way out to meet him.’ 7 Then all those virgins rose and put their lamps in order. 8 The foolish said to the discreet, ‘Give us some of YOUR oil, because our lamps are about to go out.’ 9 The discreet answered with the words, ‘Perhaps there may not be quite enough for us and YOU. Be on YOUR way, instead, to those who sell it and buy for yourselves.’ 10 While they were going off to buy, the bridegroom arrived, and the virgins that were ready went in with him to the marriage feast; and the door was shut. 11 Afterwards the rest of the virgins also came, saying, ‘Sir, sir, open to us!’ 12 In answer he said, ‘I tell YOU the truth, I do not know YOU.’

13 “Keep on the watch, therefore, because YOU know neither the day nor the hour.

14 “For it is just as when a man, about to travel abroad, summoned slaves of his and committed to them his belongings. 15 And to one he gave five talents, to another two, to still another one, to each one according to his own ability, and he went abroad. 16 Immediately the one that received the five talents went his way and did business with them and gained five more. 17 In the same way the one that received the two gained two more. 18 But the one that received just one went off, and dug in the ground and hid the silver money of his master.

19 “After a long time the master of those slaves came and settled accounts with them. 20 So the one that had received five talents came forward and brought five additional talents, saying, ‘Master, you committed five talents to me; see, I gained five talents more.’ 21 His master said to him, ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’ 22 Next the one that had received the two talents came forward and said, ‘Master, you committed to me two talents; see, I gained two talents more.’ 23 His master said to him, ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’

24 “Finally the one that had received the one talent came forward and said, ‘Master, I knew you to be an exacting man, reaping where you did not sow and gathering where you did not winnow. 25 So I grew afraid and went off and hid your talent in the ground. Here you have what is yours.’ 26 In reply his master said to him, ‘Wicked and sluggish slave, you knew, did you, that I reaped where I did not sow and gathered where I did not winnow? 27 Well, then, you ought to have deposited my silver monies with the bankers, and on my arrival I would be receiving what is mine with interest.

28 “‘Therefore TAKE away the talent from him and give it to him that has the ten talents. 29 For to everyone that has, more will be given and he will have abundance; but as for him that does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him. 30 And throw the good-for-nothing slave out into the darkness outside. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.’

31 “When the Son of man arrives in his glory, and all the angels with him, then he will sit down on his glorious throne. 32 And all the nations will be gathered before him, and he will separate people one from another, just as a shepherd separates the sheep from the goats. 33 And he will put the sheep on his right hand, but the goats on his left.

34 “Then the king will say to those on his right, ‘Come, YOU who have been blessed by my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for YOU from the founding of the world. 35 For I became hungry and YOU gave me something to eat; I got thirsty and YOU gave me something to drink. I was a stranger and YOU received me hospitably; 36 naked, and YOU clothed me. I fell sick and YOU looked after me. I was in prison and YOU came to me.’ 37 Then the righteous ones will answer him with the words, ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry and feed you, or thirsty, and give you something to drink? 38 When did we see you a stranger and receive you hospitably, or naked, and clothe you? 39 When did we see you sick or in prison and go to you?’ 40 And in reply the king will say to them, ‘Truly I say to YOU, To the extent that YOU did it to one of the least of these my brothers, YOU did it to me.’

41 “Then he will say, in turn, to those on his left, ‘Be on YOUR way from me, YOU who have been cursed, into the everlasting fire prepared for the Devil and his angels. 42 For I became hungry, but YOU gave me nothing to eat, and I got thirsty, but YOU gave me nothing to drink. 43 I was a stranger, but YOU did not receive me hospitably; naked, but YOU did not clothe me; sick and in prison, but YOU did not look after me.’ 44 Then they also will answer with the words, ‘Lord, when did we see you hungry or thirsty or a stranger or naked or sick or in prison and did not minister to you?’ 45 Then he will answer them with the words, ‘Truly I say to YOU, To the extent that YOU did not do it to one of these least ones, YOU did not do it to me.’ 46 And these will depart into everlasting cutting-off, but the righteous ones into everlasting life.”

Matthew

26 Now when Jesus had finished all these sayings, he said to his disciples: 2 “YOU know that two days from now the passover occurs, and the Son of man is to be delivered up to be impaled.”

3 Then the chief priests and the older men of the people gathered together in the courtyard of the high priest who was called Ca′ia·phas, 4 and took counsel together to seize Jesus by crafty device and kill him. 5 However, they kept saying: “Not at the festival, in order that no uproar may arise among the people.”

6 While Jesus happened to be in Beth′a·ny in the house of Simon the leper, 7 a woman with an alabaster case of costly perfumed oil approached him, and she began pouring it upon his head as he was reclining at the table. 8 On seeing this the disciples became indignant and said: “Why this waste? 9 For this could have been sold for a great deal and been given to poor people.” 10 Aware of this, Jesus said to them: “Why do YOU try to make trouble for the woman? For she did a fine deed toward me. 11 For YOU always have the poor with YOU, but YOU will not always have me. 12 For when this woman put this perfumed oil upon my body, she did it for the preparation of me for burial. 13 Truly I say to YOU, Wherever this good news is preached in all the world, what this woman did shall also be told as a remembrance of her.”

14 Then one of the twelve, the one called Judas Is·car′i·ot, went to the chief priests 15 and said: “What will YOU give me to betray him to YOU?” They stipulated to him thirty silver pieces. 16 So from then on he kept seeking a good opportunity to betray him.

17 On the first day of the unfermented cakes the disciples came up to Jesus, saying: “Where do you want us to prepare for you to eat the passover?” 18 He said: “Go into the city to So-and-so and say to him, The Teacher says, ‘My appointed time is near; I will celebrate the passover with my disciples at your home.’” 19 And the disciples did as Jesus ordered them, and they got things ready for the passover.

20 When, now, it had become evening, he was reclining at the table with the twelve disciples. 21 While they were eating, he said: “Truly I say to YOU, One of YOU will betray me.” 22 Being very much grieved at this, they commenced each and every one to say to him: “Lord, it is not I, is it?” 23 In reply he said: “He that dips his hand with me in the bowl is the one that will betray me. 24 True, the Son of man is going away, just as it is written concerning him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of man is betrayed! It would have been finer for him if that man had not been born.” 25 By way of reply Judas, who was about to betray him, said: “It is not I, is it, Rabbi?” He said to him: “You yourself said it.”

26 As they continued eating, Jesus took a loaf and, after saying a blessing, he broke it and, giving it to the disciples, he said: “TAKE, eat. This means my body.” 27 Also, he took a cup and, having given thanks, he gave it to them, saying: “Drink out of it, all of YOU; 28 for this means my ‘blood of the covenant,’ which is to be poured out in behalf of many for forgiveness of sins. 29 But I tell YOU, I will by no means drink henceforth any of this product of the vine until that day when I drink it new with YOU in the kingdom of my Father.” 30 Finally, after singing praises, they went out to the Mount of Olives.

31 Then Jesus said to them: “All of YOU will be stumbled in connection with me on this night, for it is written, ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered about.’ 32 But after I have been raised up, I will go ahead of YOU into Gal′i·lee.” 33 But Peter, in answer, said to him: “Although all the others are stumbled in connection with you, never will I be stumbled!” 34 Jesus said to him: “Truly I say to you, On this night, before a cock crows, you will disown me three times.” 35 Peter said to him: “Even if I should have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” All the other disciples also said the same thing.

36 Then Jesus came with them to the spot called Geth·sem′a·ne, and he said to the disciples: “Sit down here while I go over there and pray.” 37 And taking along Peter and the two sons of Zeb′e·dee, he started to be grieved and to be sorely troubled. 38 Then he said to them: “My soul is deeply grieved, even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch with me.” 39 And going a little way forward, he fell upon his face, praying and saying: “My Father, if it is possible, let this cup pass away from me. Yet, not as I will, but as you will.”

40 And he came to the disciples and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Could YOU men not so much as watch one hour with me? 41 Keep on the watch and pray continually, that YOU may not enter into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager, but the flesh is weak.” 42 Again, for the second time, he went off and prayed, saying: “My Father, if it is not possible for this to pass away except I drink it, let your will take place.” 43 And he came again and found them sleeping, for their eyes were heavy. 44 So leaving them, he again went off and prayed for the third time, saying once more the same word. 45 Then he came to the disciples and said to them: “At such a time as this YOU are sleeping and taking YOUR rest! Look! The hour has drawn near for the Son of man to be betrayed into the hands of sinners. 46 Get up, let us go. Look! My betrayer has drawn near.” 47 And while he was yet speaking, look! Judas, one of the twelve, came and with him a great crowd with swords and clubs from the chief priests and older men of the people.

48 Now his betrayer had given them a sign, saying: “Whoever it is I kiss, this is he; take him into custody.” 49 And going straight up to Jesus he said: “Good day, Rabbi!” and kissed him very tenderly. 50 But Jesus said to him: “Fellow, for what purpose are you present?” Then they came forward and laid hands on Jesus and took him into custody. 51 But, look! one of those with Jesus reached out his hand and drew his sword and struck the slave of the high priest and took off his ear. 52 Then Jesus said to him: “Return your sword to its place, for all those who take the sword will perish by the sword. 53 Or do you think that I cannot appeal to my Father to supply me at this moment more than twelve legions of angels? 54 In that case, how would the Scriptures be fulfilled that it must take place this way?” 55 In that hour Jesus said to the crowds: “Have YOU come out with swords and clubs as against a robber to arrest me? Day after day I used to sit in the temple teaching, and yet YOU did not take me into custody. 56 But all this has taken place for the scriptures of the prophets to be fulfilled.” Then all the disciples abandoned him and fled.

57 Those who took Jesus into custody led him away to Ca′ia·phas the high priest, where the scribes and the older men were gathered together. 58 But Peter kept following him at a good distance, as far as the courtyard of the high priest, and, after going inside, he was sitting with the house attendants to see the outcome.

59 Meantime the chief priests and the entire San′he·drin were looking for false witness against Jesus in order to put him to death, 60 but they found none, although many false witnesses came forward. Later on two came forward 61 and said: “This man said, ‘I am able to throw down the temple of God and build it up in three days.’” 62 With that the high priest stood up and said to him: “Have you no answer? What is it these are testifying against you?” 63 But Jesus kept silent. So the high priest said to him: “By the living God I put you under oath to tell us whether you are the Christ the Son of God!” 64 Jesus said to him: “You yourself said it. Yet I say to YOU men, From henceforth YOU will see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of power and coming on the clouds of heaven.” 65 Then the high priest ripped his outer garments, saying: “He has blasphemed! What further need do we have of witnesses? See! Now YOU have heard the blasphemy. 66 What is YOUR opinion?” They returned answer: “He is liable to death.” 67 Then they spit into his face and hit him with their fists. Others slapped him in the face, 68 saying: “Prophesy to us, you Christ. Who is it that struck you?”

69 Now Peter was sitting outside in the courtyard; and a servant girl came up to him, saying: “You, too, were with Jesus the Gal·i·le′an!” 70 But he denied it before them all, saying: “I do not know what you are talking about.” 71 After he had gone out to the gatehouse, another girl noticed him and said to those there: “This man was with Jesus the Naz·a·rene′.” 72 And again he denied it, with an oath: “I do not know the man!” 73 After a little while those standing around came up and said to Peter: “Certainly you also are one of them, for, in fact, your dialect gives you away.” 74 Then he started to curse and swear: “I do not know the man!” And immediately a cock crowed. 75 And Peter called to mind the saying Jesus spoke, namely: “Before a cock crows, you will disown me three times.” And he went outside and wept bitterly.

Mark

6 And he departed from there and came into his home territory, and his disciples followed him. 2 When it became sabbath, he started teaching in the synagogue; and the greater number of those listening were astounded and said: “Where did this man get these things? And why should this wisdom have been given this man, and such powerful works be performed through his hands? 3 This is the carpenter the son of Mary and the brother of James and Joseph and Judas and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble at him. 4 But Jesus went on to say to them: “A prophet is not unhonored except in his home territory and among his relatives and in his own house.” 5 So he was able to do no powerful work there except to lay his hands upon a few sickly ones and cure them. 6 Indeed, he wondered at their lack of faith. And he went round about to the villages in a circuit, teaching.

7 Now he summoned the twelve, and he initiated sending them out two by two, and he began to give them authority over the unclean spirits. 8 Also, he gave them orders to carry nothing for the trip except a staff alone, no bread, no food pouch, no copper money in their girdle purses, 9 but to bind on sandals, and not to wear two undergarments. 10 Further, he said to them: “Wherever YOU enter into a home, stay there until YOU go out of that place. 11 And wherever a place will not receive YOU nor hear YOU, on going out from there shake off the dirt that is beneath YOUR feet for a witness to them.” 12 So they set out and preached in order that people might repent; 13 and they would expel many demons and grease many sickly people with oil and cure them.

14 Now it got to the ears of King Herod, for the name of Jesus became public, and people were saying: “John the baptizer has been raised from the dead, and on that account the powerful works are operating in him.” 15 But others were saying: “It is E·li′jah.” Still others were saying: “It is a prophet like one of the prophets.” 16 But when Herod heard it he began to say: “The John that I beheaded, this one has been raised up.” 17 For Herod himself had sent out and arrested John and bound him in prison on account of He·ro′di·as the wife of Philip his brother, because he had married her. 18 For John had repeatedly said to Herod: “It is not lawful for you to be having the wife of your brother.” 19 But He·ro′di·as was nursing a grudge against him and was wanting to kill him, but could not. 20 For Herod stood in fear of John, knowing him to be a righteous and holy man; and he was keeping him safe. And after hearing him he was at a great loss what to do, yet he continued to hear him gladly.

21 But a convenient day came along when Herod spread an evening meal on his birthday for his top-ranking men and the military commanders and the foremost ones of Gal′i·lee. 22 And the daughter of this very He·ro′di·as came in and danced and pleased Herod and those reclining with him. The king said to the maiden: “Ask me for whatever you want, and I will give it to you.” 23 Yes, he swore to her: “Whatever you ask me for, I will give it to you, up to half my kingdom.” 24 And she went out and said to her mother: “What should I ask for?” She said: “The head of John the baptizer.” 25 Immediately she went in with haste to the king and made her request, saying: “I want you to give me right away on a platter the head of John the Baptist.” 26 Although he became deeply grieved, yet the king did not want to disregard her, in view of the oaths and those reclining at the table. 27 So the king immediately dispatched a body guardsman and commanded him to bring his head. And he went off and beheaded him in the prison 28 and brought his head on a platter, and he gave it to the maiden, and the maiden gave it to her mother. 29 When his disciples heard of it they came and took up his corpse and laid it in a memorial tomb.

30 And the apostles gathered together before Jesus and reported to him all the things they had done and taught. 31 And he said to them: “Come, YOU yourselves, privately into a lonely place and rest up a bit.” For there were many coming and going, and they had no leisure time even to eat a meal. 32 So off they went in the boat for a lonely place to themselves. 33 But people saw them going and many got to know it, and from all the cities they ran there together on foot and got ahead of them. 34 Well, on getting out, he saw a great crowd, but he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

35 By now the hour had grown late, and his disciples came up to him and began to say: “The place is isolated, and the hour is already late. 36 Send them away, that they may go off into the countryside and villages round about and buy themselves something to eat.” 37 In reply he said to them: “YOU give them something to eat.” At this they said to him: “Shall we go off and buy two hundred de·nar′i·i worth of loaves and give them to the people to eat?” 38 He said to them: “How many loaves have YOU? Go see!” After ascertaining it, they said: “Five, besides two fishes.” 39 And he instructed all the people to recline by companies on the green grass. 40 And they laid themselves down in groups of a hundred and of fifty. 41 Taking now the five loaves and the two fishes he looked up to heaven and said a blessing, and broke the loaves up and began giving them to the disciples, that these might place them before the people; and he divided up the two fishes for all. 42 So they all ate and were satisfied; 43 and they took up fragments, twelve baskets full, aside from the fishes. 44 Furthermore, those who ate of the loaves were five thousand men.

45 And, without delay, he compelled his disciples to board the boat and go on ahead to the opposite shore toward Beth·sa′i·da, while he himself dismissed the crowd. 46 But after saying good-bye to them he went off into a mountain to pray. 47 Evening having now fallen, the boat was in the midst of the sea, but he was alone on the land. 48 And when he saw them being hard put to it in their rowing, for the wind was against them, about the fourth watch of the night he came toward them, walking on the sea; but he was inclined to pass them by. 49 At catching sight of him walking on the sea they thought: “It is an apparition!” and they cried aloud. 50 For they all saw him and were troubled. But immediately he spoke with them, and he said to them: “Take courage, it is I; have no fear.” 51 And he got up into the boat with them, and the wind abated. At this they were very much amazed within themselves, 52 for they had not grasped the meaning of the loaves, but their hearts continued dull of understanding.

53 And when they got across to land, they came into Gen·nes′a·ret and anchored ship nearby. 54 But as soon as they got out of the boat, people recognized him, 55 and they ran around all that region and started to carry about on cots those who were ailing to where they heard he was. 56 And wherever he would enter into villages or cities or countryside they would place the sick ones in the marketplaces, and they would plead with him that they might touch just the fringe of his outer garment. And as many as did touch it were made well.

Mark

13 As he was going out of the temple one of his disciples said to him: “Teacher, see! what sort of stones and what sort of buildings!” 2 However, Jesus said to him: “Do you behold these great buildings? By no means will a stone be left here upon a stone and not be thrown down.”

3 And as he was sitting on the Mount of Olives with the temple in view, Peter and James and John and Andrew began to ask him privately: 4 “Tell us, When will these things be, and what will be the sign when all these things are destined to come to a conclusion?” 5 So Jesus started to say to them: “Look out that nobody misleads YOU. 6 Many will come on the basis of my name, saying, ‘I am he,’ and will mislead many. 7 Moreover, when YOU hear of wars and reports of wars, do not be terrified; these things must take place, but the end is not yet.

8 “For nation will rise against nation and kingdom against kingdom, there will be earthquakes in one place after another, there will be food shortages. These are a beginning of pangs of distress.

9 “As for YOU, look out for yourselves; people will deliver YOU up to local courts, and YOU will be beaten in synagogues and be put on the stand before governors and kings for my sake, for a witness to them. 10 Also, in all the nations the good news has to be preached first. 11 But when they are leading YOU along to deliver YOU up, do not be anxious beforehand about what to speak; but whatever is given YOU in that hour, speak this, for YOU are not the ones speaking, but the holy spirit is. 12 Furthermore, brother will deliver brother over to death, and a father a child, and children will rise up against parents and have them put to death; 13 and YOU will be objects of hatred by all people on account of my name. But he that has endured to the end is the one that will be saved.

14 “However, when YOU catch sight of the disgusting thing that causes desolation standing where it ought not (let the reader use discernment), then let those in Ju·de′a begin fleeing to the mountains. 15 Let the man on the housetop not come down, nor go inside to take anything out of his house; 16 and let the man in the field not return to the things behind to pick up his outer garment. 17 Woe to the pregnant women and those suckling a baby in those days! 18 Keep praying that it may not occur in wintertime; 19 for those days will be days of a tribulation such as has not occurred from the beginning of the creation which God created until that time, and will not occur again. 20 In fact, unless Jehovah had cut short the days, no flesh would be saved. But on account of the chosen ones whom he has chosen he has cut short the days.

21 “Then, too, if anyone says to YOU, ‘See! Here is the Christ,’ ‘See! There he is,’ do not believe it. 22 For false Christs and false prophets will arise and will give signs and wonders to lead astray, if possible, the chosen ones. 23 YOU, then, watch out; I have told YOU all things beforehand.

24 “But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light, 25 and the stars will be falling out of heaven, and the powers that are in the heavens will be shaken. 26 And then they will see the Son of man coming in clouds with great power and glory. 27 And then he will send forth the angels and will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from earth’s extremity to heaven’s extremity.

28 “Now from the fig tree learn the illustration: Just as soon as its young branch grows tender and puts forth its leaves, YOU know that summer is near. 29 Likewise also YOU, when YOU see these things happening, know that he is near, at the doors. 30 Truly I say to YOU that this generation will by no means pass away until all these things happen. 31 Heaven and earth will pass away, but my words will not pass away.

32 “Concerning that day or the hour nobody knows, neither the angels in heaven nor the Son, but the Father. 33 Keep looking, keep awake, for YOU do not know when the appointed time is. 34 It is like a man traveling abroad that left his house and gave the authority to his slaves, to each one his work, and commanded the doorkeeper to keep on the watch. 35 Therefore keep on the watch, for YOU do not know when the master of the house is coming, whether late in the day or at midnight or at cockcrowing or early in the morning; 36 in order that when he arrives suddenly, he does not find YOU sleeping. 37 But what I say to YOU I say to all, Keep on the watch.”

Mark

14 Now the passover and the festival of unfermented cakes was two days later. And the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how to seize him by crafty device and kill him; 2 for they repeatedly said: “Not at the festival; perhaps there might be an uproar of the people.”

3 And while he was at Beth′a·ny in the house of Simon the leper, as he was reclining at the meal, a woman came with an alabaster case of perfumed oil, genuine nard, very expensive. Breaking open the alabaster case she began to pour it upon his head. 4 At this there were some expressing indignation among themselves: “Why has this waste of the perfumed oil taken place? 5 For this perfumed oil could have been sold for upward of three hundred de·nar′i·i and been given to the poor!” And they were feeling great displeasure at her. 6 But Jesus said: “Let her alone. Why do YOU try to make trouble for her? She did a fine deed toward me. 7 For YOU always have the poor with YOU, and whenever YOU want to YOU can always do them good, but me YOU do not have always. 8 She did what she could; she undertook beforehand to put perfumed oil on my body in view of the burial. 9 Truly I say to YOU, Wherever the good news is preached in all the world, what this woman did shall also be told as a remembrance of her.”

10 And Judas Is·car′i·ot, one of the twelve, went off to the chief priests in order to betray him to them. 11 When they heard it, they rejoiced and promised to give him silver money. So he began seeking how to betray him conveniently.

12 Now on the first day of unfermented cakes, when they customarily sacrificed the passover victim, his disciples said to him: “Where do you want us to go and prepare for you to eat the passover?” 13 With that he sent forth two of his disciples and said to them: “Go into the city, and a man carrying an earthenware vessel of water will encounter YOU. Follow him, 14 and wherever he goes inside say to the householder, ‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room for me where I may eat the passover with my disciples?”’ 15 And he will show YOU a large upper room, furnished in preparation; and there prepare for us.” 16 So the disciples went out, and they entered the city and found it just as he said to them; and they prepared for the passover.

17 After evening had fallen he came with the twelve. 18 And as they were reclining at the table and eating, Jesus said: “Truly I say to YOU, One of YOU, who is eating with me, will betray me.” 19 They started to be grieved and to say to him one by one: “It is not I, is it?” 20 He said to them: “It is one of the twelve, who is dipping with me into the common bowl. 21 True, the Son of man is going away, just as it is written concerning him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of man is betrayed! It would have been finer for that man if he had not been born.”

22 And as they continued eating, he took a loaf, said a blessing, broke it and gave it to them, and said: “Take it, this means my body.” 23 And taking a cup, he offered thanks and gave it to them, and they all drank out of it. 24 And he said to them: “This means my ‘blood of the covenant,’ which is to be poured out in behalf of many. 25 Truly I say to YOU, I shall by no means drink anymore of the product of the vine until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God.” 26 Finally, after singing praises, they went out to the Mount of Olives.

27 And Jesus said to them: “YOU will all be stumbled, because it is written, ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered about.’ 28 But after I have been raised up I will go ahead of YOU into Gal′i·lee.” 29 But Peter said to him: “Even if all the others are stumbled, yet I will not be.” 30 At that Jesus said to him: “Truly I say to you, You today, yes, this night, before a cock crows twice, even you will disown me three times.” 31 But he began to say profusely: “If I have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” Also, all the others began saying the same thing.

32 So they came to a spot named Geth·sem′a·ne, and he said to his disciples: “Sit down here while I pray.” 33 And he took Peter and James and John along with him, and he started to be stunned and to be sorely troubled. 34 And he said to them: “My soul is deeply grieved, even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch.” 35 And going a little way forward he proceeded to fall on the ground and began praying that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him. 36 And he went on to say: “Abba, Father, all things are possible to you; remove this cup from me. Yet not what I want, but what you want.” 37 And he came and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Simon, are you sleeping? Did you not have strength to keep on the watch one hour? 38 Men, keep on the watch and praying, in order that YOU do not come into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager, but the flesh is weak.” 39 And he went away again and prayed, saying the same word. 40 And again he came and found them sleeping, for their eyes were weighed down, and so they did not know what to answer him. 41 And he came the third time and said to them: “At such a time as this YOU are sleeping and taking YOUR rest! It is enough! The hour has come! Look! The Son of man is betrayed into the hands of sinners. 42 Get up, let us go. Look! My betrayer has drawn near.”

43 And immediately, while he was yet speaking, Judas, one of the twelve, arrived and with him a crowd with swords and clubs from the chief priests and the scribes and the older men. 44 Now his betrayer had given them an agreed sign, saying: “Whoever it is I kiss, this is he; take him into custody and lead him away safely.” 45 And he came straight up and approached him and said: “Rabbi!” and kissed him very tenderly. 46 So they laid their hands upon him and took him into custody. 47 However, a certain one of those standing by drew his sword and struck the slave of the high priest and took his ear off. 48 But in response Jesus said to them: “Did YOU come out with swords and clubs as against a robber to arrest me? 49 Day after day I was with YOU in the temple teaching, and yet YOU did not take me into custody. Nevertheless, it is in order that the Scriptures may be fulfilled.”

50 And they all abandoned him and fled. 51 But a certain young man wearing a fine linen garment over his naked body began to follow him nearby; and they tried to seize him, 52 but he left his linen garment behind and got away naked.

53 They now led Jesus away to the high priest, and all the chief priests and the older men and the scribes assembled. 54 But Peter, from a good distance, followed him as far as in the courtyard of the high priest; and he was sitting together with the house attendants and warming himself before a bright fire. 55 Meantime the chief priests and the whole San′he·drin were looking for testimony against Jesus to put him to death, but they were not finding any. 56 Many, indeed, were giving false witness against him, but their testimonies were not in agreement. 57 Also, certain ones were rising and bearing false witness against him, saying: 58 “We heard him say, ‘I will throw down this temple that was made with hands and in three days I will build another not made with hands.’” 59 But neither on these grounds was their testimony in agreement.

60 Finally the high priest rose in their midst and questioned Jesus, saying: “Do you say nothing in reply? What is it these are testifying against you?” 61 But he kept silent and made no reply at all. Again the high priest began to question him and said to him: “Are you the Christ the Son of the Blessed One?” 62 Then Jesus said: “I am; and YOU persons will see the Son of man sitting at the right hand of power and coming with the clouds of heaven.” 63 At this the high priest ripped his inner garments and said: “What further need do we have of witnesses? 64 YOU heard the blasphemy. What is evident to YOU?” They all condemned him to be liable to death. 65 And some started to spit on him and to cover his whole face and hit him with their fists and say to him: “Prophesy!” And, slapping him in the face, the court attendants took him.

66 Now while Peter was below in the courtyard, one of the servant girls of the high priest came, 67 and, seeing Peter warming himself, she looked straight at him and said: “You, too, were with the Naz·a·rene′, this Jesus.” 68 But he denied it, saying: “Neither do I know him nor do I understand what you are saying,” and he went outside to the vestibule. 69 There the servant girl, at the sight of him, started again to say to those standing by: “This is one of them.” 70 Again he was denying it. And once more after a little while those standing by began saying to Peter: “Certainly you are one of them, for, in fact, you are a Gal·i·le′an.” 71 But he commenced to curse and swear: “I do not know this man of whom YOU speak.” 72 And immediately a cock crowed a second time; and Peter recalled the saying that Jesus spoke to him: “Before a cock crows twice, you will disown me three times.” And he broke down and gave way to weeping.

Luke

5 On an occasion when the crowd was pressing close upon him and listening to the word of God, he was standing beside the lake of Gen·nes′a·ret. 2 And he saw two boats docked at the lakeside, but the fishermen had got out of them and were washing off their nets. 3 Going aboard one of the boats, which was Simon’s, he asked him to pull away a bit from land. Then he sat down, and from the boat he began teaching the crowds. 4 When he ceased speaking, he said to Simon: “Pull out to where it is deep, and YOU men let down YOUR nets for a catch.” 5 But Simon in reply said: “Instructor, for a whole night we toiled and took nothing, but at your bidding I will lower the nets.” 6 Well, when they did this, they enclosed a great multitude of fish. In fact, their nets began ripping apart. 7 So they motioned to their partners in the other boat to come and assist them; and they did come, and they filled both boats, so that these began to sink. 8 Seeing this, Simon Peter fell down at the knees of Jesus, saying: “Depart from me, because I am a sinful man, Lord.” 9 For at the catch of fish which they took up astonishment overwhelmed him and all those with him, 10 and likewise both James and John, Zeb′e·dee’s sons, who were sharers with Simon. But Jesus said to Simon: “Stop being afraid. From now on you will be catching men alive.” 11 So they brought the boats back to land, and abandoned everything and followed him.

12 On a further occasion while he was in one of the cities, look! a man full of leprosy! When he caught sight of Jesus he fell upon his face and begged him, saying: “Lord, if you just want to, you can make me clean.” 13 And so, stretching out his hand, he touched him, saying: “I want to. Be made clean.” And immediately the leprosy vanished from him. 14 And he gave the man orders to tell nobody: “But go off and show yourself to the priest, and make an offering in connection with your cleansing, just as Moses directed, for a witness to them.” 15 But the word about him was spreading the more, and great crowds would come together to listen and to be cured of their sicknesses. 16 However, he continued in retirement in the deserts and praying.

17 In the course of one of the days he was teaching, and Pharisees and teachers of the law who had come out of every village of Gal′i·lee and Ju·de′a and Jerusalem were sitting there; and Jehovah’s power was there for him to do healing. 18 And, look! men carrying on a bed a man who was paralyzed, and they were seeking a way to bring him in and place him before him. 19 So, not finding a way to bring him in on account of the crowd, they climbed up to the roof, and through the tiling they let him down with the little bed among those in front of Jesus. 20 And when he saw their faith he said: “Man, your sins are forgiven you.” 21 Thereupon the scribes and the Pharisees started to reason, saying: “Who is this that is speaking blasphemies? Who can forgive sins except God alone?” 22 But Jesus, discerning their reasonings, said in answer to them: “What are YOU reasoning out in YOUR hearts? 23 Which is easier, to say, ‘Your sins are forgiven you,’ or to say, ‘Get up and walk’? 24 But in order for YOU to know that the Son of man has authority on the earth to forgive sins—” he said to the paralyzed man: “I say to you, Get up and pick up your little bed and be on your way home.” 25 And instantly he rose up before them, picked up what he used to lie on and went off to his home, glorifying God. 26 Then an ecstasy seized one and all, and they began to glorify God, and they became filled with fear, saying: “We have seen strange things today!”

27 Now after these things he went out and beheld a tax collector named Le′vi sitting at the tax office, and he said to him: “Be my follower.” 28 And leaving everything behind he rose up and went following him. 29 Also, Le′vi spread a big reception feast for him in his house; and there was a great crowd of tax collectors and others who were with them reclining at the meal. 30 At this the Pharisees and their scribes began murmuring to his disciples, saying: “Why is it YOU eat and drink with tax collectors and sinners?” 31 In reply Jesus said to them: “Those who are healthy do not need a physician, but those who are ailing do. 32 I have come to call, not righteous persons, but sinners to repentance.”

33 They said to him: “The disciples of John fast frequently and offer supplications, and so do those of the Pharisees, but yours eat and drink.” 34 Jesus said to them: “YOU cannot make the friends of the bridegroom fast while the bridegroom is with them, can YOU? 35 Yet days will come when the bridegroom will indeed be taken away from them; then they will fast in those days.”

36 Further, he went on to give an illustration to them: “No one cuts a patch from a new outer garment and sews it onto an old outer garment; but if he does, then both the new patch tears away and the patch from the new garment does not match the old. 37 Moreover, no one puts new wine into old wineskins; but if he does, then the new wine will burst the wineskins, and it will be spilled out and the wineskins will be ruined. 38 But new wine must be put into new wineskins. 39 No one that has drunk old wine wants new; for he says, ‘The old is nice.’”

Luke

8 Shortly afterwards he went journeying from city to city and from village to village, preaching and declaring the good news of the kingdom of God. And the twelve were with him, 2 and certain women that had been cured of wicked spirits and sicknesses, Mary the so-called Mag′da·lene, from whom seven demons had come out, 3 and Jo·an′na the wife of Chu′za, Herod’s man in charge, and Su·san′na and many other women, who were ministering to them from their belongings.

4 Now when a great crowd had collected together with those that went to him from city after city, he spoke by means of an illustration: 5 “A sower went out to sow his seed. Well, as he was sowing, some of it fell alongside the road and was trampled down, and the birds of heaven ate it up. 6 Some other landed upon the rock-mass, and, after sprouting, it dried up because of not having moisture. 7 Some other fell among the thorns, and the thorns that grew up with it choked it off. 8 Some other fell upon the good soil, and, after sprouting, it produced fruit a hundredfold.” As he told these things, he proceeded to call out: “Let him that has ears to listen, listen.”

9 But his disciples began to ask him what this illustration might mean. 10 He said: “To YOU it is granted to understand the sacred secrets of the kingdom of God, but for the rest it is in illustrations, in order that, though looking, they may look in vain and, though hearing, they may not get the meaning. 11 Now the illustration means this: The seed is the word of God. 12 Those alongside the road are the ones that have heard, then the Devil comes and takes the word away from their hearts in order that they may not believe and be saved. 13 Those upon the rock-mass are the ones who, when they hear it, receive the word with joy, but these have no root; they believe for a season, but in a season of testing they fall away. 14 As for that which fell among the thorns, these are the ones that have heard, but, by being carried away by anxieties and riches and pleasures of this life, they are completely choked and bring nothing to perfection. 15 As for that on the fine soil, these are the ones that, after hearing the word with a fine and good heart, retain it and bear fruit with endurance.

16 “No one, after lighting a lamp, covers it with a vessel or puts it underneath a bed, but he puts it on a lampstand, that those stepping in may behold the light. 17 For there is nothing hidden that will not become manifest, neither anything carefully concealed that will never become known and never come into the open. 18 Therefore, pay attention to how YOU listen; for whoever has, more will be given him, but whoever does not have, even what he imagines he has will be taken away from him.”

19 Now his mother and brothers came toward him, but they were unable to get to him because of the crowd. 20 However, it was reported to him: “Your mother and your brothers are standing outside wanting to see you.” 21 In reply he said to them: “My mother and my brothers are these who hear the word of God and do it.”

22 In the course of one of the days he and his disciples got into a boat, and he said to them: “Let us cross to the other side of the lake.” So they set sail. 23 But as they were sailing he fell asleep. Now a violent windstorm descended upon the lake, and they began to fill up with water and to be in danger. 24 Finally they went to him and roused him, saying: “Instructor, Instructor, we are about to perish!” Rousing himself, he rebuked the wind and the raging of the water, and they subsided, and a calm set in. 25 Then he said to them: “Where is YOUR faith?” But struck with fear, they marveled, saying to one another: “Who really is this, for he orders even the winds and the water, and they obey him?”

26 And they put in to shore in the country of the Ger′a·senes, which is on the side opposite Gal′i·lee. 27 But as he got out onto land a certain man from the city who had demons met him. And for a considerable time he had not worn clothing, and he was staying, not at home, but among the tombs. 28 At the sight of Jesus he cried aloud and fell down before him, and with a loud voice he said: “What have I to do with you, Jesus Son of the Most High God? I beg you, do not torment me.” 29 (For he had been ordering the unclean spirit to come out of the man. For over a long time it had held him fast, and he was repeatedly bound with chains and fetters under guard, but he would burst the bonds and be driven by the demon into the lonely places.) 30 Jesus asked him: “What is your name?” He said: “Legion,” because many demons had entered into him. 31 And they kept entreating him not to order them to go away into the abyss. 32 Now a herd of a considerable number of swine was feeding there on the mountain; so they entreated him to permit them to enter into those. And he gave them permission. 33 Then the demons went out of the man and entered into the swine, and the herd rushed over the precipice into the lake and drowned. 34 But when the herders saw what had happened, they fled and reported it to the city and to the countryside.

35 Then people turned out to see what had happened, and they came to Jesus and found the man from whom the demons came out, clothed and in his sound mind, sitting at the feet of Jesus; and they became fearful. 36 Those who had seen it reported to them how the demon-possessed man had been made well. 37 So all the multitude from the surrounding country of the Ger′a·senes asked him to get away from them, because they were in the grip of great fear. Then he went aboard the boat and turned away. 38 However, the man from whom the demons had gone out kept begging to continue with him; but he dismissed the man, saying: 39 “Be on your way back home, and keep on relating what things God did for you.” Accordingly he went away, proclaiming throughout the whole city what things Jesus did for him.

40 When Jesus got back, the crowd received him kindly, for they were all expecting him. 41 But, look! a man named Ja′i·rus came, and this man was a presiding officer of the synagogue. And he fell at the feet of Jesus and began to entreat him to enter into his house, 42 because he had an only-begotten daughter about twelve years old and she was dying.

As he was going the crowds thronged him. 43 And a woman, subject to a flow of blood for twelve years, who had not been able to get a cure from anyone, 44 approached from behind and touched the fringe of his outer garment, and instantly her flow of blood stopped. 45 So Jesus said: “Who was it that touched me?” When they were all denying it, Peter said: “Instructor, the crowds are hemming you in and closely pressing you.” 46 Yet Jesus said: “Someone touched me, for I perceived that power went out of me.” 47 Seeing that she had not escaped notice, the woman came trembling and fell down before him and disclosed before all the people the cause for which she touched him and how she was healed instantly. 48 But he said to her: “Daughter, your faith has made you well; go your way in peace.”

49 While he was yet speaking, a certain representative of the presiding officer of the synagogue came, saying: “Your daughter has died; do not bother the teacher any longer.” 50 On hearing this, Jesus answered him: “Have no fear, only put forth faith, and she will be saved.” 51 When he reached the house he did not let anyone go in with him except Peter and John and James and the girl’s father and mother. 52 But people were all weeping and beating themselves in grief for her. So he said: “STOP weeping, for she did not die but is sleeping.” 53 At this they began to laugh at him scornfully, because they knew she had died. 54 But he took her by the hand and called, saying: “Girl, get up!” 55 And her spirit returned, and she rose instantly, and he ordered something to be given her to eat. 56 Well, her parents were beside themselves; but he instructed them to tell no one what had happened.

Luke

14 And on an occasion when he went into the house of a certain one of the rulers of the Pharisees on the sabbath to eat a meal, they were closely watching him. 2 And, look! there was before him a certain man who had dropsy. 3 So in response Jesus spoke to those versed in the Law and to the Pharisees, saying: “Is it lawful on the sabbath to cure or not?” 4 But they kept silent. With that he took hold of the man, healed him and sent him away. 5 And he said to them: “Who of YOU, if his son or bull falls into a well, will not immediately pull him out on the sabbath day?” 6 And they were not able to answer back on these things.

7 He then went on to tell the invited men an illustration, as he marked how they were choosing the most prominent places for themselves, saying to them: 8 “When you are invited by someone to a marriage feast, do not lie down in the most prominent place. Perhaps someone more distinguished than you may at the time have been invited by him, 9 and he that invited you and him will come and say to you, ‘Let this man have the place.’ And then you will start off with shame to occupy the lowest place. 10 But when you are invited, go and recline in the lowest place, that when the man that has invited you comes he will say to you, ‘Friend, go on up higher.’ Then you will have honor in front of all your fellow guests. 11 For everyone that exalts himself will be humbled and he that humbles himself will be exalted.”

12 Next he proceeded to say also to the man that invited him: “When you spread a dinner or evening meal, do not call your friends or your brothers or your relatives or rich neighbors. Perhaps sometime they might also invite you in return and it would become a repayment to you. 13 But when you spread a feast, invite poor people, crippled, lame, blind; 14 and you will be happy, because they have nothing with which to repay you. For you will be repaid in the resurrection of the righteous ones.”

15 On hearing these things a certain one of the fellow guests said to him: “Happy is he who eats bread in the kingdom of God.”

16 Jesus said to him: “A certain man was spreading a grand evening meal, and he invited many. 17 And he sent his slave out at the hour of the evening meal to say to the invited ones, ‘Come, because things are now ready.’ 18 But they all in common started to beg off. The first said to him, ‘I bought a field and need to go out and see it; I ask you, Have me excused.’ 19 And another said, ‘I bought five yoke of cattle and am going to examine them; I ask you, Have me excused.’ 20 Still another said, ‘I just married a wife and for this reason I cannot come.’ 21 So the slave came up and reported these things to his master. Then the householder became wrathful and said to his slave, ‘Go out quickly into the broad ways and the lanes of the city, and bring in here the poor and crippled and blind and lame.’ 22 In time the slave said, ‘Master, what you ordered has been done, and yet there is room.’ 23 And the master said to the slave, ‘Go out into the roads and the fenced-in places, and compel them to come in, that my house may be filled. 24 For I say to YOU people, None of those men that were invited shall have a taste of my evening meal.’”

25 Now great crowds were traveling with him, and he turned and said to them: 26 “If anyone comes to me and does not hate his father and mother and wife and children and brothers and sisters, yes, and even his own soul, he cannot be my disciple. 27 Whoever is not carrying his torture stake and coming after me cannot be my disciple. 28 For example, who of YOU that wants to build a tower does not first sit down and calculate the expense, to see if he has enough to complete it? 29 Otherwise, he might lay its foundation but not be able to finish it, and all the onlookers might start to ridicule him, 30 saying, ‘This man started to build but was not able to finish.’ 31 Or what king, marching to meet another king in war, does not first sit down and take counsel whether he is able with ten thousand troops to cope with the one that comes against him with twenty thousand? 32 If, in fact, he cannot do so, then while that one is yet far away he sends out a body of ambassadors and sues for peace. 33 Thus, you may be sure, none of YOU that does not say good-bye to all his belongings can be my disciple.

34 “Salt, to be sure, is fine. But if even the salt loses its strength, with what will it be seasoned? 35 It is suitable neither for soil nor for manure. People throw it outside. Let him that has ears to listen, listen.”

Luke

16 Then he went on to say also to the disciples: “A certain man was rich and he had a steward, and this one was accused to him as handling his goods wastefully. 2 So he called him and said to him, ‘What is this I hear about you? Hand in the account of your stewardship, for you can no longer manage the house.’ 3 Then the steward said to himself, ‘What am I to do, seeing that my master will take the stewardship away from me? I am not strong enough to dig, I am ashamed to beg. 4 Ah! I know what I shall do, so that, when I am put out of the stewardship, people will receive me into their homes.’ 5 And calling to him each one of the debtors of his master he proceeded to say to the first, ‘How much are you owing my master?’ 6 He said, ‘A hundred bath measures of olive oil.’ He said to him, ‘Take your written agreement back and sit down and quickly write fifty.’ 7 Next, he said to another one, ‘Now you, how much are you owing?’ He said, ‘A hundred cor measures of wheat.’ He said to him, ‘Take your written agreement back and write eighty.’ 8 And his master commended the steward, though unrighteous, because he acted with practical wisdom; for the sons of this system of things are wiser in a practical way toward their own generation than the sons of the light are.

9 “Also, I say to YOU, Make friends for yourselves by means of the unrighteous riches, so that, when such fail, they may receive YOU into the everlasting dwelling places. 10 The person faithful in what is least is faithful also in much, and the person unrighteous in what is least is unrighteous also in much. 11 Therefore, if YOU have not proved yourselves faithful in connection with the unrighteous riches, who will entrust YOU with what is true? 12 And if YOU have not proved yourselves faithful in connection with what is another’s, who will give YOU what is for yourselves? 13 No house servant can be a slave to two masters; for, either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. YOU cannot be slaves to God and to Riches.”

14 Now the Pharisees, who were money lovers, were listening to all these things, and they began to sneer at him. 15 Consequently he said to them: “YOU are those who declare yourselves righteous before men, but God knows YOUR hearts; because what is lofty among men is a disgusting thing in God’s sight.

16 “The Law and the Prophets were until John. From then on the kingdom of God is being declared as good news, and every sort of person is pressing forward toward it. 17 Indeed, it is easier for heaven and earth to pass away than for one particle of a letter of the Law to go unfulfilled.

18 “Everyone that divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery, and he that marries a woman divorced from a husband commits adultery.

19 “But a certain man was rich, and he used to deck himself with purple and linen, enjoying himself from day to day with magnificence. 20 But a certain beggar named Laz′a·rus used to be put at his gate, full of ulcers 21 and desiring to be filled with the things dropping from the table of the rich man. Yes, too, the dogs would come and lick his ulcers. 22 Now in course of time the beggar died and he was carried off by the angels to the bosom position of Abraham.

“Also, the rich man died and was buried. 23 And in Ha′des he lifted up his eyes, he existing in torments, and he saw Abraham afar off and Laz′a·rus in the bosom position with him. 24 So he called and said, ‘Father Abraham, have mercy on me and send Laz′a·rus to dip the tip of his finger in water and cool my tongue, because I am in anguish in this blazing fire.’ 25 But Abraham said, ‘Child, remember that you received in full your good things in your lifetime, but Laz′a·rus correspondingly the injurious things. Now, however, he is having comfort here but you are in anguish. 26 And besides all these things, a great chasm has been fixed between us and YOU people, so that those wanting to go over from here to YOU people cannot, neither may people cross over from there to us.’ 27 Then he said, ‘In that event I ask you, father, to send him to the house of my father, 28 for I have five brothers, in order that he may give them a thorough witness, that they also should not get into this place of torment.’ 29 But Abraham said, ‘They have Moses and the Prophets; let them listen to these.’ 30 Then he said, ‘No, indeed, father Abraham, but if someone from the dead goes to them they will repent.’ 31 But he said to him, ‘If they do not listen to Moses and the Prophets, neither will they be persuaded if someone rises from the dead.’”

Luke

17 Then he said to his disciples: “It is unavoidable that causes for stumbling should come. Nevertheless, woe to the one through whom they come! 2 It would be of more advantage to him if a millstone were suspended from his neck and he were thrown into the sea than for him to stumble one of these little ones. 3 Pay attention to yourselves. If your brother commits a sin give him a rebuke, and if he repents forgive him. 4 Even if he sins seven times a day against you and he comes back to you seven times, saying, ‘I repent,’ you must forgive him.”

5 Now the apostles said to the Lord: “Give us more faith.” 6 Then the Lord said: “If YOU had faith the size of a mustard grain, YOU would say to this black mulberry tree, ‘Be uprooted and planted in the sea!’ and it would obey YOU.

7 “Who of YOU is there that has a slave plowing or minding the flock who will say to him when he gets in from the field, ‘Come here at once and recline at the table’? 8 Rather, will he not say to him, ‘Get something ready for me to have my evening meal, and put on an apron and minister to me until I am through eating and drinking, and afterward you can eat and drink’? 9 He will not feel gratitude to the slave because he did the things assigned, will he? 10 So YOU, also, when YOU have done all the things assigned to YOU, say, ‘We are good-for-nothing slaves. What we have done is what we ought to have done.’”

11 And while he was going to Jerusalem he was passing through the midst of Sa·mar′i·a and Gal′i·lee. 12 And as he was entering into a certain village ten leprous men met him, but they stood up afar off. 13 And they raised their voices and said: “Jesus, Instructor, have mercy on us!” 14 And when he got sight of them he said to them: “Go and show yourselves to the priests.” Then as they were going off their cleansing occurred. 15 One of them, when he saw he was healed, turned back, glorifying God with a loud voice. 16 And he fell upon his face at Jesus’ feet, thanking him; furthermore, he was a Sa·mar′i·tan. 17 In reply Jesus said: “The ten were cleansed, were they not? Where, then, are the other nine? 18 Were none found that turned back to give glory to God but this man of another nation?” 19 And he said to him: “Rise and be on your way; your faith has made you well.”

20 But on being asked by the Pharisees when the kingdom of God was coming, he answered them and said: “The kingdom of God is not coming with striking observableness, 21 neither will people be saying, ‘See here!’ or, ‘There!’ For, look! the kingdom of God is in YOUR midst.”

22 Then he said to the disciples: “Days will come when YOU will desire to see one of the days of the Son of man but YOU will not see it. 23 And people will say to YOU, ‘See there!’ or, ‘See here!’ Do not go out or chase after them. 24 For even as the lightning, by its flashing, shines from one part under heaven to another part under heaven, so the Son of man will be. 25 First, however, he must undergo many sufferings and be rejected by this generation. 26 Moreover, just as it occurred in the days of Noah, so it will be also in the days of the Son of man: 27 they were eating, they were drinking, men were marrying, women were being given in marriage, until that day when Noah entered into the ark, and the flood arrived and destroyed them all. 28 Likewise, just as it occurred in the days of Lot: they were eating, they were drinking, they were buying, they were selling, they were planting, they were building. 29 But on the day that Lot came out of Sod′om it rained fire and sulphur from heaven and destroyed them all. 30 The same way it will be on that day when the Son of man is to be revealed.

31 “On that day let the person that is on the housetop but whose movable things are in the house not come down to pick these up, and the person out in the field, let him likewise not return to the things behind. 32 REMEMBER the wife of Lot. 33 Whoever seeks to keep his soul safe for himself will lose it, but whoever loses it will preserve it alive. 34 I tell YOU, In that night two men will be in one bed; the one will be taken along, but the other will be abandoned. 35 There will be two women grinding at the same mill; the one will be taken along, but the other will be abandoned.” 36 —— 37 So in response they said to him: “Where, Lord?” He said to them: “Where the body is, there also the eagles will be gathered together.”

Luke

18 Then he went on to tell them an illustration with regard to the need for them always to pray and not to give up, 2 saying: “In a certain city there was a certain judge that had no fear of God and had no respect for man. 3 But there was a widow in that city and she kept going to him, saying, ‘See that I get justice from my adversary at law.’ 4 Well, for a while he was unwilling, but afterward he said to himself, ‘Although I do not fear God or respect a man, 5 at any rate, because of this widow’s continually making me trouble, I will see that she gets justice, so that she will not keep coming and pummeling me to a finish.’” 6 Then the Lord said: “HEAR what the judge, although unrighteous, said! 7 Certainly, then, shall not God cause justice to be done for his chosen ones who cry out to him day and night, even though he is long-suffering toward them? 8 I tell YOU, He will cause justice to be done to them speedily. Nevertheless, when the Son of man arrives, will he really find the faith on the earth?”

9 But he spoke this illustration also to some who trusted in themselves that they were righteous and who considered the rest as nothing: 10 “Two men went up into the temple to pray, the one a Pharisee and the other a tax collector. 11 The Pharisee stood and began to pray these things to himself, ‘O God, I thank you I am not as the rest of men, extortioners, unrighteous, adulterers, or even as this tax collector. 12 I fast twice a week, I give the tenth of all things I acquire.’ 13 But the tax collector standing at a distance was not willing even to raise his eyes heavenward, but kept beating his breast, saying, ‘O God, be gracious to me a sinner.’ 14 I tell YOU, This man went down to his home proved more righteous than that man; because everyone that exalts himself will be humiliated, but he that humbles himself will be exalted.”

15 Now people began to bring him also their infants for him to touch these; but on seeing it the disciples began to reprimand them. 16 However, Jesus called the infants to him, saying: “Let the young children come to me, and do not try to stop them. For the kingdom of God belongs to suchlike ones. 17 Truly I say to YOU, Whoever does not receive the kingdom of God like a young child will by no means get into it.”

18 And a certain ruler questioned him, saying: “Good Teacher, by doing what shall I inherit everlasting life?” 19 Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good, except one, God. 20 You know the commandments, ‘Do not commit adultery, Do not murder, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Honor your father and mother.’” 21 Then he said: “All these I have kept from youth on.” 22 After hearing that, Jesus said to him: “There is yet one thing lacking about you: Sell all the things you have and distribute to poor people, and you will have treasure in the heavens; and come be my follower.” 23 When he heard this, he became deeply grieved, for he was very rich.

24 Jesus looked at him and said: “How difficult a thing it will be for those having money to make their way into the kingdom of God! 25 It is easier, in fact, for a camel to get through the eye of a sewing needle than for a rich man to get into the kingdom of God.” 26 Those who heard this said: “Who possibly can be saved?” 27 He said: “The things impossible with men are possible with God.” 28 But Peter said: “Look! We have left our own things and followed you.” 29 He said to them: “Truly I say to YOU, There is no one who has left house or wife or brothers or parents or children for the sake of the kingdom of God 30 who will not in any way get many times more in this period of time, and in the coming system of things everlasting life.”

31 Then he took the twelve aside and said to them: “Look! We are going up to Jerusalem, and all the things written by means of the prophets as to the Son of man will be completed. 32 For instance, he will be delivered up to men of the nations and will be made fun of and be treated insolently and spit upon; 33 and after scourging him they will kill him, but on the third day he will rise.” 34 However, they did not get the meaning of any of these things; but this utterance was hidden from them, and they were not knowing the things said.

35 Now as he was getting near to Jer′i·cho a certain blind man was sitting beside the road begging. 36 Because he heard a crowd moving through he began to inquire what this might mean. 37 They reported to him: “Jesus the Naz·a·rene′ is passing by!” 38 At that he cried out, saying: “Jesus, Son of David, have mercy on me!” 39 And those going in advance began to tell him sternly to keep quiet, but that much more he kept shouting: “Son of David, have mercy on me.” 40 Then Jesus stood still and commanded the man to be led to him. After he got near, Jesus asked him: 41 “What do you want me to do for you?” He said: “Lord, let me recover sight.” 42 So Jesus said to him: “Recover your sight; your faith has made you well.” 43 And instantly he recovered sight, and he began to follow him, glorifying God. Also, all the people, at seeing it, gave praise to God.

Luke

22 Now the festival of the unfermented cakes, the so-called Passover, was getting near. 2 Also, the chief priests and the scribes were seeking the effective way for them to get rid of him, for they were in fear of the people. 3 But Satan entered into Judas, the one called Is·car′i·ot, who was numbered among the twelve; 4 and he went off and talked with the chief priests and temple captains about the effective way to betray him to them. 5 Well, they rejoiced and agreed to give him silver money. 6 So he consented, and he began to seek a good opportunity to betray him to them without a crowd around.

7 The day of the unfermented cakes now arrived, on which the passover victim must be sacrificed; 8 and he dispatched Peter and John, saying: “Go and get the passover ready for us to eat.” 9 They said to him: “Where do you want us to get it ready?” 10 He said to them: “Look! When YOU enter into the city a man carrying an earthenware vessel of water will meet YOU. Follow him into the house into which he enters. 11 And YOU must say to the landlord of the house, ‘The Teacher says to you: “Where is the guest room in which I may eat the passover with my disciples?”’ 12 And that man will show YOU a large upper room furnished. Get it ready there.” 13 So they departed and found it just as he had said to them, and they got the passover ready.

14 At length when the hour came, he reclined at the table, and the apostles with him. 15 And he said to them: “I have greatly desired to eat this passover with YOU before I suffer; 16 for I tell YOU, I will not eat it again until it becomes fulfilled in the kingdom of God.” 17 And, accepting a cup, he gave thanks and said: “Take this and pass it from one to the other among yourselves; 18 for I tell YOU, From now on I will not drink again from the product of the vine until the kingdom of God arrives.”

19 Also, he took a loaf, gave thanks, broke it, and gave it to them, saying: “This means my body which is to be given in YOUR behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.” 20 Also, the cup in the same way after they had the evening meal, he saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood, which is to be poured out in YOUR behalf.

21 “But, look! the hand of my betrayer is with me at the table. 22 Because the Son of man is going his way according to what is marked out; all the same, woe to that man through whom he is betrayed!” 23 So they started to discuss among themselves the question of which of them would really be the one that was about to do this.

24 However, there also arose a heated dispute among them over which one of them seemed to be greatest. 25 But he said to them: “The kings of the nations lord it over them, and those having authority over them are called Benefactors. 26 YOU, though, are not to be that way. But let him that is the greatest among YOU become as the youngest, and the one acting as chief as the one ministering. 27 For which one is greater, the one reclining at the table or the one ministering? Is it not the one reclining at the table? But I am in YOUR midst as the one ministering.

28 “However, YOU are the ones that have stuck with me in my trials; 29 and I make a covenant with YOU, just as my Father has made a covenant with me, for a kingdom, 30 that YOU may eat and drink at my table in my kingdom, and sit on thrones to judge the twelve tribes of Israel.

31 “Simon, Simon, look! Satan has demanded to have YOU men to sift YOU as wheat. 32 But I have made supplication for you that your faith may not give out; and you, when once you have returned, strengthen your brothers.” 33 Then he said to him: “Lord, I am ready to go with you both into prison and into death.” 34 But he said: “I tell you, Peter, A cock will not crow today until you have three times denied knowing me.”

35 He also said to them: “When I sent YOU forth without purse and food pouch and sandals, YOU did not want for anything, did YOU?” They said: “No!” 36 Then he said to them: “But now let the one that has a purse take it up, likewise also a food pouch; and let the one having no sword sell his outer garment and buy one. 37 For I tell YOU that this which is written must be accomplished in me, namely, ‘And he was reckoned with lawless ones.’ For that which concerns me is having an accomplishment.” 38 Then they said: “Lord, look! here are two swords.” He said to them: “It is enough.”

39 On going out he went as customarily to the Mount of Olives; and the disciples also followed him. 40 Having come to the place he said to them: “Carry on prayer, that YOU do not enter into temptation.” 41 And he himself drew away from them about a stone’s throw, and bent his knees and began to pray, 42 saying: “Father, if you wish, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.” 43 Then an angel from heaven appeared to him and strengthened him. 44 But getting into an agony he continued praying more earnestly; and his sweat became as drops of blood falling to the ground. 45 And he rose from prayer, went to the disciples and found them slumbering from grief; 46 and he said to them: “Why are YOU sleeping? Rise and carry on prayer, that YOU do not enter into temptation.”

47 While he was yet speaking, look! a crowd, and the man called Judas, one of the twelve, was going before them; and he approached Jesus to kiss him. 48 But Jesus said to him: “Judas, do you betray the Son of man with a kiss?” 49 When those about him saw what was going to happen, they said: “Lord, shall we strike with the sword?” 50 A certain one of them even did strike the slave of the high priest and took off his right ear. 51 But in reply Jesus said: “LET it go as far as this.” And he touched the ear and healed him. 52 Jesus then said to the chief priests and captains of the temple and older men that had come there for him: “Did YOU come out with swords and clubs as against a robber? 53 While I was with YOU in the temple day after day YOU did not stretch out YOUR hands against me. But this is YOUR hour and the authority of darkness.”

54 Then they arrested him and led him off and brought him into the house of the high priest; but Peter was following at a distance. 55 When they lit a fire in the midst of the courtyard and sat down together, Peter was sitting in among them. 56 But a certain servant girl saw him sitting by the bright fire and looked him over and said: “This man also was with him.” 57 But he denied it, saying: “I do not know him, woman.” 58 And after a short time another person seeing him said: “You also are one of them.” But Peter said: “Man, I am not.” 59 And after about an hour intervened a certain other man began insisting strongly: “For a certainty this man also was with him; for, in fact, he is a Gal·i·le′an!” 60 But Peter said: “Man, I do not know what you are saying.” And instantly, while he was yet speaking, a cock crowed. 61 And the Lord turned and looked upon Peter, and Peter recalled the utterance of the Lord when he said to him: “Before a cock crows today you will disown me three times.” 62 And he went outside and wept bitterly.

63 Now the men that had him in custody began to make fun of him, hitting him; 64 and after covering him over they would ask and say: “Prophesy. Who is it that struck you?” 65 And they went on saying many other things in blasphemy against him.

66 At length when it became day, the assembly of older men of the people, both chief priests and scribes, gathered together, and they haled him into their San′he·drin hall, saying: 67 “If you are the Christ, tell us.” But he said to them: “Even if I told YOU, YOU would not believe it at all. 68 Moreover, if I questioned YOU, YOU would not answer at all. 69 However, from now on the Son of man will be sitting at the powerful right hand of God.” 70 At this they all said: “Are you, therefore, the Son of God?” He said to them: “YOU yourselves are saying that I am.” 71 They said: “Why do we need further witness? For we ourselves have heard it out of his own mouth.”

John

4 When, now, the Lord became aware that the Pharisees had heard that Jesus was making and baptizing more disciples than John— 2 although, indeed, Jesus himself did no baptizing but his disciples did— 3 he left Ju·de′a and departed again for Gal′i·lee. 4 But it was necessary for him to go through Sa·mar′i·a. 5 Accordingly he came to a city of Sa·mar′i·a called Sy′char near the field that Jacob gave to Joseph his son. 6 In fact, Jacob’s fountain was there. Now Jesus, tired out from the journey, was sitting at the fountain just as he was. The hour was about the sixth.

7 A woman of Sa·mar′i·a came to draw water. Jesus said to her: “Give me a drink.” 8 (For his disciples had gone off into the city to buy foodstuffs.) 9 Therefore the Sa·mar′i·tan woman said to him: “How is it that you, despite being a Jew, ask me for a drink, when I am a Sa·mar′i·tan woman?” (For Jews have no dealings with Sa·mar′i·tans.) 10 In answer Jesus said to her: “If you had known the free gift of God and who it is that says to you, ‘Give me a drink,’ you would have asked him, and he would have given you living water.” 11 She said to him: “Sir, you have not even a bucket for drawing water, and the well is deep. From what source, therefore, do you have this living water? 12 You are not greater than our forefather Jacob, who gave us the well and who himself together with his sons and his cattle drank out of it, are you?” 13 In answer Jesus said to her: “Everyone drinking from this water will get thirsty again. 14 Whoever drinks from the water that I will give him will never get thirsty at all, but the water that I will give him will become in him a fountain of water bubbling up to impart everlasting life.” 15 The woman said to him: “Sir, give me this water, so that I may neither thirst nor keep coming over to this place to draw water.”

16 He said to her: “Go, call your husband and come to this place.” 17 In answer the woman said: “I do not have a husband.” Jesus said to her: “You said well, ‘A husband I do not have.’ 18 For you have had five husbands, and the man you now have is not your husband. This you have said truthfully.” 19 The woman said to him: “Sir, I perceive you are a prophet. 20 Our forefathers worshiped in this mountain; but YOU people say that in Jerusalem is the place where persons ought to worship.” 21 Jesus said to her: “Believe me, woman, The hour is coming when neither in this mountain nor in Jerusalem will YOU people worship the Father. 22 YOU worship what YOU do not know; we worship what we know, because salvation originates with the Jews. 23 Nevertheless, the hour is coming, and it is now, when the true worshipers will worship the Father with spirit and truth, for, indeed, the Father is looking for suchlike ones to worship him. 24 God is a Spirit, and those worshiping him must worship with spirit and truth.” 25 The woman said to him: “I know that Mes·si′ah is coming, who is called Christ. Whenever that one arrives, he will declare all things to us openly.” 26 Jesus said to her: “I who am speaking to you am he.”

27 Now at this point his disciples arrived, and they began to wonder because he was speaking with a woman. Of course, no one said: “What are you looking for?” or, “Why do you talk with her?” 28 The woman, therefore, left her water jar and went off into the city and told the men: 29 “Come here, see a man that told me all the things I did. This is not perhaps the Christ, is it?” 30 They went out of the city and began coming to him.

31 Meanwhile the disciples were urging him, saying: “Rabbi, eat.” 32 But he said to them: “I have food to eat of which YOU do not know.” 33 Therefore the disciples began saying to one another: “No one has brought him anything to eat, has he?” 34 Jesus said to them: “My food is for me to do the will of him that sent me and to finish his work. 35 Do YOU not say that there are yet four months before the harvest comes? Look! I say to YOU: Lift up YOUR eyes and view the fields, that they are white for harvesting. Already 36 the reaper is receiving wages and gathering fruit for everlasting life, so that the sower and the reaper may rejoice together. 37 In this respect, indeed, the saying is true, One is the sower and another the reaper. 38 I dispatched YOU to reap what YOU have spent no labor on. Others have labored, and YOU have entered into the benefit of their labor.”

39 Now many of the Sa·mar′i·tans out of that city put faith in him on account of the word of the woman who said in witness: “He told me all the things I did.” 40 Therefore when the Sa·mar′i·tans came to him, they began asking him to stay with them; and he stayed there two days. 41 Consequently many more believed on account of what he said, 42 and they began to say to the woman: “We do not believe any longer on account of your talk; for we have heard for ourselves and we know that this man is for a certainty the savior of the world.”

43 After the two days he left there for Gal′i·lee. 44 Jesus himself, however, bore witness that in his own homeland a prophet has no honor. 45 When, therefore, he arrived in Gal′i·lee, the Gal·i·le′ans received him, because they had seen all the things he did in Jerusalem at the festival, for they also had gone to the festival.

46 Accordingly he came again to Ca′na of Gal′i·lee, where he had turned the water into wine. Now there was a certain attendant of the king whose son was sick in Ca·per′na·um. 47 When this man heard that Jesus had come out of Ju·de′a into Gal′i·lee, he went off to him and began asking him to come down and heal his son, for he was at the point of dying. 48 However, Jesus said to him: “Unless YOU people see signs and wonders, YOU will by no means believe.” 49 The attendant of the king said to him: “Lord, come down before my young child dies.” 50 Jesus said to him: “Go your way; your son lives.” The man believed the word that Jesus spoke to him and went his way. 51 But already while he was on his way down his slaves met him to say that his boy was living. 52 Therefore he began to inquire of them the hour in which he got better in health. Accordingly they said to him: “Yesterday at the seventh hour the fever left him.” 53 Therefore the father knew it was in the very hour that Jesus said to him: “Your son lives.” And he and his whole household believed. 54 Again this was the second sign Jesus performed when he came out of Ju·de′a into Gal′i·lee.

John

6 After these things Jesus departed across the sea of Gal′i·lee, or Ti·be′ri·as. 2 But a great crowd kept following him, because they were beholding the signs he was performing upon those who were ill. 3 So Jesus went up into a mountain, and there he was sitting with his disciples. 4 Now the passover, the festival of the Jews, was near. 5 When, therefore, Jesus raised his eyes and observed that a great crowd was coming to him, he said to Philip: “Where shall we buy loaves for these to eat?” 6 However, he was saying this to test him, for he himself knew what he was about to do. 7 Philip answered him: “Two hundred de·nar′i·i worth of loaves is not enough for them, so that each one may get a little.” 8 One of his disciples, Andrew the brother of Simon Peter, said to him: 9 “Here is a little boy that has five barley loaves and two small fishes. But what are these among so many?”

10 Jesus said: “HAVE the men recline as at meal.” Now there was a lot of grass in the place. Therefore the men reclined, about five thousand in number. 11 So Jesus took the loaves and, after giving thanks, he distributed them to those reclining, likewise also as much of the small fishes as they wanted. 12 But when they had their fill he said to his disciples: “Gather together the fragments that remain over, so that nothing is wasted.” 13 Therefore they gathered them together, and they filled twelve baskets with fragments from the five barley loaves, which were left over by those who had eaten.

14 Hence when the men saw the signs he performed, they began to say: “This is for a certainty the prophet that was to come into the world.” 15 Therefore Jesus, knowing they were about to come and seize him to make him king, withdrew again into the mountain all alone.

16 When evening fell, his disciples went down to the sea, 17 and, boarding a boat, they set out across the sea for Ca·per′na·um. Well, by now it had grown dark and Jesus had not yet come to them. 18 Also, the sea began to be stirred up because a strong wind was blowing. 19 However, when they had rowed about three or four miles, they beheld Jesus walking upon the sea and getting near the boat; and they became fearful. 20 But he said to them: “It is I; have no fear!” 21 Therefore they were willing to take him into the boat, and directly the boat was at the land to which they were trying to go.

22 The next day the crowd that was standing on the other side of the sea saw that there was no boat there except a little one, and that Jesus had not entered into the boat with his disciples but that only his disciples had left; 23 but boats from Ti·be′ri·as arrived near the place where they ate the bread after the Lord had given thanks. 24 Therefore when the crowd saw that neither Jesus was there nor his disciples, they boarded their little boats and came to Ca·per′na·um to look for Jesus.

25 So when they found him across the sea they said to him: “Rabbi, when did you get here?” 26 Jesus answered them and said: “Most truly I say to YOU, YOU are looking for me, not because YOU saw signs, but because YOU ate from the loaves and were satisfied. 27 Work, not for the food that perishes, but for the food that remains for life everlasting, which the Son of man will give YOU; for upon this one the Father, even God, has put his seal of approval.”

28 Therefore they said to him: “What shall we do to work the works of God?” 29 In answer Jesus said to them: “This is the work of God, that YOU exercise faith in him whom that One sent forth.” 30 Therefore they said to him: “What, then, are you performing as a sign, in order for us to see it and believe you? What work are you doing? 31 Our forefathers ate the manna in the wilderness, just as it is written, ‘He gave them bread from heaven to eat.’” 32 Hence Jesus said to them: “Most truly I say to YOU, Moses did not give YOU the bread from heaven, but my Father does give YOU the true bread from heaven. 33 For the bread of God is the one who comes down from heaven and gives life to the world.” 34 Therefore they said to him: “Lord, always give us this bread.”

35 Jesus said to them: “I am the bread of life. He that comes to me will not get hungry at all, and he that exercises faith in me will never get thirsty at all. 36 But I have said to YOU, YOU have even seen me and yet do not believe. 37 Everything the Father gives me will come to me, and the one that comes to me I will by no means drive away; 38 because I have come down from heaven to do, not my will, but the will of him that sent me. 39 This is the will of him that sent me, that I should lose nothing out of all that he has given me but that I should resurrect it at the last day. 40 For this is the will of my Father, that everyone that beholds the Son and exercises faith in him should have everlasting life, and I will resurrect him at the last day.”

41 Therefore the Jews began to murmur at him because he said: “I am the bread that came down from heaven”; 42 and they began saying: “Is this not Jesus the son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know? How is it that now he says, ‘I have come down from heaven’?” 43 In answer Jesus said to them: “Stop murmuring among yourselves. 44 No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him; and I will resurrect him in the last day. 45 It is written in the Prophets, ‘And they will all be taught by Jehovah.’ Everyone that has heard from the Father and has learned comes to me. 46 Not that any man has seen the Father, except he who is from God; this one has seen the Father. 47 Most truly I say to YOU, He that believes has everlasting life.

48 “I am the bread of life. 49 YOUR forefathers ate the manna in the wilderness and yet died. 50 This is the bread that comes down from heaven, so that anyone may eat of it and not die. 51 I am the living bread that came down from heaven; if anyone eats of this bread he will live forever; and, for a fact, the bread that I shall give is my flesh in behalf of the life of the world.”

52 Therefore the Jews began contending with one another, saying: “How can this man give us his flesh to eat?” 53 Accordingly Jesus said to them: “Most truly I say to YOU, Unless YOU eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, YOU have no life in yourselves. 54 He that feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood has everlasting life, and I shall resurrect him at the last day; 55 for my flesh is true food, and my blood is true drink. 56 He that feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood remains in union with me, and I in union with him. 57 Just as the living Father sent me forth and I live because of the Father, he also that feeds on me, even that one will live because of me. 58 This is the bread that came down from heaven. It is not as when YOUR forefathers ate and yet died. He that feeds on this bread will live forever.” 59 These things he said as he was teaching in public assembly at Ca·per′na·um.

60 Therefore many of his disciples, when they heard this, said: “This speech is shocking; who can listen to it?” 61 But Jesus, knowing in himself that his disciples were murmuring about this, said to them: “Does this stumble YOU? 62 What, therefore, if YOU should behold the Son of man ascending to where he was before? 63 It is the spirit that is life-giving; the flesh is of no use at all. The sayings that I have spoken to YOU are spirit and are life. 64 But there are some of YOU that do not believe.” For from the beginning Jesus knew who were the ones not believing and who was the one that would betray him. 65 So he went on to say: “This is why I have said to YOU, No one can come to me unless it is granted him by the Father.”

66 Owing to this many of his disciples went off to the things behind and would no longer walk with him. 67 Therefore Jesus said to the twelve: “YOU do not want to go also, do YOU?” 68 Simon Peter answered him: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life; 69 and we have believed and come to know that you are the Holy One of God.” 70 Jesus answered them: “I chose YOU twelve, did I not? Yet one of YOU is a slanderer.” 71 He was, in fact, speaking of Judas the son of Simon Is·car′i·ot; for this one was going to betray him, although one of the twelve.

John

7 Now after these things Jesus continued walking about in Gal′i·lee, for he did not want to walk about in Ju·de′a, because the Jews were seeking to kill him. 2 However, the festival of the Jews, the festival of tabernacles, was near. 3 Therefore his brothers said to him: “Pass on over from here and go into Ju·de′a, in order that your disciples also may behold the works you do. 4 For nobody does anything in secret while himself seeking to be known publicly. If you do these things, manifest yourself to the world.” 5 His brothers were, in fact, not exercising faith in him. 6 Therefore Jesus said to them: “My due time is not yet present, but YOUR due time is always at hand. 7 The world has no reason to hate YOU, but it hates me, because I bear witness concerning it that its works are wicked. 8 YOU go up to the festival; I am not yet going up to this festival, because my due time has not yet fully come.” 9 So after he told them these things, he remained in Gal′i·lee.

10 But when his brothers had gone up to the festival, then he also went up himself, not openly but as in secret. 11 Therefore the Jews began looking for him at the festival and saying: “Where is that man?” 12 And there was a lot of subdued talk about him among the crowds. Some would say: “He is a good man.” Others would say: “He is not, but he misleads the crowd.” 13 No one, of course, would speak about him publicly because of the fear of the Jews.

14 When by now the festival was half over, Jesus went up into the temple and began teaching. 15 Therefore the Jews fell to wondering, saying: “How does this man have a knowledge of letters, when he has not studied at the schools?” 16 Jesus, in turn, answered them and said: “What I teach is not mine, but belongs to him that sent me. 17 If anyone desires to do His will, he will know concerning the teaching whether it is from God or I speak of my own originality. 18 He that speaks of his own originality is seeking his own glory; but he that seeks the glory of him that sent him, this one is true, and there is no unrighteousness in him. 19 Moses gave YOU the Law, did he not? But not one of YOU obeys the Law. Why are YOU seeking to kill me?” 20 The crowd answered: “You have a demon. Who is seeking to kill you?” 21 In answer Jesus said to them: “One deed I performed, and YOU are all wondering. 22 For this reason Moses has given YOU the circumcision—not that it is from Moses, but that it is from the forefathers—and YOU circumcise a man on a sabbath. 23 If a man receives circumcision on a sabbath in order that the law of Moses may not be broken, are YOU violently angry at me because I made a man completely sound in health on a sabbath? 24 Stop judging from the outward appearance, but judge with righteous judgment.”

25 Therefore some of the inhabitants of Jerusalem began to say: “This is the man they are seeking to kill, is it not? 26 And yet, see! he is speaking in public, and they say nothing to him. The rulers have not come to know for a certainty that this is the Christ, have they? 27 On the contrary, we know where this man is from; yet when the Christ comes, no one is to know where he is from.” 28 Therefore Jesus cried out as he was teaching in the temple and said: “YOU both know me and know where I am from. Also, I have not come of my own initiative, but he that sent me is real, and YOU do not know him. 29 I know him, because I am a representative from him, and that One sent me forth.” 30 Hence they began seeking to get hold of him, but no one laid a hand upon him, because his hour had not yet come. 31 Still, many of the crowd put faith in him; and they commenced saying: “When the Christ arrives, he will not perform more signs than this man has performed, will he?”

32 The Pharisees heard the crowd murmuring these things about him, and the chief priests and the Pharisees dispatched officers to get hold of him. 33 Therefore Jesus said: “I continue a little while longer with YOU before I go to him that sent me. 34 YOU will look for me, but YOU will not find me, and where I am YOU cannot come.” 35 Therefore the Jews said among themselves: “Where does this man intend going, so that we shall not find him? He does not intend to go to the Jews dispersed among the Greeks and teach the Greeks, does he? 36 What does this saying mean that he said, ‘YOU will look for me, but YOU will not find me, and where I am YOU cannot come’?”

37 Now on the last day, the great day of the festival, Jesus was standing up and he cried out, saying: “If anyone is thirsty, let him come to me and drink. 38 He that puts faith in me, just as the Scripture has said, ‘Out from his inmost part streams of living water will flow.’” 39 However, he said this concerning the spirit which those who put faith in him were about to receive; for as yet there was no spirit, because Jesus had not yet been glorified. 40 Therefore some of the crowd that heard these words began saying: “This is for a certainty The Prophet.” 41 Others were saying: “This is the Christ.” But some were saying: “The Christ is not actually coming out of Gal′i·lee, is he? 42 Has not the Scripture said that the Christ is coming from the offspring of David, and from Beth′le·hem the village where David used to be?” 43 Therefore a division over him developed among the crowd. 44 Some of them, though, were wanting to get hold of him, but no one did lay his hands upon him.

45 Therefore the officers went back to the chief priests and Pharisees, and the latter said to them: “Why is it YOU did not bring him in?” 46 The officers replied: “Never has another man spoken like this.” 47 In turn the Pharisees answered: “YOU have not been misled also, have YOU? 48 Not one of the rulers or of the Pharisees has put faith in him, has he? 49 But this crowd that does not know the Law are accursed people.” 50 Nic·o·de′mus, who had come to him previously, and who was one of them, said to them: 51 “Our law does not judge a man unless first it has heard from him and come to know what he is doing, does it?” 52 In answer they said to him: “You are not also out of Gal′i·lee, are you? Search and see that no prophet is to be raised up out of Gal′i·lee.”*

* Manuscripts Codex Sinaiticus, Codex Vaticanus, and the Sinaitic Syriac codex omit verses 53 to chapter 8, verse 11, which read (with some variations in the various Greek texts and versions) as follows:

53 So they went each one to his home.

John

8 But Jesus went to the Mount of Olives. 2 At daybreak, however, he again presented himself at the temple, and all the people began coming to him, and he sat down and began to teach them. 3 Now the scribes and the Pharisees brought a woman caught at adultery, and, after standing her in their midst, 4 they said to him: “Teacher, this woman has been caught in the act of committing adultery. 5 In the Law Moses prescribed for us to stone such sort of women. What, really, do you say?” 6 Of course, they were saying this to put him to the test, in order to have something with which to accuse him. But Jesus bent down and began to write with his finger in the ground. 7 When they persisted in asking him, he straightened up and said to them: “Let the one of YOU that is sinless be the first to throw a stone at her.” 8 And bending over again he kept on writing in the ground. 9 But those who heard this began going out, one by one, starting with the older men, and he was left alone, and the woman that was in their midst. 10 Straightening up, Jesus said to her: “Woman, where are they? Did no one condemn you?” 11 She said: “No one, sir.” Jesus said: “Neither do I condemn you. Go your way; from now on practice sin no more.”

12 Therefore Jesus spoke again to them, saying: “I am the light of the world. He that follows me will by no means walk in darkness, but will possess the light of life.” 13 Hence the Pharisees said to him: “You bear witness about yourself; your witness is not true.” 14 In answer Jesus said to them: “Even if I do bear witness about myself, my witness is true, because I know where I came from and where I am going. But YOU do not know where I came from and where I am going. 15 YOU judge according to the flesh; I do not judge any man at all. 16 And yet if I do judge, my judgment is truthful, because I am not alone, but the Father who sent me is with me. 17 Also, in YOUR own Law it is written, ‘The witness of two men is true.’ 18 I am one that bears witness about myself, and the Father who sent me bears witness about me.” 19 Therefore they went on to say to him: “Where is your Father?” Jesus answered: “YOU know neither me nor my Father. If YOU did know me, YOU would know my Father also.” 20 These sayings he spoke in the treasury as he was teaching in the temple. But no one laid hold of him, because his hour had not yet come.

21 Hence he said to them again: “I am going away, and YOU will look for me, and yet YOU will die in YOUR sin. Where I am going YOU cannot come.” 22 Therefore the Jews began to say: “He will not kill himself, will he? Because he says, ‘Where I am going YOU cannot come.’” 23 So he went on to say to them: “YOU are from the realms below; I am from the realms above. YOU are from this world; I am not from this world. 24 Therefore I said to YOU, YOU will die in YOUR sins. For if YOU do not believe that I am he, YOU will die in YOUR sins.” 25 Therefore they began to say to him: “Who are you?” Jesus said to them: “Why am I even speaking to YOU at all? 26 I have many things to speak concerning YOU and to pass judgment upon. As a matter of fact, he that sent me is true, and the very things I heard from him I am speaking in the world.” 27 They did not grasp that he was talking to them about the Father. 28 Therefore Jesus said: “When once YOU have lifted up the Son of man, then YOU will know that I am he, and that I do nothing of my own initiative; but just as the Father taught me I speak these things. 29 And he that sent me is with me; he did not abandon me to myself, because I always do the things pleasing to him.” 30 As he was speaking these things, many put faith in him.

31 And so Jesus went on to say to the Jews that had believed him: “If YOU remain in my word, YOU are really my disciples, 32 and YOU will know the truth, and the truth will set YOU free.” 33 They replied to him: “We are Abraham’s offspring and never have we been slaves to anybody. How is it you say, ‘YOU will become free’?” 34 Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to YOU, Every doer of sin is a slave of sin. 35 Moreover, the slave does not remain in the household forever; the son remains forever. 36 Therefore if the Son sets YOU free, YOU will be actually free. 37 I know that YOU are Abraham’s offspring; but YOU are seeking to kill me, because my word makes no progress among YOU. 38 What things I have seen with my Father I speak; and YOU, therefore, do the things YOU have heard from YOUR father.” 39 In answer they said to him: “Our father is Abraham.” Jesus said to them: “If YOU are Abraham’s children, do the works of Abraham. 40 But now YOU are seeking to kill me, a man that has told YOU the truth that I heard from God. Abraham did not do this. 41 YOU do the works of YOUR father.” They said to him: “We were not born from fornication; we have one Father, God.”

42 Jesus said to them: “If God were YOUR Father, YOU would love me, for from God I came forth and am here. Neither have I come of my own initiative at all, but that One sent me forth. 43 Why is it YOU do not know what I am speaking? Because YOU cannot listen to my word. 44 YOU are from YOUR father the Devil, and YOU wish to do the desires of YOUR father. That one was a manslayer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie. 45 Because I, on the other hand, tell the truth, YOU do not believe me. 46 Who of YOU convicts me of sin? If I speak truth, why is it YOU do not believe me? 47 He that is from God listens to the sayings of God. This is why YOU do not listen, because YOU are not from God.”

48 In answer the Jews said to him: “Do we not rightly say, You are a Sa·mar′i·tan and have a demon?” 49 Jesus answered: “I do not have a demon, but I honor my Father, and YOU dishonor me. 50 But I am not seeking glory for myself; there is One that is seeking and judging. 51 Most truly I say to YOU, If anyone observes my word, he will never see death at all.” 52 The Jews said to him: “Now we do know you have a demon. Abraham died, also the prophets; but you say, ‘If anyone observes my word, he will never taste death at all.’ 53 You are not greater than our father Abraham, who died, are you? Also, the prophets died. Who do you claim to be?” 54 Jesus answered: “If I glorify myself, my glory is nothing. It is my Father that glorifies me, he who YOU say is YOUR God; 55 and yet YOU have not known him. But I know him. And if I said I do not know him I should be like YOU, a liar. But I do know him and am observing his word. 56 Abraham YOUR father rejoiced greatly in the prospect of seeing my day, and he saw it and rejoiced.” 57 Therefore the Jews said to him: “You are not yet fifty years old, and still you have seen Abraham?” 58 Jesus said to them: “Most truly I say to YOU, Before Abraham came into existence, I have been.” 59 Therefore they picked up stones to hurl them at him; but Jesus hid and went out of the temple.

John

9 Now as he was passing along he saw a man blind from birth. 2 And his disciples asked him: “Rabbi, who sinned, this man or his parents, so that he was born blind?” 3 Jesus answered: “Neither this man sinned nor his parents, but it was in order that the works of God might be made manifest in his case. 4 We must work the works of him that sent me while it is day; the night is coming when no man can work. 5 As long as I am in the world, I am the world’s light.” 6 After he said these things, he spit on the ground and made a clay with the saliva, and put his clay upon the man’s eyes 7 and said to him: “Go wash in the pool of Si·lo′am” (which is translated ‘Sent forth’). And so he went off and washed, and came back seeing.

8 Therefore the neighbors and those who formerly used to see he was a beggar began to say: “This is the man that used to sit and beg, is it not?” 9 Some would say: “This is he.” Others would say: “Not at all, but he is like him.” The man would say: “I am he.” 10 Consequently they began to say to him: “How, then, were your eyes opened?” 11 He answered: “The man called Jesus made a clay and smeared it on my eyes and said to me, ‘Go to Si·lo′am and wash.’ I therefore went and washed and gained sight.” 12 At this they said to him: “Where is that man?” He said: “I do not know.”

13 They led the once-blind man himself to the Pharisees. 14 Incidentally it was Sabbath on the day that Jesus made the clay and opened his eyes. 15 This time, therefore, the Pharisees also took up asking him how he gained sight. He said to them: “He put a clay upon my eyes, and I washed and have sight.” 16 Therefore some of the Pharisees began to say: “This is not a man from God, because he does not observe the Sabbath.” Others began to say: “How can a man that is a sinner perform signs of that sort?” So there was a division among them. 17 Hence they said to the blind man again: “What do you say about him, seeing that he opened your eyes?” The man said: “He is a prophet.”

18 However, the Jews did not believe concerning him that he had been blind and had gained sight, until they called the parents of the man that gained sight. 19 And they asked them: “Is this YOUR son who YOU say was born blind? How, then, is it he sees at present?” 20 Then in answer his parents said: “We know that this is our son and that he was born blind. 21 But how it is he now sees we do not know, or who opened his eyes we do not know. ASK him. He is of age. He must speak for himself.” 22 His parents said these things because they were in fear of the Jews, for the Jews had already come to an agreement that, if anyone confessed him as Christ, he should get expelled from the synagogue. 23 This is why his parents said: “He is of age. QUESTION him.”

24 Therefore a second time they called the man that had been blind and said to him: “Give glory to God; we know that this man is a sinner.” 25 In turn he answered: “Whether he is a sinner I do not know. One thing I do know, that, whereas I was blind, I see at present.” 26 Therefore they said to him: “What did he do to you? How did he open your eyes?” 27 He answered them: “I told YOU already, and yet YOU did not listen. Why do YOU want to hear it again? YOU do not want to become his disciples also, do YOU?” 28 At this they reviled him and said: “You are a disciple of that man, but we are disciples of Moses. 29 We know that God has spoken to Moses; but as for this man, we do not know where he is from.” 30 In answer the man said to them: “This certainly is a marvel, that YOU do not know where he is from, and yet he opened my eyes. 31 We know that God does not listen to sinners, but if anyone is God-fearing and does his will, he listens to this one. 32 From of old it has never been heard that anyone opened the eyes of one born blind. 33 If this man were not from God, he could do nothing at all.” 34 In answer they said to him: “You were altogether born in sins, and yet are you teaching us?” And they threw him out!

35 Jesus heard that they had thrown him out, and, on finding him, he said: “Are you putting faith in the Son of man?” 36 The man answered: “And who is he, sir, that I may put faith in him?” 37 Jesus said to him: “You have seen him and, besides, he that is speaking with you is that one.” 38 Then he said: “I do put faith in him, Lord.” And he did obeisance to him. 39 And Jesus said: “For this judgment I came into this world: that those not seeing might see and those seeing might become blind.” 40 Those of the Pharisees who were with him heard these things, and they said to him: “We are not blind also, are we?” 41 Jesus said to them: “If YOU were blind, YOU would have no sin. But now YOU say, ‘We see.’ YOUR sin remains.”

John

11 Now there was a certain man sick, Laz′a·rus of Beth′a·ny, of the village of Mary and of Martha her sister. 2 It was, in fact, the Mary that greased the Lord with perfumed oil and wiped his feet dry with her hair, whose brother Laz′a·rus was sick. 3 Therefore his sisters dispatched word to him, saying: “Lord, see! the one for whom you have affection is sick.” 4 But when Jesus heard it he said: “This sickness is not with death as its object, but is for the glory of God, in order that the Son of God may be glorified through it.”

5 Now Jesus loved Martha and her sister and Laz′a·rus. 6 However, when he heard that he was sick, then he actually remained two days in the place where he was. 7 Then after this he said to the disciples: “Let us go into Ju·de′a again.” 8 The disciples said to him: “Rabbi, just lately the Ju·de′ans were seeking to stone you, and are you going there again?” 9 Jesus answered: “There are twelve hours of daylight, are there not? If anyone walks in daylight he does not bump against anything, because he sees the light of this world. 10 But if anyone walks in the night, he bumps against something, because the light is not in him.”

11 He said these things, and after this he said to them: “Laz′a·rus our friend has gone to rest, but I am journeying there to awaken him from sleep.” 12 Therefore the disciples said to him: “Lord, if he has gone to rest, he will get well.” 13 Jesus had spoken, however, about his death. But they imagined he was speaking about taking rest in sleep. 14 At that time, therefore, Jesus said to them outspokenly: “Laz′a·rus has died, 15 and I rejoice on YOUR account that I was not there, in order for YOU to believe. But let us go to him.” 16 Therefore Thomas, who was called The Twin, said to his fellow disciples: “Let us also go, that we may die with him.”

17 Consequently when Jesus arrived, he found he had already been four days in the memorial tomb. 18 Now Beth′a·ny was near Jerusalem at a distance of about two miles. 19 Accordingly many of the Jews had come to Martha and Mary in order to console them concerning their brother. 20 Therefore Martha, when she heard that Jesus was coming, met him; but Mary kept sitting at home. 21 Martha therefore said to Jesus: “Lord, if you had been here my brother would not have died. 22 And yet at present I know that as many things as you ask God for, God will give you.” 23 Jesus said to her: “Your brother will rise.” 24 Martha said to him: “I know he will rise in the resurrection on the last day.” 25 Jesus said to her: “I am the resurrection and the life. He that exercises faith in me, even though he dies, will come to life; 26 and everyone that is living and exercises faith in me will never die at all. Do you believe this?” 27 She said to him: “Yes, Lord; I have believed that you are the Christ the Son of God, the One coming into the world.” 28 And when she had said this, she went off and called Mary her sister, saying secretly: “The Teacher is present and is calling you.” 29 The latter, when she heard this, got up quickly and was on her way to him.

30 Jesus had not yet, in fact, come into the village, but he was still in the place where Martha met him. 31 Therefore the Jews that were with her in the house and that were consoling her, on seeing Mary rise quickly and go out, followed her, supposing that she was going to the memorial tomb to weep there. 32 And so Mary, when she arrived where Jesus was and caught sight of him, fell at his feet, saying to him: “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.” 33 Jesus, therefore, when he saw her weeping and the Jews that came with her weeping, groaned in the spirit and became troubled; 34 and he said: “Where have YOU laid him?” They said to him: “Lord, come and see.” 35 Jesus gave way to tears. 36 Therefore the Jews began to say: “See, what affection he used to have for him!” 37 But some of them said: “Was not this man that opened the eyes of the blind man able to prevent this one from dying?”

38 Hence Jesus, after groaning again within himself, came to the memorial tomb. It was, in fact, a cave, and a stone was lying against it. 39 Jesus said: “TAKE the stone away.” Martha, the sister of the deceased, said to him: “Lord, by now he must smell, for it is four days.” 40 Jesus said to her: “Did I not tell you that if you would believe you would see the glory of God?” 41 Therefore they took the stone away. Now Jesus raised his eyes heavenward and said: “Father, I thank you that you have heard me. 42 True, I knew that you always hear me; but on account of the crowd standing around I spoke, in order that they might believe that you sent me forth.” 43 And when he had said these things, he cried out with a loud voice: “Laz′a·rus, come on out!” 44 The man that had been dead came out with his feet and hands bound with wrappings, and his countenance was bound about with a cloth. Jesus said to them: “Loose him and let him go.”

45 Therefore many of the Jews that had come to Mary and that beheld what he did put faith in him; 46 but some of them went off to the Pharisees and told them the things Jesus did. 47 Consequently the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered the San′he·drin together and began to say: “What are we to do, because this man performs many signs? 48 If we let him alone this way, they will all put faith in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation.” 49 But a certain one of them, Ca′ia·phas, who was high priest that year, said to them: “YOU do not know anything at all, 50 and YOU do not reason out that it is to YOUR benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people and not for the whole nation to be destroyed.” 51 This, though, he did not say of his own originality; but because he was high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus was destined to die for the nation, 52 and not for the nation only, but in order that the children of God who are scattered about he might also gather together in one. 53 Therefore from that day on they took counsel to kill him.

54 Hence Jesus no longer walked about publicly among the Jews, but he departed from there to the country near the wilderness, into a city called E′phra·im, and there he remained with the disciples. 55 Now the passover of the Jews was near, and many people went up out of the country to Jerusalem before the passover in order to cleanse themselves ceremonially. 56 Therefore they went looking for Jesus and they would say to one another as they stood around in the temple: “What is YOUR opinion? That he will not come to the festival at all?” 57 As it was, the chief priests and the Pharisees had given orders that if anyone got to know where he was, he should disclose it, in order that they might seize him.

John

16 “I have spoken these things to YOU that YOU may not be stumbled. 2 Men will expel YOU from the synagogue. In fact, the hour is coming when everyone that kills YOU will imagine he has rendered a sacred service to God. 3 But they will do these things because they have not come to know either the Father or me. 4 Nevertheless, I have spoken these things to YOU that, when the hour for them arrives, YOU may remember I told them to YOU.

“These things, however, I did not tell YOU at first, because I was with YOU. 5 But now I am going to him that sent me, and yet not one of YOU asks me, ‘Where are you going?’ 6 But because I have spoken these things to YOU grief has filled YOUR hearts. 7 Nevertheless, I am telling YOU the truth, It is for YOUR benefit I am going away. For if I do not go away, the helper will by no means come to YOU; but if I do go my way, I will send him to YOU. 8 And when that one arrives he will give the world convincing evidence concerning sin and concerning righteousness and concerning judgment: 9 in the first place, concerning sin, because they are not exercising faith in me; 10 then concerning righteousness, because I am going to the Father and YOU will behold me no longer; 11 then concerning judgment, because the ruler of this world has been judged.

12 “I have many things yet to say to YOU, but YOU are not able to bear them at present. 13 However, when that one arrives, the spirit of the truth, he will guide YOU into all the truth, for he will not speak of his own impulse, but what things he hears he will speak, and he will declare to YOU the things coming. 14 That one will glorify me, because he will receive from what is mine and will declare it to YOU. 15 All the things that the Father has are mine. That is why I said he receives from what is mine and declares it to YOU. 16 In a little while YOU will behold me no longer, and, again, in a little while YOU will see me.”

17 Therefore some of his disciples said to one another: “What does this mean that he says to us, ‘In a little while YOU will not behold me, and, again, in a little while YOU will see me,’ and, ‘because I am going to the Father’?” 18 Hence they were saying: “What does this mean that he says, ‘a little while’? We do not know what he is talking about.” 19 Jesus knew they were wanting to question him, so he said to them: “Are YOU inquiring among yourselves over this, because I said, In a little while YOU will not behold me, and, again, in a little while YOU will see me? 20 Most truly I say to YOU, YOU will weep and wail, but the world will rejoice; YOU will be grieved, but YOUR grief will be turned into joy. 21 A woman, when she is giving birth, has grief, because her hour has arrived; but when she has brought forth the young child, she remembers the tribulation no more because of the joy that a man has been born into the world. 22 YOU also, therefore, are now, indeed, having grief; but I shall see YOU again and YOUR hearts will rejoice, and YOUR joy no one will take from YOU. 23 And in that day YOU will ask me no question at all. Most truly I say to YOU, If YOU ask the Father for anything he will give it to YOU in my name. 24 Until this present time YOU have not asked a single thing in my name. Ask and YOU will receive, that YOUR joy may be made full.

25 “I have spoken these things to YOU in comparisons. The hour is coming when I will speak to YOU no more in comparisons, but I will report to YOU with plainness concerning the Father. 26 In that day YOU will ask in my name, and I do not say to YOU that I shall make request of the Father concerning YOU. 27 For the Father himself has affection for YOU, because YOU have had affection for me and have believed that I came out as the Father’s representative. 28 I came out from the Father and have come into the world. Further, I am leaving the world and am going my way to the Father.”

29 His disciples said: “See! Now you are speaking with plainness, and are uttering no comparison. 30 Now we know that you know all things and you do not need to have anyone question you. By this we believe that you came out from God.” 31 Jesus answered them: “Do YOU believe at present? 32 Look! The hour is coming, indeed, it has come, when YOU will be scattered each one to his own house and YOU will leave me alone; and yet I am not alone, because the Father is with me. 33 I have said these things to YOU that by means of me YOU may have peace. In the world YOU are having tribulation, but take courage! I have conquered the world.”

John

18 Having said these things, Jesus went out with his disciples across the winter torrent of Kid′ron to where there was a garden, and he and his disciples entered into it. 2 Now Judas, his betrayer, also knew the place, because Jesus had many times met there with his disciples. 3 Therefore Judas took the soldier band and officers of the chief priests and of the Pharisees and came there with torches and lamps and weapons. 4 Jesus, therefore, knowing all the things coming upon him, went forth and said to them: “Whom are YOU looking for?” 5 They answered him: “Jesus the Naz·a·rene′.” He said to them: “I am he.” Now Judas, his betrayer, was also standing with them.

6 However, when he said to them: “I am he,” they drew back and fell to the ground. 7 Therefore he asked them again: “Whom are YOU looking for?” They said: “Jesus the Naz·a·rene′.” 8 Jesus answered: “I told YOU I am he. If, therefore, it is I YOU are looking for, let these go”; 9 in order that the word might be fulfilled which he said: “Of those whom you have given me I have not lost a single one.”

10 Then Simon Peter, as he had a sword, drew it and struck the slave of the high priest and cut his right ear off. The name of the slave was Malchus. 11 Jesus, however, said to Peter: “Put the sword into its sheath. The cup that the Father has given me, should I not by all means drink it?”

12 Then the soldier band and the military commander and the officers of the Jews seized Jesus and bound him, 13 and they led him first to An′nas; for he was father-in-law to Ca′ia·phas, who was high priest that year. 14 Ca′ia·phas was, in fact, the one that counseled the Jews that it was to their benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people.

15 Now Simon Peter as well as another disciple was following Jesus. That disciple was known to the high priest, and he went in with Jesus into the courtyard of the high priest, 16 but Peter was standing outside at the door. Therefore the other disciple, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to the doorkeeper and brought Peter in. 17 The servant girl, the doorkeeper, then said to Peter: “You are not also one of this man’s disciples, are you?” He said: “I am not.” 18 Now the slaves and the officers were standing about, as they had built a charcoal fire, because it was cold, and they were warming themselves. Peter also was standing with them and warming himself.

19 And so the chief priest questioned Jesus about his disciples and about his teaching. 20 Jesus answered him: “I have spoken to the world publicly. I always taught in a synagogue and in the temple, where all the Jews come together; and I spoke nothing in secret. 21 Why do you question me? Question those who have heard what I spoke to them. See! These know what I said.” 22 After he said these things, one of the officers that was standing by gave Jesus a slap in the face and said: “Is that the way you answer the chief priest?” 23 Jesus answered him: “If I spoke wrongly, bear witness concerning the wrong; but if rightly, why do you hit me?” 24 Then An′nas sent him away bound to Ca′ia·phas the high priest.

25 Now Simon Peter was standing and warming himself. Then they said to him: “You are not also one of his disciples, are you?” He denied it and said: “I am not.” 26 One of the slaves of the high priest, being a relative of the man whose ear Peter cut off, said: “I saw you in the garden with him, did I not?” 27 However, Peter denied it again; and immediately a cock crowed.

28 Then they led Jesus from Ca′ia·phas to the governor’s palace. It was now early in the day. But they themselves did not enter into the governor’s palace, that they might not get defiled but might eat the passover. 29 Therefore Pilate came outside to them and said: “What accusation do YOU bring against this man?” 30 In answer they said to him: “If this man were not a wrongdoer, we would not have delivered him up to you.” 31 Hence Pilate said to them: “Take him yourselves and judge him according to YOUR law.” The Jews said to him: “It is not lawful for us to kill anyone.” 32 This, in order that the word of Jesus might be fulfilled which he said to signify what sort of death he was destined to die.

33 So Pilate entered into the governor’s palace again and called Jesus and said to him: “Are you the king of the Jews?” 34 Jesus answered: “Is it of your own originality that you say this, or did others tell you about me?” 35 Pilate answered: “I am not a Jew, am I? Your own nation and the chief priests delivered you up to me. What did you do?” 36 Jesus answered: “My kingdom is no part of this world. If my kingdom were part of this world, my attendants would have fought that I should not be delivered up to the Jews. But, as it is, my kingdom is not from this source.” 37 Therefore Pilate said to him: “Well, then, are you a king?” Jesus answered: “You yourself are saying that I am a king. For this I have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth. Everyone that is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.” 38 Pilate said to him: “What is truth?”

And after saying this, he went out again to the Jews and said to them: “I find no fault in him. 39 Moreover, YOU have a custom that I should release a man to YOU at the passover. Do YOU, therefore, wish me to release to YOU the king of the Jews?” 40 Then they shouted again, saying: “Not this man, but Bar·ab′bas!” Now Bar·ab′bas was a robber.

Acts

6 Now in these days, when the disciples were increasing, a murmuring arose on the part of the Greek-speaking Jews against the Hebrew-speaking Jews, because their widows were being overlooked in the daily distribution. 2 So the twelve called the multitude of the disciples to them and said: “It is not pleasing for us to leave the word of God to distribute food to tables. 3 So, brothers, search out for yourselves seven certified men from among YOU, full of spirit and wisdom, that we may appoint them over this necessary business; 4 but we shall devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word.” 5 And the thing spoken was pleasing to the whole multitude, and they selected Stephen, a man full of faith and holy spirit, and Philip and Proch′o·rus and Ni·ca′nor and Ti′mon and Par′me·nas and Nic·o·la′us, a proselyte of Antioch; 6 and they placed them before the apostles, and, after having prayed, these laid their hands upon them.

7 Consequently the word of God went on growing, and the number of the disciples kept multiplying in Jerusalem very much; and a great crowd of priests began to be obedient to the faith.

8 Now Stephen, full of graciousness and power, was performing great portents and signs among the people. 9 But certain men rose up of those from the so-called Synagogue of the Freedmen, and of the Cy·re′ni·ans and Alexandrians and of those from Ci·li′cia and Asia, to dispute with Stephen; 10 and yet they could not hold their own against the wisdom and the spirit with which he was speaking. 11 Then they secretly induced men to say: “We have heard him speaking blasphemous sayings against Moses and God.” 12 And they stirred up the people and the older men and the scribes, and, coming upon him suddenly, they took him by force and led him to the San′he·drin. 13 And they brought forward false witnesses, who said: “This man does not stop speaking things against this holy place and against the Law. 14 For instance, we have heard him say that this Jesus the Naz·a·rene′ will throw down this place and change the customs that Moses handed down to us.”

15 And as all those sitting in the San′he·drin gazed at him, they saw that his face was as an angel’s face.

Acts

9 But Saul, still breathing threat and murder against the disciples of the Lord, went to the high priest 2 and asked him for letters to the synagogues in Damascus, in order that he might bring bound to Jerusalem any whom he found who belonged to The Way, both men and women.

3 Now as he was traveling he approached Damascus, when suddenly a light from heaven flashed around him, 4 and he fell to the ground and heard a voice say to him: “Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?” 5 He said: “Who are you, Lord?” He said: “I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting. 6 Nevertheless, rise and enter into the city, and what you must do will be told you.” 7 Now the men that were journeying with him were standing speechless, hearing, indeed, the sound of a voice, but not beholding any man. 8 But Saul got up from the ground, and though his eyes were opened he was seeing nothing. So they led him by the hand and conducted him into Damascus. 9 And for three days he did not see anything, and he neither ate nor drank.

10 There was in Damascus a certain disciple named An·a·ni′as, and the Lord said to him in a vision: “An·a·ni′as!” He said: “Here I am, Lord.” 11 The Lord said to him: “Rise, go to the street called Straight, and at the house of Judas look for a man named Saul, from Tarsus. For, look! he is praying, 12 and in a vision he has seen a man named An·a·ni′as come in and lay his hands upon him that he might recover sight.” 13 But An·a·ni′as answered: “Lord, I have heard from many about this man, how many injurious things he did to your holy ones in Jerusalem. 14 And here he has authority from the chief priests to put in bonds all those calling upon your name.” 15 But the Lord said to him: “Be on your way, because this man is a chosen vessel to me to bear my name to the nations as well as to kings and the sons of Israel. 16 For I shall show him plainly how many things he must suffer for my name.”

17 So An·a·ni′as went off and entered into the house, and he laid his hands upon him and said: “Saul, brother, the Lord, the Jesus that appeared to you on the road over which you were coming, has sent me forth, in order that you may recover sight and be filled with holy spirit.” 18 And immediately there fell from his eyes what looked like scales, and he recovered sight; and he rose and was baptized, 19 and he took food and gained strength.

He got to be for some days with the disciples in Damascus, 20 and immediately in the synagogues he began to preach Jesus, that this One is the Son of God. 21 But all those hearing him gave way to astonishment and would say: “Is this not the man that ravaged those in Jerusalem who call upon this name, and that had come here for this very purpose, that he might lead them bound to the chief priests?” 22 But Saul kept on acquiring power all the more and was confounding the Jews that dwelt in Damascus as he proved logically that this is the Christ.

23 Now when a good many days were coming to a close, the Jews took counsel together to do away with him. 24 However, their plot against him became known to Saul. But they were closely watching also the gates both day and night in order to do away with him. 25 So his disciples took him and let him down by night through an opening in the wall, lowering him in a basket.

26 On arriving in Jerusalem he made efforts to join himself to the disciples; but they were all afraid of him, because they did not believe he was a disciple. 27 So Bar′na·bas came to his aid and led him to the apostles, and he told them in detail how on the road he had seen the Lord and that he had spoken to him, and how in Damascus he had spoken boldly in the name of Jesus. 28 And he continued with them, walking in and out at Jerusalem, speaking boldly in the name of the Lord; 29 and he was talking and disputing with the Greek-speaking Jews. But these made attempts to do away with him. 30 When the brothers detected this, they brought him down to Caes·a·re′a and sent him off to Tarsus.

31 Then, indeed, the congregation throughout the whole of Ju·de′a and Gal′i·lee and Sa·mar′i·a entered into a period of peace, being built up; and as it walked in the fear of Jehovah and in the comfort of the holy spirit it kept on multiplying.

32 Now as Peter was going through all parts he came down also to the holy ones that dwelt in Lyd′da. 33 There he found a certain man named Ae·ne′as, who had been lying flat on his cot for eight years, as he was paralyzed. 34 And Peter said to him: “Ae·ne′as, Jesus Christ heals you. Rise and make up your bed.” And he rose immediately. 35 And all those who inhabited Lyd′da and the plain of Shar′on saw him, and these turned to the Lord.

36 But in Jop′pa there was a certain disciple named Tab′i·tha, which, when translated, means Dor′cas. She abounded in good deeds and gifts of mercy that she was rendering. 37 But in those days she happened to fall sick and die. So they bathed her and laid her in an upper chamber. 38 Now as Lyd′da was near Jop′pa, when the disciples heard that Peter was in this city they dispatched two men to him to entreat him: “Please do not hesitate to come on as far as us.” 39 At that Peter rose and went with them. And when he arrived, they led him up into the upper chamber; and all the widows presented themselves to him weeping and exhibiting many inner garments and outer garments that Dor′cas used to make while she was with them. 40 But Peter put everybody outside and, bending his knees, he prayed, and, turning to the body, he said: “Tab′i·tha, rise!” She opened her eyes and, as she caught sight of Peter, she sat up. 41 Giving her his hand, he raised her up, and he called the holy ones and the widows and presented her alive. 42 This became known throughout all Jop′pa, and many became believers on the Lord. 43 For quite a few days he remained in Jop′pa with a certain Simon, a tanner.

Acts

11 Now the apostles and the brothers that were in Ju·de′a heard that people of the nations had also received the word of God. 2 So when Peter came up to Jerusalem, the supporters of circumcision began to contend with him, 3 saying he had gone into the house of men that were not circumcised and had eaten with them. 4 At this Peter commenced and went on to explain the particulars to them, saying:

5 “I was in the city of Jop′pa praying, and in a trance I saw a vision, some sort of vessel descending like a great linen sheet being let down by its four extremities from heaven, and it came clear to me. 6 Gazing into it, I made observations and saw four-footed creatures of the earth and wild beasts and creeping things and birds of heaven. 7 I also heard a voice say to me, ‘Rise, Peter, slaughter and eat!’ 8 But I said, ‘Not at all, Lord, because a defiled or unclean thing has never entered into my mouth.’ 9 The second time the voice from heaven answered, ‘You stop calling defiled the things God has cleansed.’ 10 This occurred for a third time, and everything was pulled up again into heaven. 11 Also, look! at that instant there were three men standing at the house in which we were, they having been dispatched from Caes·a·re′a to me. 12 So the spirit told me to go with them, not doubting at all. But these six brothers also went with me, and we entered into the house of the man.

13 “He reported to us how he saw the angel stand in his house and say, ‘Dispatch men to Jop′pa and send for Simon who is surnamed Peter, 14 and he will speak those things to you by which you and all your household may get saved.’ 15 But when I started to speak, the holy spirit fell upon them just as it did also upon us in the beginning. 16 At this I called to mind the saying of the Lord, how he used to say, ‘John, for his part, baptized with water, but YOU will be baptized in holy spirit.’ 17 If, therefore, God gave the same free gift to them as he also did to us who have believed upon the Lord Jesus Christ, who was I that I should be able to hinder God?”

18 Now when they heard these things, they acquiesced, and they glorified God, saying: “Well, then, God has granted repentance for the purpose of life to people of the nations also.”

19 Consequently those who had been scattered by the tribulation that arose over Stephen went through as far as Phoe·ni′cia and Cy′prus and Antioch, but speaking the word to no one except to Jews only. 20 However, out of them there were some men of Cy′prus and Cy·re′ne that came to Antioch and began talking to the Greek-speaking people, declaring the good news of the Lord Jesus. 21 Furthermore, the hand of Jehovah was with them, and a great number that became believers turned to the Lord.

22 The account about them got to the ears of the congregation that was in Jerusalem, and they sent out Bar′na·bas as far as Antioch. 23 When he arrived and saw the undeserved kindness of God, he rejoiced and began to encourage them all to continue in the Lord with hearty purpose; 24 for he was a good man and full of holy spirit and of faith. And a considerable crowd was added to the Lord. 25 So he went off to Tarsus to make a thorough search for Saul 26 and, after he found him, he brought him to Antioch. It thus came about that for a whole year they gathered together with them in the congregation and taught quite a crowd, and it was first in Antioch that the disciples were by divine providence called Christians.

27 Now in these days prophets came down from Jerusalem to Antioch. 28 One of them named Ag′a·bus rose and proceeded to indicate through the spirit that a great famine was about to come upon the entire inhabited earth; which, for that matter, did take place in the time of Claudius. 29 So those of the disciples determined, each of them according as anyone could afford it, to send a relief ministration to the brothers dwelling in Ju·de′a; 30 and this they did, dispatching it to the older men by the hand of Bar′na·bas and Saul.

Acts

15 And certain men came down from Ju·de′a and began to teach the brothers: “Unless YOU get circumcised according to the custom of Moses, YOU cannot be saved.” 2 But when there had occurred no little dissension and disputing by Paul and Bar′na·bas with them, they arranged for Paul and Bar′na·bas and some others of them to go up to the apostles and older men in Jerusalem regarding this dispute.

3 Accordingly, after being conducted partway by the congregation, these men continued on their way through both Phoe·ni′cia and Sa·mar′i·a, relating in detail the conversion of people of the nations, and they were causing great joy to all the brothers. 4 On arriving in Jerusalem they were kindly received by the congregation and the apostles and the older men, and they recounted the many things God had done by means of them. 5 Yet, some of those of the sect of the Pharisees that had believed rose up from their seats and said: “It is necessary to circumcise them and charge them to observe the law of Moses.”

6 And the apostles and the older men gathered together to see about this affair. 7 Now when much disputing had taken place, Peter rose and said to them: “Men, brothers, YOU well know that from early days God made the choice among YOU that through my mouth people of the nations should hear the word of the good news and believe; 8 and God, who knows the heart, bore witness by giving them the holy spirit, just as he did to us also. 9 And he made no distinction at all between us and them, but purified their hearts by faith. 10 Now, therefore, why are YOU making a test of God by imposing upon the neck of the disciples a yoke that neither our forefathers nor we were capable of bearing? 11 On the contrary, we trust to get saved through the undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus in the same way as those people also.”

12 At that the entire multitude became silent, and they began to listen to Bar′na·bas and Paul relate the many signs and portents that God did through them among the nations. 13 After they quit speaking, James answered, saying: “Men, brothers, hear me. 14 Sym′e·on has related thoroughly how God for the first time turned his attention to the nations to take out of them a people for his name. 15 And with this the words of the Prophets agree, just as it is written, 16 ‘After these things I shall return and rebuild the booth of David that is fallen down; and I shall rebuild its ruins and erect it again, 17 in order that those who remain of the men may earnestly seek Jehovah, together with people of all the nations, people who are called by my name, says Jehovah, who is doing these things, 18 known from of old.’ 19 Hence my decision is not to trouble those from the nations who are turning to God, 20 but to write them to abstain from things polluted by idols and from fornication and from what is strangled and from blood. 21 For from ancient times Moses has had in city after city those who preach him, because he is read aloud in the synagogues on every sabbath.”

22 Then the apostles and the older men together with the whole congregation favored sending chosen men from among them to Antioch along with Paul and Bar′na·bas, namely, Judas who was called Bar′sab·bas and Silas, leading men among the brothers; 23 and by their hand they wrote:

“The apostles and the older men, brothers, to those brothers in Antioch and Syria and Ci·li′cia who are from the nations: Greetings! 24 Since we have heard that some from among us have caused YOU trouble with speeches, trying to subvert YOUR souls, although we did not give them any instructions, 25 we have come to a unanimous accord and have favored choosing men to send to YOU together with our loved ones, Bar′na·bas and Paul, 26 men that have delivered up their souls for the name of our Lord Jesus Christ. 27 We are therefore dispatching Judas and Silas, that they also may report the same things by word. 28 For the holy spirit and we ourselves have favored adding no further burden to YOU, except these necessary things, 29 to keep abstaining from things sacrificed to idols and from blood and from things strangled and from fornication. If YOU carefully keep yourselves from these things, YOU will prosper. Good health to YOU!”

30 Accordingly, when these men were let go, they went down to Antioch, and they gathered the multitude together and handed them the letter. 31 After reading it, they rejoiced over the encouragement. 32 And Judas and Silas, since they themselves were also prophets, encouraged the brothers with many a discourse and strengthened them. 33 So, when they had passed some time, they were let go in peace by the brothers to those who had sent them out. 34 —— 35 However, Paul and Bar′na·bas continued spending time in Antioch teaching and declaring, with many others also, the good news of the word of Jehovah.

36 Now after some days Paul said to Bar′na·bas: “Above all things, let us return and visit the brothers in every one of the cities in which we published the word of Jehovah to see how they are.” 37 For his part, Bar′na·bas was determined to take along also John, who was called Mark. 38 But Paul did not think it proper to be taking this one along with them, seeing that he had departed from them from Pam·phyl′i·a and had not gone with them to the work. 39 At this there occurred a sharp burst of anger, so that they separated from each other; and Bar′na·bas took Mark along and sailed away to Cy′prus. 40 Paul selected Silas and went off after he had been entrusted by the brothers to the undeserved kindness of Jehovah. 41 But he went through Syria and Ci·li′cia, strengthening the congregations.

Acts

17 They now journeyed through Am·phip′o·lis and Ap·ol·lo′ni·a and came to Thes·sa·lo·ni′ca, where there was a synagogue of the Jews. 2 So according to Paul’s custom he went inside to them, and for three sabbaths he reasoned with them from the Scriptures, 3 explaining and proving by references that it was necessary for the Christ to suffer and to rise from the dead, and saying: “This is the Christ, this Jesus whom I am publishing to YOU.” 4 As a result some of them became believers and associated themselves with Paul and Silas, and a great multitude of the Greeks who worshiped God and not a few of the principal women did so.

5 But the Jews, getting jealous, took into their company certain wicked men of the marketplace idlers and formed a mob and proceeded to throw the city into an uproar. And they assaulted the house of Ja′son and went seeking to have them brought forth to the rabble. 6 When they did not find them they dragged Ja′son and certain brothers to the city rulers, crying out: “These men that have overturned the inhabited earth are present here also, 7 and Ja′son has received them with hospitality. And all these men act in opposition to the decrees of Caesar, saying there is another king, Jesus.” 8 They indeed agitated the crowd and the city rulers when they heard these things; 9 and first after taking sufficient security from Ja′son and the others they let them go.

10 Immediately by night the brothers sent both Paul and Silas out to Be·roe′a, and these, upon arriving, went into the synagogue of the Jews. 11 Now the latter were more noble-minded than those in Thes·sa·lo·ni′ca, for they received the word with the greatest eagerness of mind, carefully examining the Scriptures daily as to whether these things were so. 12 Therefore many of them became believers, and so did not a few of the reputable Greek women and of the men. 13 But when the Jews from Thes·sa·lo·ni′ca learned that the word of God was published also in Be·roe′a by Paul, they came there also to incite and agitate the masses. 14 Then the brothers immediately sent Paul off to go as far as the sea; but both Silas and Timothy remained behind there. 15 However, those conducting Paul brought him as far as Athens and, after receiving a command for Silas and Timothy to come to him as quickly as possible, they departed.

16 Now while Paul was waiting for them in Athens, his spirit within him came to be irritated at beholding that the city was full of idols. 17 Consequently he began to reason in the synagogue with the Jews and the other people who worshiped God and every day in the marketplace with those who happened to be on hand. 18 But certain ones of both the Ep·i·cu·re′an and the Sto′ic philosophers took to conversing with him controversially, and some would say: “What is it this chatterer would like to tell?” Others: “He seems to be a publisher of foreign deities.” This was because he was declaring the good news of Jesus and the resurrection. 19 So they laid hold of him and led him to the Ar·e·op′a·gus, saying: “Can we get to know what this new teaching is which is spoken by you? 20 For you are introducing some things that are strange to our ears. Therefore we desire to get to know what these things purport to be.” 21 In fact, all Athenians and the foreigners sojourning there would spend their leisure time at nothing but telling something or listening to something new. 22 Paul now stood in the midst of the Ar·e·op′a·gus and said:

“Men of Athens, I behold that in all things YOU seem to be more given to the fear of the deities than others are. 23 For instance, while passing along and carefully observing YOUR objects of veneration I also found an altar on which had been inscribed ‘To an Unknown God.’ Therefore what YOU are unknowingly giving godly devotion to, this I am publishing to YOU. 24 The God that made the world and all the things in it, being, as this One is, Lord of heaven and earth, does not dwell in handmade temples, 25 neither is he attended to by human hands as if he needed anything, because he himself gives to all persons life and breath and all things. 26 And he made out of one man every nation of men, to dwell upon the entire surface of the earth, and he decreed the appointed times and the set limits of the dwelling of men, 27 for them to seek God, if they might grope for him and really find him, although, in fact, he is not far off from each one of us. 28 For by him we have life and move and exist, even as certain ones of the poets among YOU have said, ‘For we are also his progeny.’

29 “Seeing, therefore, that we are the progeny of God, we ought not to imagine that the Divine Being is like gold or silver or stone, like something sculptured by the art and contrivance of man. 30 True, God has overlooked the times of such ignorance, yet now he is telling mankind that they should all everywhere repent. 31 Because he has set a day in which he purposes to judge the inhabited earth in righteousness by a man whom he has appointed, and he has furnished a guarantee to all men in that he has resurrected him from the dead.”

32 Well, when they heard of a resurrection of the dead, some began to mock, while others said: “We will hear you about this even another time.” 33 Thus Paul went out from their midst, 34 but some men joined themselves to him and became believers, among whom also were Di·o·nys′i·us, a judge of the court of the Ar·e·op′a·gus, and a woman named Dam′a·ris, and others besides them.

Acts

19 In the course of events, while A·pol′los was in Corinth, Paul went through the inland parts and came down to Eph′e·sus, and found some disciples; 2 and he said to them: “Did YOU receive holy spirit when YOU became believers?” They said to him: “Why, we have never heard whether there is a holy spirit.” 3 And he said: “In what, then, were YOU baptized?” They said: “In John’s baptism.” 4 Paul said: “John baptized with the baptism in symbol of repentance, telling the people to believe in the one coming after him, that is, in Jesus.” 5 On hearing this, they got baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. 6 And when Paul laid his hands upon them, the holy spirit came upon them, and they began speaking with tongues and prophesying. 7 All together, there were about twelve men.

8 Entering into the synagogue, he spoke with boldness for three months, giving talks and using persuasion concerning the kingdom of God. 9 But when some went on hardening themselves and not believing, speaking injuriously about The Way before the multitude, he withdrew from them and separated the disciples from them, daily giving talks in the school auditorium of Ty·ran′nus. 10 This took place for two years, so that all those inhabiting the district of Asia heard the word of the Lord, both Jews and Greeks.

11 And God kept performing extraordinary works of power through the hands of Paul, 12 so that even cloths and aprons were borne from his body to the ailing people, and the diseases left them, and the wicked spirits came out. 13 But certain ones of the roving Jews who practiced the casting out of demons also undertook to name the name of the Lord Jesus over those having the wicked spirits, saying: “I solemnly charge YOU by Jesus whom Paul preaches.” 14 Now there were seven sons of a certain Sce′va, a Jewish chief priest, doing this. 15 But in answer the wicked spirit said to them: “I know Jesus and I am acquainted with Paul; but who are YOU?” 16 With that the man in whom the wicked spirit was leaped upon them, got the mastery of one after the other, and prevailed against them, so that they fled naked and wounded out of that house. 17 This became known to all, both the Jews and the Greeks that dwelt in Eph′e·sus; and a fear fell upon them all, and the name of the Lord Jesus went on being magnified. 18 And many of those who had become believers would come and confess and report their practices openly. 19 Indeed, quite a number of those who practiced magical arts brought their books together and burned them up before everybody. And they calculated together the prices of them and found them worth fifty thousand pieces of silver. 20 Thus in a mighty way the word of Jehovah kept growing and prevailing.

21 Now when these things had been completed, Paul purposed in his spirit that, after going through Mac·e·do′ni·a and A·cha′ia, he would journey to Jerusalem, saying: “After I get there I must also see Rome.” 22 So he dispatched to Mac·e·do′ni·a two of those who ministered to him, Timothy and E·ras′tus, but he himself delayed for some time in the district of Asia.

23 At that particular time there arose no little disturbance concerning The Way. 24 For a certain man named De·me′tri·us, a silversmith, by making silver shrines of Ar′te·mis furnished the craftsmen no little gain; 25 and he gathered them and those who worked at such things and said: “Men, YOU well know that from this business we have our prosperity. 26 Also, YOU behold and hear how not only in Eph′e·sus but in nearly all the district of Asia this Paul has persuaded a considerable crowd and turned them to another opinion, saying that the ones that are made by hands are not gods. 27 Moreover, the danger exists not only that this occupation of ours will come into disrepute but also that the temple of the great goddess Ar′te·mis will be esteemed as nothing and even her magnificence which the whole district of Asia and the inhabited earth worships is about to be brought down to nothing.” 28 Hearing this and becoming full of anger, the men began crying out, saying: “Great is Ar′te·mis of the E·phe′sians!”

29 So the city became filled with confusion, and with one accord they rushed into the theater, taking forcibly along with them Ga′ius and Ar·is·tar′chus, Mac·e·do′ni·ans, traveling companions of Paul. 30 For his part, Paul was willing to go inside to the people, but the disciples would not permit him. 31 Even some of the commissioners of festivals and games, who were friendly to him, sent to him and began pleading for him not to risk himself in the theater. 32 The fact is, some were crying out one thing and others another; for the assembly was in confusion, and the majority of them did not know the reason why they had come together. 33 So together they brought Alexander out of the crowd, the Jews thrusting him up front; and Alexander motioned with his hand and was wanting to make his defense to the people. 34 But when they recognized that he was a Jew, one cry arose from them all as they shouted for about two hours: “Great is Ar′te·mis of the E·phe′sians!”

35 When, finally, the city recorder had quieted the crowd, he said: “Men of Eph′e·sus, who really is there of mankind that does not know that the city of the E·phe′sians is the temple keeper of the great Ar′te·mis and of the image that fell from heaven? 36 Therefore since these things are indisputable, it is becoming for YOU to keep calm and not act rashly. 37 For YOU have brought these men who are neither robbers of temples nor blasphemers of our goddess. 38 Therefore if De·me′tri·us and the craftsmen with him do have a case against someone, court days are held and there are proconsuls; let them bring charges against one another. 39 If, though, YOU are searching for anything beyond that, it must be decided in a regular assembly. 40 For we are really in danger of being charged with sedition over today’s affair, no single cause existing that will permit us to render a reason for this disorderly mob.” 41 And when he had said these things, he dismissed the assembly.

Acts

20 Now after the uproar had subsided, Paul sent for the disciples, and when he had encouraged them and bidden them farewell, he went forth to journey into Mac·e·do′ni·a. 2 After going through those parts and encouraging the ones there with many a word, he came into Greece. 3 And when he had spent three months there, because a plot was hatched against him by the Jews as he was about to set sail for Syria, he made up his mind to return through Mac·e·do′ni·a. 4 There were accompanying him Sop′a·ter the son of Pyr′rhus of Be·roe′a, Ar·is·tar′chus and Se·cun′dus of the Thes·sa·lo′ni·ans, and Ga′ius of Der′be, and Timothy, and from the district of Asia Tych′i·cus and Troph′i·mus. 5 These went on and were waiting for us in Tro′as; 6 but we put out to sea from Phi·lip′pi after the days of the unfermented cakes, and we came to them in Tro′as within five days; and there we spent seven days.

7 On the first day of the week, when we were gathered together to have a meal, Paul began discoursing to them, as he was going to depart the next day; and he prolonged his speech until midnight. 8 So there were quite a few lamps in the upper chamber where we were gathered together. 9 Seated at the window, a certain young man named Eu′ty·chus fell into a deep sleep while Paul kept talking on, and, collapsing in sleep, he fell down from the third story and was picked up dead. 10 But Paul went downstairs, threw himself upon him and embraced him and said: “STOP raising a clamor, for his soul is in him.” 11 He now went upstairs and began the meal and took food, and after conversing for quite a while, until daybreak, he at length departed. 12 So they took the boy away alive and were comforted beyond measure.

13 We now went ahead to the boat and set sail to As′sos, where we were intending to take Paul aboard, for, after giving instructions to this effect, he himself was intending to go on foot. 14 So when he caught up with us in As′sos, we took him aboard and went to Mit·y·le′ne; 15 and, sailing away from there the succeeding day, we arrived opposite Chi′os, but the next day we touched at Sa′mos, and on the following day we arrived at Mi·le′tus. 16 For Paul had decided to sail past Eph′e·sus, in order that he might not spend any time in the district of Asia; for he was hastening to get to Jerusalem on the day of the festival of Pentecost if he possibly could.

17 However, from Mi·le′tus he sent to Eph′e·sus and called for the older men of the congregation. 18 When they got to him he said to them: “YOU well know how from the first day that I stepped into the district of Asia I was with YOU the whole time, 19 slaving for the Lord with the greatest lowliness of mind and tears and trials that befell me by the plots of the Jews; 20 while I did not hold back from telling YOU any of the things that were profitable nor from teaching YOU publicly and from house to house. 21 But I thoroughly bore witness both to Jews and to Greeks about repentance toward God and faith in our Lord Jesus. 22 And now, look! bound in the spirit, I am journeying to Jerusalem, although not knowing the things that will happen to me in it, 23 except that from city to city the holy spirit repeatedly bears witness to me as it says that bonds and tribulations are waiting for me. 24 Nevertheless, I do not make my soul of any account as dear to me, if only I may finish my course and the ministry that I received of the Lord Jesus, to bear thorough witness to the good news of the undeserved kindness of God.

25 “And now, look! I know that all of YOU among whom I went preaching the kingdom will see my face no more. 26 Hence I call YOU to witness this very day that I am clean from the blood of all men, 27 for I have not held back from telling YOU all the counsel of God. 28 Pay attention to yourselves and to all the flock, among which the holy spirit has appointed YOU overseers, to shepherd the congregation of God, which he purchased with the blood of his own Son. 29 I know that after my going away oppressive wolves will enter in among YOU and will not treat the flock with tenderness, 30 and from among YOU yourselves men will rise and speak twisted things to draw away the disciples after themselves.

31 “Therefore keep awake, and bear in mind that for three years, night and day, I did not quit admonishing each one with tears. 32 And now I commit YOU to God and to the word of his undeserved kindness, which word can build YOU up and give YOU the inheritance among all the sanctified ones. 33 I have coveted no man’s silver or gold or apparel. 34 YOU yourselves know that these hands have attended to the needs of me and of those with me. 35 I have exhibited to YOU in all things that by thus laboring YOU must assist those who are weak, and must bear in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said, ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

36 And when he had said these things, he kneeled down with all of them and prayed. 37 Indeed, quite a bit of weeping broke out among them all, and they fell upon Paul’s neck and tenderly kissed him, 38 because they were especially pained at the word he had spoken that they were going to behold his face no more. So they proceeded to conduct him to the boat.

Acts

21 Now when we had torn ourselves away from them and put out to sea, we ran with a straight course and came to Cos, but on the next day to Rhodes, and from there to Pat′a·ra. 2 And when we had found a boat that was crossing to Phoe·ni′cia, we went aboard and sailed away. 3 After coming in sight of the island of Cy′prus we left it behind on the left side and sailed on to Syria, and landed at Tyre, for there the boat was to unload its cargo. 4 By a search we found the disciples and remained here seven days. But through the spirit they repeatedly told Paul not to set foot in Jerusalem. 5 So when we had completed the days, we went forth and started on our way; but they all, together with the women and children, conducted us as far as outside the city. And kneeling down on the beach we had prayer 6 and said good-bye to one another, and we went up into the boat but they returned to their homes.

7 We then completed the voyage from Tyre and arrived at Ptol·e·ma′is, and we greeted the brothers and stayed one day with them. 8 The next day we set out and arrived in Caes·a·re′a, and we entered into the house of Philip the evangelizer, who was one of the seven men, and we stayed with him. 9 This man had four daughters, virgins, that prophesied. 10 But while we were remaining quite a number of days, a certain prophet named Ag′a·bus came down from Ju·de′a, 11 and he came to us and took up the girdle of Paul, bound his own feet and hands and said: “Thus says the holy spirit, ‘The man to whom this girdle belongs the Jews will bind in this manner in Jerusalem and deliver into the hands of people of the nations.’” 12 Now when we heard this, both we and those of that place began entreating him not to go up to Jerusalem. 13 Then Paul answered: “What are YOU doing by weeping and making me weak at heart? Rest assured, I am ready not only to be bound but also to die at Jerusalem for the name of the Lord Jesus.” 14 When he would not be dissuaded, we acquiesced with the words: “Let the will of Jehovah take place.”

15 Now after these days we prepared for the journey and began going up to Jerusalem. 16 But some of the disciples from Caes·a·re′a also went with us, to bring us to the man at whose home we were to be entertained, a certain Mna′son of Cy′prus, an early disciple. 17 When we got into Jerusalem, the brothers received us gladly. 18 But on the following day Paul went in with us to James; and all the older men were present. 19 And he greeted them and began giving in detail an account of the things God did among the nations through his ministry.

20 After hearing this they began to glorify God, and they said to him: “You behold, brother, how many thousands of believers there are among the Jews; and they are all zealous for the Law. 21 But they have heard it rumored about you that you have been teaching all the Jews among the nations an apostasy from Moses, telling them neither to circumcise their children nor to walk in the solemn customs. 22 What, then, is to be done about it? In any case they are going to hear you have arrived. 23 Therefore do this which we tell you: We have four men with a vow upon themselves. 24 Take these men along and cleanse yourself ceremonially with them and take care of their expenses, that they may have their heads shaved. And so everybody will know that there is nothing to the rumors they were told about you, but that you are walking orderly, you yourself also keeping the Law. 25 As for the believers from among the nations, we have sent out, rendering our decision that they should keep themselves from what is sacrificed to idols as well as from blood and what is strangled and from fornication.”

26 Then Paul took the men along the next day and cleansed himself ceremonially with them and went into the temple, to give notice of the days to be fulfilled for the ceremonial cleansing, until the offering should be presented for each one of them.

27 Now when the seven days were about to be concluded, the Jews from Asia on beholding him in the temple began to throw all the crowd into confusion, and they laid their hands upon him, 28 crying out: “Men of Israel, help! This is the man that teaches everybody everywhere against the people and the Law and this place and, what is more, he even brought Greeks into the temple and has defiled this holy place.” 29 For they had previously seen Troph′i·mus the E·phe′sian in the city with him, but they were imagining Paul had brought him into the temple. 30 And the whole city was set in an uproar, and a running together of the people occurred; and they laid hold of Paul and dragged him outside the temple. And immediately the doors were closed. 31 And while they were seeking to kill him, information came up to the commander of the band that all Jerusalem was in confusion; 32 and he at once took soldiers and army officers and ran down to them. When they caught sight of the military commander and the soldiers, they quit beating Paul.

33 Then the military commander came near and took hold of him and gave command for him to be bound with two chains; and he proceeded to inquire who he might be and what he had done. 34 But some in the crowd began shouting out one thing, and others another. So, being unable himself to learn anything certain because of the tumult, he commanded him to be brought to the soldiers’ quarters. 35 But when he got upon the stairs, the situation became such that he was being carried along by the soldiers because of the violence of the crowd; 36 for the multitude of the people kept following, crying out: “Take him away!”

37 And as he was about to be led into the soldiers’ quarters, Paul said to the military commander: “Am I allowed to say something to you?” He said: “Can you speak Greek? 38 Are you not really the Egyptian who before these days stirred up a sedition and led the four thousand dagger men out into the wilderness?” 39 Then Paul said: “I am, in fact, a Jew, of Tarsus in Ci·li′cia, a citizen of no obscure city. So I beg you, permit me to speak to the people.” 40 After he gave permission, Paul, standing on the stairs, motioned with his hand to the people. When a great silence fell, he addressed them in the Hebrew language, saying:

Acts

23 Looking intently at the San′he·drin Paul said: “Men, brothers, I have behaved before God with a perfectly clear conscience down to this day.” 2 At this the high priest An·a·ni′as ordered those standing by him to strike him on the mouth. 3 Then Paul said to him: “God is going to strike you, you whitewashed wall. Do you at one and the same time sit to judge me in accord with the Law and, transgressing the Law, command me to be struck?” 4 Those standing by said: “Are you reviling the high priest of God?” 5 And Paul said: “Brothers, I did not know he was high priest. For it is written, ‘You must not speak injuriously of a ruler of your people.’”

6 Now when Paul took note that the one part was of Sadducees but the other of Pharisees, he proceeded to cry out in the San′he·drin: “Men, brothers, I am a Pharisee, a son of Pharisees. Over the hope of resurrection of the dead I am being judged.” 7 Because he said this, a dissension arose between the Pharisees and Sadducees, and the multitude was split. 8 For Sadducees say there is neither resurrection nor angel nor spirit, but the Pharisees publicly declare them all. 9 So there broke out a loud screaming, and some of the scribes of the party of the Pharisees rose and began contending fiercely, saying: “We find nothing wrong in this man; but if a spirit or an angel spoke to him,—.” 10 Now when the dissension grew great, the military commander became afraid that Paul would be pulled to pieces by them, and he commanded the force of soldiers to go down and snatch him from their midst and bring him into the soldiers’ quarters.

11 But the following night the Lord stood by him and said: “Be of good courage! For as you have been giving a thorough witness on the things about me in Jerusalem, so you must also bear witness in Rome.”

12 Now when it became day, the Jews formed a conspiracy and bound themselves with a curse, saying they would neither eat nor drink until they had killed Paul. 13 There were more than forty men that formed this oath-bound conspiracy; 14 and they went to the chief priests and the older men and said: “We have solemnly bound ourselves with a curse not to take a bite of food until we have killed Paul. 15 Now, therefore, YOU together with the San′he·drin make it clear to the military commander why he should bring him down to YOU as though YOU intended to determine more accurately the matters involving him. But before he gets near we will be ready to do away with him.”

16 However, the son of Paul’s sister heard of their lying in wait, and he came and entered into the soldiers’ quarters and reported it to Paul. 17 So Paul called one of the army officers to him and said: “Lead this young man off to the military commander, for he has something to report to him.” 18 Therefore this man took him and led him to the military commander and said: “The prisoner Paul called me to him and requested me to lead this young man to you, as he has something to tell you.” 19 The military commander took him by the hand and withdrew and began inquiring privately: “What is it you have to report to me?” 20 He said: “The Jews have agreed to request you to bring Paul down to the San′he·drin tomorrow as though intending to learn something more accurate about him. 21 Above all things, do not let them persuade you, for more than forty men of theirs are lying in wait for him, and they have bound themselves with a curse neither to eat nor to drink until they have done away with him; and they are now ready, waiting for the promise from you.” 22 Therefore the military commander let the young man go after ordering him: “Do not blab to anyone that you have made these things clear to me.”

23 And he summoned a certain two of the army officers and said: “Get two hundred soldiers ready to march clear to Caes·a·re′a, also seventy horsemen and two hundred spearmen, at the third hour of the night. 24 Also, provide beasts of burden that they may have Paul ride and convey him safely to Felix the governor.” 25 And he wrote a letter having this form:

26 “Claudius Lys′i·as to his excellency, Governor Felix: Greetings! 27 This man was seized by the Jews and was about to be done away with by them, but I came suddenly with a force of soldiers and rescued him, because I learned he was a Roman. 28 And wishing to ascertain the cause for which they were accusing him, I brought him down into their San′he·drin. 29 I found him to be accused about questions of their Law, but not charged with a single thing deserving of death or bonds. 30 But because a plot that is to be laid against the man has been disclosed to me, I am at once sending him to you, and commanding the accusers to speak against him before you.”

31 Therefore these soldiers took Paul according to their orders and brought him by night to An·tip′a·tris. 32 The next day they permitted the horsemen to go on with him, and they returned to the soldiers’ quarters. 33 The horsemen entered into Caes·a·re′a and delivered the letter to the governor and also presented Paul to him. 34 So he read it and inquired from what province he was, and ascertained that he was from Ci·li′cia. 35 “I shall give you a thorough hearing,” he said, “when your accusers arrive also.” And he commanded that he be kept under guard in the prae·to′ri·an palace of Herod.

Acts

28 And when we had made it to safety, then we learned that the island was called Malta. 2 And the foreign-speaking people showed us extraordinary human kindness, for they kindled a fire and received all of us helpfully because of the rain that was falling and because of the cold. 3 But when Paul collected a certain bundle of sticks and laid it upon the fire, a viper came out due to the heat and fastened itself on his hand. 4 When the foreign-speaking people caught sight of the venomous creature hanging from his hand, they began saying to one another: “Surely this man is a murderer, and although he made it to safety from the sea, vindictive justice did not permit him to keep on living.” 5 However, he shook the venomous creature off into the fire and suffered no harm. 6 But they were expecting he was going to swell up with inflammation or suddenly drop dead. After they waited for a long while and beheld nothing hurtful happen to him, they changed their mind and began saying he was a god.

7 Now in the neighborhood of that place the principal man of the island, named Pub′li·us, had lands; and he received us hospitably and entertained us benevolently three days. 8 But it happened that the father of Pub′li·us was lying down distressed with fever and dysentery, and Paul went in to him and prayed, laid his hands upon him and healed him. 9 After this occurred, the rest of the people on the island who had sicknesses also began to come to him and be cured. 10 And they also honored us with many gifts and, when we were setting sail, they loaded us with things for our needs.

11 Three months later we set sail in a boat from Alexandria that had wintered in the island and with the figurehead “Sons of Zeus.” 12 And putting into port at Syracuse we remained three days, 13 from which place we went around and arrived at Rhe′gi·um. And a day later a south wind sprang up and we made it into Pu·te′o·li on the second day. 14 Here we found brothers and were entreated to remain with them seven days; and in this way we came toward Rome. 15 And from there the brothers, when they heard the news about us, came to meet us as far as the Marketplace of Ap′pi·us and Three Taverns and, upon catching sight of them, Paul thanked God and took courage. 16 When, finally, we entered into Rome, Paul was permitted to stay by himself with the soldier guarding him.

17 However, three days later he called together those who were the principal men of the Jews. When they had assembled, he proceeded to say to them: “Men, brothers, although I had done nothing contrary to the people or the customs of our forefathers, I was delivered over as a prisoner from Jerusalem into the hands of the Romans. 18 And these, after making an examination, were desirous of releasing me, as there was no cause for death in me. 19 But when the Jews kept speaking against it, I was compelled to appeal to Caesar, but not as though I had anything of which to accuse my nation. 20 Really on this account I entreated to see and speak to YOU, for because of the hope of Israel this chain I have around me.” 21 They said to him: “Neither have we received letters concerning you from Ju·de′a, nor has anyone of the brothers that has arrived reported or spoken anything wicked about you. 22 But we think it proper to hear from you what your thoughts are, for truly as regards this sect it is known to us that everywhere it is spoken against.”

23 They now arranged for a day with him, and they came in greater numbers to him in his lodging place. And he explained the matter to them by bearing thorough witness concerning the kingdom of God and by using persuasion with them concerning Jesus from both the law of Moses and the Prophets, from morning till evening. 24 And some began to believe the things said; others would not believe. 25 So, because they were at disagreement with one another, they began to depart, while Paul made this one comment:

“The holy spirit aptly spoke through Isaiah the prophet to YOUR forefathers, 26 saying, ‘Go to this people and say: “By hearing, YOU will hear but by no means understand; and, looking, YOU will look but by no means see. 27 For the heart of this people has grown unreceptive, and with their ears they have heard without response, and they have shut their eyes; that they should never see with their eyes and hear with their ears and understand with their heart and turn back, and I should heal them.”’ 28 Therefore let it be known to YOU that this, the means by which God saves, has been sent out to the nations; they will certainly listen to it.” 29 ——

30 So he remained for an entire two years in his own hired house, and he would kindly receive all those who came in to him, 31 preaching the kingdom of God to them and teaching the things concerning the Lord Jesus Christ with the greatest freeness of speech, without hindrance.

Romans

6 Consequently, what shall we say? Shall we continue in sin, that undeserved kindness may abound? 2 Never may that happen! Seeing that we died with reference to sin, how shall we keep on living any longer in it? 3 Or do YOU not know that all of us who were baptized into Christ Jesus were baptized into his death? 4 Therefore we were buried with him through our baptism into his death, in order that, just as Christ was raised up from the dead through the glory of the Father, we also should likewise walk in a newness of life. 5 For if we have become united with him in the likeness of his death, we shall certainly also be united with him in the likeness of his resurrection; 6 because we know that our old personality was impaled with him, that our sinful body might be made inactive, that we should no longer go on being slaves to sin. 7 For he who has died has been acquitted from his sin.

8 Moreover, if we have died with Christ, we believe that we shall also live with him. 9 For we know that Christ, now that he has been raised up from the dead, dies no more; death is master over him no more. 10 For the death that he died, he died with reference to sin once for all time; but the life that he lives, he lives with reference to God. 11 Likewise also YOU: reckon yourselves to be dead indeed with reference to sin but living with reference to God by Christ Jesus.

12 Therefore do not let sin continue to rule as king in YOUR mortal bodies that YOU should obey their desires. 13 Neither go on presenting YOUR members to sin as weapons of unrighteousness, but present yourselves to God as those alive from the dead, also YOUR members to God as weapons of righteousness. 14 For sin must not be master over YOU, seeing that YOU are not under law but under undeserved kindness.

15 What follows? Shall we commit a sin because we are not under law but under undeserved kindness? Never may that happen! 16 Do YOU not know that if YOU keep presenting yourselves to anyone as slaves to obey him, YOU are slaves of him because YOU obey him, either of sin with death in view or of obedience with righteousness in view? 17 But thanks to God that YOU were the slaves of sin but YOU became obedient from the heart to that form of teaching to which YOU were handed over. 18 Yes, since YOU were set free from sin, YOU became slaves to righteousness. 19 I am speaking in human terms because of the weakness of YOUR flesh: for even as YOU presented YOUR members as slaves to uncleanness and lawlessness with lawlessness in view, so now present YOUR members as slaves to righteousness with holiness in view. 20 For when YOU were slaves of sin, YOU were free as to righteousness.

21 What, then, was the fruit that YOU used to have at that time? Things of which YOU are now ashamed. For the end of those things is death. 22 However, now, because YOU were set free from sin but became slaves to God, YOU are having YOUR fruit in the way of holiness, and the end everlasting life. 23 For the wages sin pays is death, but the gift God gives is everlasting life by Christ Jesus our Lord.

1 Corinthians

4 Let a man so appraise us as being subordinates of Christ and stewards of sacred secrets of God. 2 Besides, in this case, what is looked for in stewards is for a man to be found faithful. 3 Now to me it is a very trivial matter that I should be examined by YOU or by a human tribunal. Even I do not examine myself. 4 For I am not conscious of anything against myself. Yet by this I am not proved righteous, but he that examines me is Jehovah. 5 Hence do not judge anything before the due time, until the Lord comes, who will both bring the secret things of darkness to light and make the counsels of the hearts manifest, and then each one will have his praise come to him from God.

6 Now, brothers, these things I have transferred so as to apply to myself and A·pol′los for YOUR good, that in our case YOU may learn the rule: “Do not go beyond the things that are written,” in order that YOU may not be puffed up individually in favor of the one against the other. 7 For who makes you to differ from another? Indeed, what do you have that you did not receive? If, now, you did indeed receive it, why do you boast as though you did not receive it?

8 YOU men already have YOUR fill, do YOU? YOU are rich already, are YOU? YOU have begun ruling as kings without us, have YOU? And I wish indeed that YOU had begun ruling as kings, that we also might rule with YOU as kings. 9 For it seems to me that God has put us the apostles last on exhibition as men appointed to death, because we have become a theatrical spectacle to the world, and to angels, and to men. 10 We are fools because of Christ, but YOU are discreet in Christ; we are weak, but YOU are strong; YOU are in good repute, but we are in dishonor. 11 Down to this very hour we continue to hunger and also to thirst and to be scantily clothed and to be knocked about and to be homeless 12 and to toil, working with our own hands. When being reviled, we bless; when being persecuted, we bear up; 13 when being defamed, we entreat; we have become as the refuse of the world, the offscouring of all things, until now.

14 I am writing these things, not to shame YOU, but to admonish YOU as my beloved children. 15 For though YOU may have ten thousand tutors in Christ, YOU certainly do not have many fathers; for in Christ Jesus I have become YOUR father through the good news. 16 I entreat YOU, therefore, become imitators of me. 17 That is why I am sending Timothy to YOU, as he is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord; and he will put YOU in mind of my methods in connection with Christ Jesus, just as I am teaching everywhere in every congregation.

18 Some are puffed up as though I were in fact not coming to YOU. 19 But I will come to YOU shortly, if Jehovah wills, and I shall get to know, not the speech of those who are puffed up, but their power. 20 For the kingdom of God lies not in speech, but in power. 21 What do YOU want? Shall I come to YOU with a rod, or with love and mildness of spirit?

1 Corinthians

11 Become imitators of me, even as I am of Christ.

2 Now I commend YOU because in all things YOU have me in mind and YOU are holding fast the traditions just as I handed them on to YOU. 3 But I want YOU to know that the head of every man is the Christ; in turn the head of a woman is the man; in turn the head of the Christ is God. 4 Every man that prays or prophesies having something on his head shames his head; 5 but every woman that prays or prophesies with her head uncovered shames her head, for it is one and the same as if she were a woman with a shaved head. 6 For if a woman does not cover herself, let her also be shorn; but if it is disgraceful for a woman to be shorn or shaved, let her be covered.

7 For a man ought not to have his head covered, as he is God’s image and glory; but the woman is man’s glory. 8 For man is not out of woman, but woman out of man; 9 and, what is more, man was not created for the sake of the woman, but woman for the sake of the man. 10 That is why the woman ought to have a sign of authority upon her head because of the angels.

11 Besides, in connection with the Lord neither is woman without man nor man without woman. 12 For just as the woman is out of the man, so also the man is through the woman; but all things are out of God. 13 Judge for YOUR own selves: Is it fitting for a woman to pray uncovered to God? 14 Does not nature itself teach YOU that if a man has long hair, it is a dishonor to him; 15 but if a woman has long hair, it is a glory to her? Because her hair is given her instead of a headdress. 16 However, if any man seems to dispute for some other custom, we have no other, neither do the congregations of God.

17 But, while giving these instructions, I do not commend YOU because it is, not for the better, but for the worse that YOU meet together. 18 For first of all, when YOU come together in a congregation, I hear divisions exist among YOU; and in some measure I believe it. 19 For there must also be sects among YOU, that the persons approved may also become manifest among YOU.

20 Therefore, when YOU come together to one place, it is not possible to eat the Lord’s evening meal. 21 For, when YOU eat it, each one takes his own evening meal beforehand, so that one is hungry but another is intoxicated. 22 Certainly YOU do have houses for eating and drinking, do YOU not? Or do YOU despise the congregation of God and make those who have nothing ashamed? What shall I say to YOU? Shall I commend YOU? In this I do not commend YOU.

23 For I received from the Lord that which I also handed on to YOU, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was going to be handed over took a loaf 24 and, after giving thanks, he broke it and said: “This means my body which is in YOUR behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.” 25 He did likewise respecting the cup also, after he had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood. Keep doing this, as often as YOU drink it, in remembrance of me.” 26 For as often as YOU eat this loaf and drink this cup, YOU keep proclaiming the death of the Lord, until he arrives.

27 Consequently whoever eats the loaf or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be guilty respecting the body and the blood of the Lord. 28 First let a man approve himself after scrutiny, and thus let him eat of the loaf and drink of the cup. 29 For he that eats and drinks eats and drinks judgment against himself if he does not discern the body. 30 That is why many among YOU are weak and sickly, and quite a few are sleeping in death. 31 But if we would discern what we ourselves are, we would not be judged. 32 However, when we are judged, we are disciplined by Jehovah, that we may not become condemned with the world. 33 Consequently, my brothers, when YOU come together to eat it, wait for one another. 34 If anyone is hungry, let him eat at home, that YOU may not come together for judgment. But the remaining matters I will set in order when I get there.

The Second to the Corinthians

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will, and Timothy our brother to the congregation of God that is in Corinth, together with all the holy ones who are in all of A·cha′ia:

2 May YOU have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts us in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort those in any sort of tribulation through the comfort with which we ourselves are being comforted by God. 5 For just as the sufferings for the Christ abound in us, so the comfort we get also abounds through the Christ. 6 Now whether we are in tribulation, it is for YOUR comfort and salvation; or whether we are being comforted, it is for YOUR comfort that operates to make YOU endure the same sufferings that we also suffer. 7 And so our hope for YOU is unwavering, knowing as we do that, just as YOU are sharers of the sufferings, in the same way YOU will also share the comfort.

8 For we do not wish YOU to be ignorant, brothers, about the tribulation that happened to us in the district of Asia, that we were under extreme pressure beyond our strength, so that we were very uncertain even of our lives. 9 In fact, we felt within ourselves that we had received the sentence of death. This was that we might have our trust, not in ourselves, but in the God who raises up the dead. 10 From such a great thing as death he did rescue us and will rescue us; and our hope is in him that he will also rescue us further. 11 YOU also can help along by YOUR supplication for us, in order that thanks may be given by many in our behalf for what is kindly given to us due to many prayerful faces.

12 For the thing we boast of is this, to which our conscience bears witness, that with holiness and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom but with God’s undeserved kindness, we have conducted ourselves in the world, but more especially toward YOU. 13 For we are really not writing YOU things except those which YOU well know or also recognize; and which I hope YOU will continue to recognize to the end, 14 just as YOU have also recognized, to an extent, that we are a cause for YOU to boast, just as YOU will also be for us in the day of our Lord Jesus.

15 So, with this confidence, I was intending before to come to YOU, that YOU might have a second occasion for joy, 16 and after a stopover with YOU to go to Mac·e·do′ni·a, and to come back from Mac·e·do′ni·a to YOU and be conducted partway by YOU to Ju·de′a. 17 Well, when I had such an intention, I did not indulge in any lightness, did I? Or what things I purpose, do I purpose them according to the flesh, that with me there should be “Yes, Yes” and “No, No”? 18 But God can be relied upon that our speech addressed to YOU is not Yes and yet No. 19 For the Son of God, Christ Jesus, who was preached among YOU through us, that is, through me and Sil·va′nus and Timothy, did not become Yes and yet No, but Yes has become Yes in his case. 20 For no matter how many the promises of God are, they have become Yes by means of him. Therefore also through him is the “Amen” said to God for glory through us. 21 But he who guarantees that YOU and we belong to Christ and he who has anointed us is God. 22 He has also put his seal upon us and has given us the token of what is to come, that is, the spirit, in our hearts.

23 Now I call upon God as a witness against my own soul that it is to spare YOU that I have not yet come to Corinth. 24 Not that we are the masters over YOUR faith, but we are fellow workers for YOUR joy, for it is by YOUR faith that YOU are standing.

2 Corinthians

6 Working together with him, we also entreat YOU not to accept the undeserved kindness of God and miss its purpose. 2 For he says: “In an acceptable time I heard you, and in a day of salvation I helped you.” Look! Now is the especially acceptable time. Look! Now is the day of salvation.

3 In no way are we giving any cause for stumbling, that our ministry might not be found fault with; 4 but in every way we recommend ourselves as God’s ministers, by the endurance of much, by tribulations, by cases of need, by difficulties, 5 by beatings, by prisons, by disorders, by labors, by sleepless nights, by times without food, 6 by purity, by knowledge, by long-suffering, by kindness, by holy spirit, by love free from hypocrisy, 7 by truthful speech, by God’s power; through the weapons of righteousness on the right hand and on the left, 8 through glory and dishonor, through bad report and good report; as deceivers and yet truthful, 9 as being unknown and yet being recognized, as dying and yet, look! we live, as disciplined and yet not delivered to death, 10 as sorrowing but ever rejoicing, as poor but making many rich, as having nothing and yet possessing all things.

11 Our mouth has been opened to YOU, Corinthians, our heart has widened out. 12 YOU are not cramped for room within us, but YOU are cramped for room in YOUR own tender affections. 13 So, as a recompense in return—I speak as to children—YOU, too, widen out.

14 Do not become unevenly yoked with unbelievers. For what fellowship do righteousness and lawlessness have? Or what sharing does light have with darkness? 15 Further, what harmony is there between Christ and Be′li·al? Or what portion does a faithful person have with an unbeliever? 16 And what agreement does God’s temple have with idols? For we are a temple of a living God; just as God said: “I shall reside among them and walk among them, and I shall be their God, and they will be my people.” 17 “‘Therefore get out from among them, and separate yourselves,’ says Jehovah, ‘and quit touching the unclean thing’”; “‘and I will take YOU in.’” 18 “‘And I shall be a father to YOU, and YOU will be sons and daughters to me,’ says Jehovah the Almighty.”

2 Corinthians

9 Now concerning the ministry that is for the holy ones, it is superfluous for me to write YOU, 2 for I know YOUR readiness of mind of which I am boasting to the Mac·e·do′ni·ans about YOU, that A·cha′ia has stood ready now for a year, and YOUR zeal has stirred up the majority of them. 3 But I am sending the brothers, that our boasting about YOU might not prove empty in this respect, but that YOU may really be ready, just as I used to say YOU would be. 4 Otherwise, in some way, if Mac·e·do′ni·ans should come with me and find YOU not ready, we—not to say YOU—should be put to shame in this assurance of ours. 5 Therefore I thought it necessary to encourage the brothers to come to YOU in advance and to get ready in advance YOUR bountiful gift previously promised, that thus this might be ready as a bountiful gift and not as something extorted.

6 But as to this, he that sows sparingly will also reap sparingly; and he that sows bountifully will also reap bountifully. 7 Let each one do just as he has resolved in his heart, not grudgingly or under compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver.

8 God, moreover, is able to make all his undeserved kindness abound toward YOU, that, while YOU always have full self-sufficiency in everything, YOU may have plenty for every good work. 9 (Just as it is written: “He has distributed widely, he has given to the poor ones, his righteousness continues forever.” 10 Now he that abundantly supplies seed to the sower and bread for eating will supply and multiply the seed for YOU to sow and will increase the products of YOUR righteousness.) 11 In everything YOU are being enriched for every sort of generosity, which produces through us an expression of thanks to God; 12 because the ministry of this public service is not only to supply abundantly the wants of the holy ones but also to be rich with many expressions of thanks to God. 13 Through the proof that this ministry gives, they glorify God because YOU are submissive to the good news about the Christ, as YOU publicly declare YOU are, and because YOU are generous in YOUR contribution to them and to all; 14 and with supplication for YOU they long for YOU because of the surpassing undeserved kindness of God upon YOU.

15 Thanks be to God for his indescribable free gift.

2 Corinthians

13 This is the third time I am coming to YOU. “At the mouth of two witnesses or of three every matter must be established.” 2 I have said previously and, as if present the second time and yet absent now, I say in advance to those who have sinned before and to all the rest, that if ever I come again I will not spare, 3 since YOU are seeking a proof of Christ speaking in me, Christ who is not weak toward YOU but is powerful among YOU. 4 True, indeed, he was impaled owing to weakness, but he is alive owing to God’s power. True, also, we are weak with him, but we shall live together with him owing to God’s power toward YOU.

5 Keep testing whether YOU are in the faith, keep proving what YOU yourselves are. Or do YOU not recognize that Jesus Christ is in union with YOU? Unless YOU are disapproved. 6 I truly hope YOU will come to know we are not disapproved.

7 Now we pray to God that YOU may do nothing wrong, not that we ourselves may appear approved, but that YOU may be doing what is fine, though we ourselves may appear disapproved. 8 For we can do nothing against the truth, but only for the truth. 9 We certainly rejoice whenever we are weak but YOU are powerful; and for this we are praying, YOUR being readjusted. 10 That is why I write these things while absent, that, when I am present, I may not act with severity according to the authority that the Lord gave me, to build up and not to tear down.

11 Finally, brothers, continue to rejoice, to be readjusted, to be comforted, to think in agreement, to live peaceably; and the God of love and of peace will be with YOU. 12 Greet one another with a holy kiss. 13 All the holy ones send YOU their greetings.

14 The undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus Christ and the love of God and the sharing in the holy spirit be with all of YOU.

To the Ephesians

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will, to the holy ones who are in Eph′e·sus and faithful ones in union with Christ Jesus:

2 May YOU have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, for he has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places in union with Christ, 4 just as he chose us in union with him before the founding of the world, that we should be holy and without blemish before him in love. 5 For he foreordained us to the adoption through Jesus Christ as sons to himself, according to the good pleasure of his will, 6 in praise of his glorious undeserved kindness which he kindly conferred upon us by means of his loved one. 7 By means of him we have the release by ransom through the blood of that one, yes, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his undeserved kindness.

8 This he caused to abound toward us in all wisdom and good sense, 9 in that he made known to us the sacred secret of his will. It is according to his good pleasure which he purposed in himself 10 for an administration at the full limit of the appointed times, namely, to gather all things together again in the Christ, the things in the heavens and the things on the earth. Yes, in him, 11 in union with whom we were also assigned as heirs, in that we were foreordained according to the purpose of him who operates all things according to the way his will counsels, 12 that we should serve for the praise of his glory, we who have been first to hope in the Christ. 13 But YOU also hoped in him after YOU heard the word of truth, the good news about YOUR salvation. By means of him also, after YOU believed, YOU were sealed with the promised holy spirit, 14 which is a token in advance of our inheritance, for the purpose of releasing by a ransom God’s own possession, to his glorious praise.

15 That is why I also, since I have heard of the faith YOU have in the Lord Jesus and toward all the holy ones, 16 do not cease giving thanks for YOU. I continue mentioning YOU in my prayers, 17 that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give YOU a spirit of wisdom and of revelation in the accurate knowledge of him; 18 the eyes of YOUR heart having been enlightened, that YOU may know what is the hope to which he called YOU, what the glorious riches are which he holds as an inheritance for the holy ones, 19 and what the surpassing greatness of his power is toward us believers. It is according to the operation of the mightiness of his strength, 20 with which he has operated in the case of the Christ when he raised him up from the dead and seated him at his right hand in the heavenly places, 21 far above every government and authority and power and lordship and every name named, not only in this system of things, but also in that to come. 22 He also subjected all things under his feet, and made him head over all things to the congregation, 23 which is his body, the fullness of him who fills up all things in all.

Ephesians

6 Children, be obedient to YOUR parents in union with the Lord, for this is righteous: 2 “Honor your father and your mother”; which is the first command with a promise: 3 “That it may go well with you and you may endure a long time on the earth.” 4 And YOU, fathers, do not be irritating YOUR children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and mental-regulating of Jehovah.

5 YOU slaves, be obedient to those who are YOUR masters in a fleshly sense, with fear and trembling in the sincerity of YOUR hearts, as to the Christ, 6 not by way of eye-service as men pleasers, but as Christ’s slaves, doing the will of God whole-souled. 7 Be slaves with good inclinations, as to Jehovah, and not to men, 8 for YOU know that each one, whatever good he may do, will receive this back from Jehovah, whether he be slave or freeman. 9 Also, YOU masters, keep doing the same things to them, letting up on the threatening, for YOU know that the Master of both them and YOU is in the heavens, and there is no partiality with him.

10 Finally, go on acquiring power in the Lord and in the mightiness of his strength. 11 Put on the complete suit of armor from God that YOU may be able to stand firm against the machinations of the Devil; 12 because we have a wrestling, not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places. 13 On this account take up the complete suit of armor from God, that YOU may be able to resist in the wicked day and, after YOU have done all things thoroughly, to stand firm.

14 Stand firm, therefore, with YOUR loins girded about with truth, and having on the breastplate of righteousness, 15 and with YOUR feet shod with the equipment of the good news of peace. 16 Above all things, take up the large shield of faith, with which YOU will be able to quench all the wicked one’s burning missiles. 17 Also, accept the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word, 18 while with every form of prayer and supplication YOU carry on prayer on every occasion in spirit. And to that end keep awake with all constancy and with supplication in behalf of all the holy ones, 19 also for me, that ability to speak may be given me with the opening of my mouth, with freeness of speech to make known the sacred secret of the good news, 20 for which I am acting as an ambassador in chains; that I may speak in connection with it with boldness as I ought to speak.

21 Now in order that YOU may also know about my affairs, as to how I am doing, Tych′i·cus, a beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, will make everything known to YOU. 22 I am sending him to YOU for this very purpose, that YOU may know of the things having to do with us and that he may comfort YOUR hearts.

23 May the brothers have peace and love with faith from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. 24 May the undeserved kindness be with all those loving our Lord Jesus Christ in incorruptness.

Philippians

2 If, then, there is any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any sharing of spirit, if any tender affections and compassions, 2 make my joy full in that YOU are of the same mind and have the same love, being joined together in soul, holding the one thought in mind, 3 doing nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with lowliness of mind considering that the others are superior to YOU, 4 keeping an eye, not in personal interest upon just YOUR own matters, but also in personal interest upon those of the others.

5 Keep this mental attitude in YOU that was also in Christ Jesus, 6 who, although he was existing in God’s form, gave no consideration to a seizure, namely, that he should be equal to God. 7 No, but he emptied himself and took a slave’s form and came to be in the likeness of men. 8 More than that, when he found himself in fashion as a man, he humbled himself and became obedient as far as death, yes, death on a torture stake. 9 For this very reason also God exalted him to a superior position and kindly gave him the name that is above every other name, 10 so that in the name of Jesus every knee should bend of those in heaven and those on earth and those under the ground, 11 and every tongue should openly acknowledge that Jesus Christ is Lord to the glory of God the Father.

12 Consequently, my beloved ones, in the way that YOU have always obeyed, not during my presence only, but now much more readily during my absence, keep working out YOUR own salvation with fear and trembling; 13 for God is the one that, for the sake of his good pleasure, is acting within YOU in order for YOU both to will and to act. 14 Keep doing all things free from murmurings and arguments, 15 that YOU may come to be blameless and innocent, children of God without a blemish in among a crooked and twisted generation, among whom YOU are shining as illuminators in the world, 16 keeping a tight grip on the word of life, that I may have cause for exultation in Christ’s day, that I did not run in vain or work hard in vain. 17 Notwithstanding, even if I am being poured out like a drink offering upon the sacrifice and public service to which faith has led YOU, I am glad and I rejoice with all of YOU. 18 Now in the same way YOU yourselves also be glad and rejoice with me.

19 For my part I am hoping in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to YOU shortly, that I may be a cheerful soul when I get to know about the things pertaining to YOU. 20 For I have no one else of a disposition like his who will genuinely care for the things pertaining to YOU. 21 For all the others are seeking their own interests, not those of Christ Jesus. 22 But YOU know the proof he gave of himself, that like a child with a father he slaved with me in furtherance of the good news. 23 This, therefore, is the man I am hoping to send just as soon as I have seen how things stand concerning me. 24 Indeed, I am confident in the Lord that I myself shall also come shortly.

25 However, I consider it necessary to send to YOU E·paph·ro·di′tus, my brother and fellow worker and fellow soldier, but YOUR envoy and private servant for my need, 26 since he is longing to see all of YOU and is depressed because YOU heard he had fallen sick. 27 Yes, indeed, he fell sick nearly to the point of death; but God had mercy on him, in fact, not only on him, but also on me, that I should not get grief upon grief. 28 Therefore with the greater haste I am sending him, that on seeing him YOU may rejoice again and I may be the more free from grief. 29 Therefore give him the customary welcome in the Lord with all joy; and keep holding men of that sort dear, 30 because on account of the Lord’s work he came quite near to death, exposing his soul to danger, that he might fully make up for YOUR not being here to render private service to me.

Philippians

3 Finally, my brothers, continue rejoicing in the Lord. To be writing the same things to YOU is not troublesome for me, but it is of safety to YOU.

2 Look out for the dogs, look out for the workers of injury, look out for those who mutilate the flesh. 3 For we are those with the real circumcision, who are rendering sacred service by God’s spirit and have our boasting in Christ Jesus and do not have our confidence in the flesh, 4 though I, if anyone, do have grounds for confidence also in the flesh.

If any other man thinks he has grounds for confidence in the flesh, I the more so: 5 circumcised the eighth day, out of the family stock of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew born from Hebrews; as respects law, a Pharisee; 6 as respects zeal, persecuting the congregation; as respects righteousness that is by means of law, one who proved himself blameless. 7 Yet what things were gains to me, these I have considered loss on account of the Christ. 8 Why, for that matter, I do indeed also consider all things to be loss on account of the excelling value of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord. On account of him I have taken the loss of all things and I consider them as a lot of refuse, that I may gain Christ 9 and be found in union with him, having, not my own righteousness, which results from law, but that which is through faith in Christ, the righteousness that issues from God on the basis of faith, 10 so as to know him and the power of his resurrection and a sharing in his sufferings, submitting myself to a death like his, 11 to see if I may by any means attain to the earlier resurrection from the dead.

12 Not that I have already received it or am already made perfect, but I am pursuing to see if I may also lay hold on that for which I have also been laid hold on by Christ Jesus. 13 Brothers, I do not yet consider myself as having laid hold on it; but there is one thing about it: Forgetting the things behind and stretching forward to the things ahead, 14 I am pursuing down toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God by means of Christ Jesus. 15 Let us, then, as many of us as are mature, be of this mental attitude; and if YOU are mentally inclined otherwise in any respect, God will reveal the above attitude to YOU. 16 At any rate, to what extent we have made progress, let us go on walking orderly in this same routine.

17 Unitedly become imitators of me, brothers, and keep YOUR eye on those who are walking in a way that accords with the example YOU have in us. 18 For there are many, I used to mention them often but now I mention them also with weeping, who are walking as the enemies of the torture stake of the Christ, 19 and their finish is destruction, and their god is their belly, and their glory consists in their shame, and they have their minds upon things on the earth. 20 As for us, our citizenship exists in the heavens, from which place also we are eagerly waiting for a savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, 21 who will refashion our humiliated body to be conformed to his glorious body according to the operation of the power that he has, even to subject all things to himself.

2 Thessalonians

3 Finally, brothers, carry on prayer for us, that the word of Jehovah may keep moving speedily and being glorified just as it is in fact with YOU; 2 and that we may be delivered from harmful and wicked men, for faith is not a possession of all people. 3 But the Lord is faithful, and he will make YOU firm and keep YOU from the wicked one. 4 Moreover, we have confidence in the Lord regarding YOU, that YOU are doing and will go on doing the things we order. 5 May the Lord continue directing YOUR hearts successfully into the love of God and into the endurance for the Christ.

6 Now we are giving YOU orders, brothers, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, to withdraw from every brother walking disorderly and not according to the tradition YOU received from us. 7 For YOU yourselves know the way YOU ought to imitate us, because we did not behave disorderly among YOU 8 nor did we eat food from anyone free. To the contrary, by labor and toil night and day we were working so as not to impose an expensive burden upon any one of YOU. 9 Not that we do not have authority, but in order that we might offer ourselves as an example to YOU to imitate us. 10 In fact, also, when we were with YOU, we used to give YOU this order: “If anyone does not want to work, neither let him eat.” 11 For we hear certain ones are walking disorderly among YOU, not working at all but meddling with what does not concern them. 12 To such persons we give the order and exhortation in the Lord Jesus Christ that by working with quietness they should eat food they themselves earn.

13 For YOUR part, brothers, do not give up in doing right. 14 But if anyone is not obedient to our word through this letter, keep this one marked, stop associating with him, that he may become ashamed. 15 And yet do not be considering him as an enemy, but continue admonishing him as a brother.

16 Now may the Lord of peace himself give YOU peace constantly in every way. The Lord be with all of YOU.

17 Here is my greeting, Paul’s, in my own hand, which is a sign in every letter; this is the way I write.

18 The undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of YOU.

The First to Timothy

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus under command of God our Savior and of Christ Jesus, our hope, 2 to Timothy, a genuine child in the faith:

May there be undeserved kindness, mercy, peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.

3 Just as I encouraged you to stay in Eph′e·sus when I was about to go my way into Mac·e·do′ni·a, so I do now, that you might command certain ones not to teach different doctrine, 4 nor to pay attention to false stories and to genealogies, which end up in nothing, but which furnish questions for research rather than a dispensing of anything by God in connection with faith. 5 Really the objective of this mandate is love out of a clean heart and out of a good conscience and out of faith without hypocrisy. 6 By deviating from these things certain ones have been turned aside into idle talk, 7 wanting to be teachers of law, but not perceiving either the things they are saying or the things about which they are making strong assertions.

8 Now we know that the Law is fine provided one handles it lawfully 9 in the knowledge of this fact, that law is promulgated, not for a righteous man, but for persons lawless and unruly, ungodly and sinners, lacking loving-kindness, and profane, murderers of fathers and murderers of mothers, manslayers, 10 fornicators, men who lie with males, kidnappers, liars, false swearers, and whatever other thing is in opposition to the healthful teaching 11 according to the glorious good news of the happy God, with which I was entrusted.

12 I am grateful to Christ Jesus our Lord, who imparted power to me, because he considered me faithful by assigning me to a ministry, 13 although formerly I was a blasphemer and a persecutor and an insolent man. Nevertheless, I was shown mercy, because I was ignorant and acted with a lack of faith. 14 But the undeserved kindness of our Lord abounded exceedingly along with faith and love that is in connection with Christ Jesus. 15 Faithful and deserving of full acceptance is the saying that Christ Jesus came into the world to save sinners. Of these I am foremost. 16 Nevertheless, the reason why I was shown mercy was that by means of me as the foremost case Christ Jesus might demonstrate all his long-suffering for a sample of those who are going to rest their faith on him for everlasting life.

17 Now to the King of eternity, incorruptible, invisible, the only God, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.

18 This mandate I commit to you, child, Timothy, in accord with the predictions that led directly on to you, that by these you may go on waging the fine warfare; 19 holding faith and a good conscience, which some have thrust aside and have experienced shipwreck concerning their faith. 20 Hy·me·nae′us and Alexander belong to these, and I have handed them over to Satan that they may be taught by discipline not to blaspheme.

Titus

3 Continue reminding them to be in subjection and be obedient to governments and authorities as rulers, to be ready for every good work, 2 to speak injuriously of no one, not to be belligerent, to be reasonable, exhibiting all mildness toward all men. 3 For even we were once senseless, disobedient, being misled, being slaves to various desires and pleasures, carrying on in badness and envy, abhorrent, hating one another.

4 However, when the kindness and the love for man on the part of our Savior, God, was manifested, 5 owing to no works in righteousness that we had performed, but according to his mercy he saved us through the bath that brought us to life and through the making of us new by holy spirit. 6 This spirit he poured out richly upon us through Jesus Christ our Savior, 7 that, after being declared righteous by virtue of the undeserved kindness of that one, we might become heirs according to a hope of everlasting life.

8 Faithful is the saying, and concerning these things I desire you to make firm assertions constantly, in order that those who have believed God may keep their minds on maintaining fine works. These things are fine and beneficial to men.

9 But shun foolish questionings and genealogies and strife and fights over the Law, for they are unprofitable and futile. 10 As for a man that promotes a sect, reject him after a first and a second admonition; 11 knowing that such a man has been turned out of the way and is sinning, he being self-condemned.

12 When I send Ar′te·mas or Tych′i·cus to you, do your utmost to come to me at Ni·cop′o·lis, for there is where I have decided to winter. 13 Carefully supply Ze′nas, who is versed in the Law, and A·pol′los for their trip, that they may not lack anything. 14 But let our people also learn to maintain fine works so as to meet their pressing needs, that they may not be unfruitful.

15 All those with me send you their greetings. Give my greetings to those who have affection for us in the faith.

May the undeserved kindness be with all of YOU people.

To the Hebrews

1 God, who long ago spoke on many occasions and in many ways to our forefathers by means of the prophets, 2 has at the end of these days spoken to us by means of a Son, whom he appointed heir of all things, and through whom he made the systems of things. 3 He is the reflection of his glory and the exact representation of his very being, and he sustains all things by the word of his power; and after he had made a purification for our sins he sat down on the right hand of the Majesty in lofty places. 4 So he has become better than the angels, to the extent that he has inherited a name more excellent than theirs.

5 For example, to which one of the angels did he ever say: “You are my son; I, today, I have become your father”? And again: “I myself shall become his father, and he himself will become my son”? 6 But when he again brings his Firstborn into the inhabited earth, he says: “And let all God’s angels do obeisance to him.”

7 Also, with reference to the angels he says: “And he makes his angels spirits, and his public servants a flame of fire.” 8 But with reference to the Son: “God is your throne forever and ever, and the scepter of your kingdom is the scepter of uprightness. 9 You loved righteousness, and you hated lawlessness. That is why God, your God, anointed you with the oil of exultation more than your partners.” 10 And: “You at the beginning, O Lord, laid the foundations of the earth itself, and the heavens are the works of your hands. 11 They themselves will perish, but you yourself are to remain continually; and just like an outer garment they will all grow old, 12 and you will wrap them up just as a cloak, as an outer garment; and they will be changed, but you are the same, and your years will never run out.”

13 But with reference to which one of the angels has he ever said: “Sit at my right hand, until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet”? 14 Are they not all spirits for public service, sent forth to minister for those who are going to inherit salvation?

Hebrews

2 That is why it is necessary for us to pay more than the usual attention to the things heard by us, that we may never drift away. 2 For if the word spoken through angels proved to be firm, and every transgression and disobedient act received a retribution in harmony with justice; 3 how shall we escape if we have neglected a salvation of such greatness in that it began to be spoken through our Lord and was verified for us by those who heard him, 4 while God joined in bearing witness with signs as well as portents and various powerful works and with distributions of holy spirit according to his will?

5 For it is not to angels that he has subjected the inhabited earth to come, about which we are speaking. 6 But a certain witness has given proof somewhere, saying: “What is man that you keep him in mind, or the son of man that you take care of him? 7 You made him a little lower than angels; with glory and honor you crowned him, and appointed him over the works of your hands. 8 All things you subjected under his feet.” For in that he subjected all things to him God left nothing that is not subject to him. Now, though, we do not yet see all things in subjection to him; 9 but we behold Jesus, who has been made a little lower than angels, crowned with glory and honor for having suffered death, that he by God’s undeserved kindness might taste death for every man.

10 For it was fitting for the one for whose sake all things are and through whom all things are, in bringing many sons to glory, to make the Chief Agent of their salvation perfect through sufferings. 11 For both he who is sanctifying and those who are being sanctified all stem from one, and for this cause he is not ashamed to call them “brothers,” 12 as he says: “I will declare your name to my brothers; in the middle of the congregation I will praise you with song.” 13 And again: “I will have my trust in him.” And again: “Look! I and the young children, whom Jehovah gave me.”

14 Therefore, since the “young children” are sharers of blood and flesh, he also similarly partook of the same things, that through his death he might bring to nothing the one having the means to cause death, that is, the Devil; 15 and that he might emancipate all those who for fear of death were subject to slavery all through their lives. 16 For he is really not assisting angels at all, but he is assisting Abraham’s seed. 17 Consequently he was obliged to become like his “brothers” in all respects, that he might become a merciful and faithful high priest in things pertaining to God, in order to offer propitiatory sacrifice for the sins of the people. 18 For in that he himself has suffered when being put to the test, he is able to come to the aid of those who are being put to the test.

Hebrews

5 For every high priest taken from among men is appointed in behalf of men over the things pertaining to God, that he may offer gifts and sacrifices for sins. 2 He is able to deal moderately with the ignorant and erring ones since he also is surrounded with his own weakness, 3 and on its account he is obliged to make offerings for sins as much for himself as for the people.

4 Also, a man takes this honor, not of his own accord, but only when he is called by God, just as Aaron also was. 5 So too the Christ did not glorify himself by becoming a high priest, but was glorified by him who spoke with reference to him: “You are my son; I, today, I have become your father.” 6 Just as he says also in another place: “You are a priest forever according to the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.”

7 In the days of his flesh Christ offered up supplications and also petitions to the One who was able to save him out of death, with strong outcries and tears, and he was favorably heard for his godly fear. 8 Although he was a Son, he learned obedience from the things he suffered; 9 and after he had been made perfect he became responsible for everlasting salvation to all those obeying him, 10 because he has been specifically called by God a high priest according to the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.

11 Concerning him we have much to say and hard to be explained, since YOU have become dull in YOUR hearing. 12 For, indeed, although YOU ought to be teachers in view of the time, YOU again need someone to teach YOU from the beginning the elementary things of the sacred pronouncements of God; and YOU have become such as need milk, not solid food. 13 For everyone that partakes of milk is unacquainted with the word of righteousness, for he is a babe. 14 But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their perceptive powers trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Hebrews

10 For since the Law has a shadow of the good things to come, but not the very substance of the things, men can never with the same sacrifices from year to year which they offer continually make those who approach perfect. 2 Otherwise, would the sacrifices not have stopped being offered, because those rendering sacred service who had been cleansed once for all time would have no consciousness of sins anymore? 3 To the contrary, by these sacrifices there is a reminding of sins from year to year, 4 for it is not possible for the blood of bulls and of goats to take sins away.

5 Hence when he comes into the world he says: “‘Sacrifice and offering you did not want, but you prepared a body for me. 6 You did not approve of whole burnt offerings and sin offering.’ 7 Then I said, ‘Look! I am come (in the roll of the book it is written about me) to do your will, O God.’” 8 After first saying: “You did not want nor did you approve of sacrifices and offerings and whole burnt offerings and sin offering”—sacrifices that are offered according to the Law— 9 then he actually says: “Look! I am come to do your will.” He does away with what is first that he may establish what is second. 10 By the said “will” we have been sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all time.

11 Also, every priest takes his station from day to day to render public service and to offer the same sacrifices often, as these are at no time able to take sins away completely. 12 But this man offered one sacrifice for sins perpetually and sat down at the right hand of God, 13 from then on awaiting until his enemies should be placed as a stool for his feet. 14 For it is by one sacrificial offering that he has made those who are being sanctified perfect perpetually. 15 Moreover, the holy spirit also bears witness to us, for after it has said: 16 “‘This is the covenant that I shall covenant toward them after those days,’ says Jehovah. ‘I will put my laws in their hearts, and in their minds I shall write them,’” 17 it says afterwards: “And I shall by no means call their sins and their lawless deeds to mind anymore.” 18 Now where there is forgiveness of these, there is no longer an offering for sin.

19 Therefore, brothers, since we have boldness for the way of entry into the holy place by the blood of Jesus, 20 which he inaugurated for us as a new and living way through the curtain, that is, his flesh, 21 and since we have a great priest over the house of God, 22 let us approach with true hearts in the full assurance of faith, having had our hearts sprinkled from a wicked conscience and our bodies bathed with clean water. 23 Let us hold fast the public declaration of our hope without wavering, for he is faithful that promised. 24 And let us consider one another to incite to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking the gathering of ourselves together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as YOU behold the day drawing near.

26 For if we practice sin willfully after having received the accurate knowledge of the truth, there is no longer any sacrifice for sins left, 27 but there is a certain fearful expectation of judgment and there is a fiery jealousy that is going to consume those in opposition. 28 Any man that has disregarded the law of Moses dies without compassion, upon the testimony of two or three. 29 Of how much more severe a punishment, do YOU think, will the man be counted worthy who has trampled upon the Son of God and who has esteemed as of ordinary value the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified, and who has outraged the spirit of undeserved kindness with contempt? 30 For we know him that said: “Vengeance is mine; I will recompense”; and again: “Jehovah will judge his people.” 31 It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.

32 However, keep on remembering the former days in which, after YOU were enlightened, YOU endured a great contest under sufferings, 33 sometimes while YOU were being exposed as in a theater both to reproaches and tribulations, and sometimes while YOU became sharers with those who were having such an experience. 34 For YOU both expressed sympathy for those in prison and joyfully took the plundering of YOUR belongings, knowing YOU yourselves have a better and an abiding possession.

35 Do not, therefore, throw away YOUR freeness of speech, which has a great reward to be paid it. 36 For YOU have need of endurance, in order that, after YOU have done the will of God, YOU may receive the fulfillment of the promise. 37 For yet “a very little while,” and “he who is coming will arrive and will not delay.” 38 “But my righteous one will live by reason of faith,” and, “if he shrinks back, my soul has no pleasure in him.” 39 Now we are not the sort that shrink back to destruction, but the sort that have faith to the preserving alive of the soul.

James

4 From what source are there wars and from what source are there fights among YOU? Are they not from this source, namely, from YOUR cravings for sensual pleasure that carry on a conflict in YOUR members? 2 YOU desire, and yet YOU do not have. YOU go on murdering and coveting, and yet YOU are not able to obtain. YOU go on fighting and waging war. YOU do not have because of YOUR not asking. 3 YOU do ask, and yet YOU do not receive, because YOU are asking for a wrong purpose, that YOU may expend it upon YOUR cravings for sensual pleasure.

4 Adulteresses, do YOU not know that the friendship with the world is enmity with God? Whoever, therefore, wants to be a friend of the world is constituting himself an enemy of God. 5 Or does it seem to YOU that the scripture says to no purpose: “It is with a tendency to envy that the spirit which has taken up residence within us keeps longing”? 6 However, the undeserved kindness which he gives is greater. Hence it says: “God opposes the haughty ones, but he gives undeserved kindness to the humble ones.”

7 Subject yourselves, therefore, to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from YOU. 8 Draw close to God, and he will draw close to YOU. Cleanse YOUR hands, YOU sinners, and purify YOUR hearts, YOU indecisive ones. 9 Give way to misery and mourn and weep. Let YOUR laughter be turned into mourning, and YOUR joy into dejection. 10 Humble yourselves in the eyes of Jehovah, and he will exalt YOU.

11 Quit speaking against one another, brothers. He who speaks against a brother or judges his brother speaks against law and judges law. Now if you judge law, you are, not a doer of law, but a judge. 12 One there is that is lawgiver and judge, he who is able to save and to destroy. But you, who are you to be judging your neighbor?

13 Come, now, YOU who say: “Today or tomorrow we will journey to this city and will spend a year there, and we will engage in business and make profits,” 14 whereas YOU do not know what YOUR life will be tomorrow. For YOU are a mist appearing for a little while and then disappearing. 15 Instead, YOU ought to say: “If Jehovah wills, we shall live and also do this or that.” 16 But now YOU take pride in YOUR self-assuming brags. All such taking of pride is wicked. 17 Therefore, if one knows how to do what is right and yet does not do it, it is a sin for him.

1 Peter

2 Accordingly, put away all badness and all deceitfulness and hypocrisy and envies and all sorts of backbiting, 2 and, as newborn infants, form a longing for the unadulterated milk belonging to the word, that through it YOU may grow to salvation, 3 provided YOU have tasted that the Lord is kind.

4 Coming to him as to a living stone, rejected, it is true, by men, but chosen, precious, with God, 5 YOU yourselves also as living stones are being built up a spiritual house for the purpose of a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. 6 For it is contained in Scripture: “Look! I am laying in Zion a stone, chosen, a foundation cornerstone, precious; and no one exercising faith in it will by any means come to disappointment.”

7 It is to YOU, therefore, that he is precious, because YOU are believers; but to those not believing, “the identical stone that the builders rejected has become the head of the corner,” 8 and “a stone of stumbling and a rock-mass of offense.” These are stumbling because they are disobedient to the word. To this very end they were also appointed. 9 But YOU are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for special possession, that YOU should declare abroad the excellencies” of the one that called YOU out of darkness into his wonderful light. 10 For YOU were once not a people, but are now God’s people; YOU were those who had not been shown mercy, but are now those who have been shown mercy.

11 Beloved, I exhort YOU as aliens and temporary residents to keep abstaining from fleshly desires, which are the very ones that carry on a conflict against the soul. 12 Maintain YOUR conduct fine among the nations, that, in the thing in which they are speaking against YOU as evildoers, they may as a result of YOUR fine works of which they are eyewitnesses glorify God in the day for his inspection.

13 For the Lord’s sake subject yourselves to every human creation: whether to a king as being superior 14 or to governors as being sent by him to inflict punishment on evildoers but to praise doers of good. 15 For so the will of God is, that by doing good YOU may muzzle the ignorant talk of the unreasonable men. 16 Be as free people, and yet holding YOUR freedom, not as a blind for badness, but as slaves of God. 17 Honor men of all sorts, have love for the whole association of brothers, be in fear of God, have honor for the king.

18 Let house servants be in subjection to their owners with all due fear, not only to the good and reasonable, but also to those hard to please. 19 For if someone, because of conscience toward God, bears up under grievous things and suffers unjustly, this is an agreeable thing. 20 For what merit is there in it if, when YOU are sinning and being slapped, YOU endure it? But if, when YOU are doing good and YOU suffer, YOU endure it, this is a thing agreeable with God.

21 In fact, to this course YOU were called, because even Christ suffered for YOU, leaving YOU a model for YOU to follow his steps closely. 22 He committed no sin, nor was deception found in his mouth. 23 When he was being reviled, he did not go reviling in return. When he was suffering, he did not go threatening, but kept on committing himself to the one who judges righteously. 24 He himself bore our sins in his own body upon the stake, in order that we might be done with sins and live to righteousness. And “by his stripes YOU were healed.” 25 For YOU were like sheep, going astray; but now YOU have returned to the shepherd and overseer of YOUR souls.

Revelation

2 “To the angel of the congregation in Eph′e·sus write: These are the things that he says who holds the seven stars in his right hand, he who walks in the midst of the seven golden lampstands, 2 ‘I know your deeds, and your labor and endurance, and that you cannot bear bad men, and that you put those to the test who say they are apostles, but they are not, and you found them liars. 3 You are also showing endurance, and you have borne up for my name’s sake and have not grown weary. 4 Nevertheless, I hold this against you, that you have left the love you had at first.

5 “‘Therefore remember from what you have fallen, and repent and do the former deeds. If you do not, I am coming to you, and I will remove your lampstand from its place, unless you repent. 6 Still, you do have this, that you hate the deeds of the sect of Nic·o·la′us, which I also hate. 7 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: To him that conquers I will grant to eat of the tree of life, which is in the paradise of God.’

8 “And to the angel of the congregation in Smyr′na write: These are the things that he says, ‘the First and the Last,’ who became dead and came to life again, 9 ‘I know your tribulation and poverty—but you are rich—and the blasphemy by those who say they themselves are Jews, and yet they are not but are a synagogue of Satan. 10 Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of YOU into prison that YOU may be fully put to the test, and that YOU may have tribulation ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life. 11 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: He that conquers will by no means be harmed by the second death.’

12 “And to the angel of the congregation in Per′ga·mum write: These are the things that he says who has the sharp, long two-edged sword, 13 ‘I know where you are dwelling, that is, where the throne of Satan is; and yet you keep on holding fast my name, and you did not deny your faith in me even in the days of An′ti·pas, my witness, the faithful one, who was killed by YOUR side, where Satan is dwelling.

14 “‘Nevertheless, I have a few things against you, that you have there those holding fast the teaching of Ba′laam, who went teaching Ba′lak to put a stumbling block before the sons of Israel, to eat things sacrificed to idols and to commit fornication. 15 So you, also, have those holding fast the teaching of the sect of Nic·o·la′us likewise. 16 Therefore repent. If you do not, I am coming to you quickly, and I will war with them with the long sword of my mouth.

17 “‘Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations: To him that conquers I will give some of the hidden manna, and I will give him a white pebble, and upon the pebble a new name written which no one knows except the one receiving it.’

18 “And to the angel of the congregation in Thy·a·ti′ra write: These are the things that the Son of God says, he who has his eyes like a fiery flame, and his feet are like fine copper, 19 ‘I know your deeds, and your love and faith and ministry and endurance, and that your deeds of late are more than those formerly.

20 “‘Nevertheless, I do hold this against you, that you tolerate that woman Jez′e·bel, who calls herself a prophetess, and she teaches and misleads my slaves to commit fornication and to eat things sacrificed to idols. 21 And I gave her time to repent, but she is not willing to repent of her fornication. 22 Look! I am about to throw her into a sickbed, and those committing adultery with her into great tribulation, unless they repent of her deeds. 23 And her children I will kill with deadly plague, so that all the congregations will know that I am he who searches the kidneys and hearts, and I will give to YOU individually according to YOUR deeds.

24 “‘However, I say to the rest of YOU who are in Thy·a·ti′ra, all those who do not have this teaching, the very ones who did not get to know the “deep things of Satan,” as they say: I am not putting upon YOU any other burden. 25 Just the same, hold fast what YOU have until I come. 26 And to him that conquers and observes my deeds down to the end I will give authority over the nations, 27 and he shall shepherd the people with an iron rod so that they will be broken to pieces like clay vessels, the same as I have received from my Father, 28 and I will give him the morning star. 29 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

Revelation

3 “And to the angel of the congregation in Sar′dis write: These are the things that he says who has the seven spirits of God and the seven stars, ‘I know your deeds, that you have the name that you are alive, but you are dead. 2 Become watchful, and strengthen the things remaining that were ready to die, for I have not found your deeds fully performed before my God. 3 Therefore, continue mindful of how you have received and how you heard, and go on keeping it, and repent. Certainly unless you wake up, I shall come as a thief, and you will not know at all at what hour I shall come upon you.

4 “‘Nevertheless, you do have a few names in Sar′dis that did not defile their outer garments, and they shall walk with me in white ones, because they are worthy. 5 He that conquers will thus be arrayed in white outer garments; and I will by no means blot out his name from the book of life, but I will make acknowledgment of his name before my Father and before his angels. 6 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

7 “And to the angel of the congregation in Philadelphia write: These are the things he says who is holy, who is true, who has the key of David, who opens so that no one will shut, and shuts so that no one opens, 8 ‘I know your deeds—look! I have set before you an opened door, which no one can shut—that you have a little power, and you kept my word and did not prove false to my name. 9 Look! I will give those from the synagogue of Satan who say they are Jews, and yet they are not but are lying—look! I will make them come and do obeisance before your feet and make them know I have loved you. 10 Because you kept the word about my endurance, I will also keep you from the hour of test, which is to come upon the whole inhabited earth, to put a test upon those dwelling on the earth. 11 I am coming quickly. Keep on holding fast what you have, that no one may take your crown.

12 “‘The one that conquers—I will make him a pillar in the temple of my God, and he will by no means go out from it anymore, and I will write upon him the name of my God and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem which descends out of heaven from my God, and that new name of mine. 13 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’

14 “And to the angel of the congregation in La·o·di·ce′a write: These are the things that the Amen says, the faithful and true witness, the beginning of the creation by God, 15 ‘I know your deeds, that you are neither cold nor hot. I wish you were cold or else hot. 16 So, because you are lukewarm and neither hot nor cold, I am going to vomit you out of my mouth. 17 Because you say: “I am rich and have acquired riches and do not need anything at all,” but you do not know you are miserable and pitiable and poor and blind and naked, 18 I advise you to buy from me gold refined by fire that you may become rich, and white outer garments that you may become dressed and that the shame of your nakedness may not become manifested, and eyesalve to rub in your eyes that you may see.

19 “‘All those for whom I have affection I reprove and discipline. Therefore be zealous and repent. 20 Look! I am standing at the door and knocking. If anyone hears my voice and opens the door, I will come into his house and take the evening meal with him and he with me. 21 To the one that conquers I will grant to sit down with me on my throne, even as I conquered and sat down with my Father on his throne. 22 Let the one who has an ear hear what the spirit says to the congregations.’”

Revelation

11 And a reed like a rod was given me as he said: “Get up and measure the temple sanctuary of God and the altar and those worshiping in it. 2 But as for the courtyard that is outside the temple sanctuary, cast it clear out and do not measure it, because it has been given to the nations, and they will trample the holy city underfoot for forty-two months. 3 And I will cause my two witnesses to prophesy a thousand two hundred and sixty days dressed in sackcloth.” 4 These are symbolized by the two olive trees and the two lampstands and are standing before the Lord of the earth.

5 And if anyone wants to harm them, fire issues forth from their mouths and devours their enemies; and if anyone should want to harm them, in this manner he must be killed. 6 These have the authority to shut up heaven that no rain should fall during the days of their prophesying, and they have authority over the waters to turn them into blood and to strike the earth with every sort of plague as often as they wish.

7 And when they have finished their witnessing, the wild beast that ascends out of the abyss will make war with them and conquer them and kill them. 8 And their corpses will be on the broad way of the great city which is in a spiritual sense called Sod′om and Egypt, where their Lord was also impaled. 9 And those of the peoples and tribes and tongues and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, and they do not let their corpses be laid in a tomb. 10 And those dwelling on the earth rejoice over them and enjoy themselves, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those dwelling on the earth.

11 And after the three and a half days spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood upon their feet, and great fear fell upon those beholding them. 12 And they heard a loud voice out of heaven say to them: “Come on up here.” And they went up into heaven in the cloud, and their enemies beheld them. 13 And in that hour a great earthquake occurred, and a tenth of the city fell; and seven thousand persons were killed by the earthquake, and the rest became frightened and gave glory to the God of heaven.

14 The second woe is past. Look! The third woe is coming quickly.

15 And the seventh angel blew his trumpet. And loud voices occurred in heaven, saying: “The kingdom of the world did become the kingdom of our Lord and of his Christ, and he will rule as king forever and ever.”

16 And the twenty-four elders who were seated before God upon their thrones fell upon their faces and worshiped God, 17 saying: “We thank you, Jehovah God, the Almighty, the One who is and who was, because you have taken your great power and begun ruling as king. 18 But the nations became wrathful, and your own wrath came, and the appointed time for the dead to be judged, and to give their reward to your slaves the prophets and to the holy ones and to those fearing your name, the small and the great, and to bring to ruin those ruining the earth.”

19 And the temple sanctuary of God that is in heaven was opened, and the ark of his covenant was seen in his temple sanctuary. And there occurred lightnings and voices and thunders and an earthquake and a great hail.

Revelation

19 After these things I heard what was as a loud voice of a great crowd in heaven. They said: “Praise Jah, YOU people! The salvation and the glory and the power belong to our God, 2 because his judgments are true and righteous. For he has executed judgment upon the great harlot who corrupted the earth with her fornication, and he has avenged the blood of his slaves at her hand.” 3 And right away for the second time they said: “Praise Jah, YOU people! And the smoke from her goes on ascending forever and ever.”

4 And the twenty-four elders and the four living creatures fell down and worshiped God seated upon the throne, and said: “Amen! Praise Jah, YOU people!”

5 Also, a voice issued forth from the throne and said: “Be praising our God, all YOU his slaves, who fear him, the small ones and the great.”

6 And I heard what was as a voice of a great crowd and as a sound of many waters and as a sound of heavy thunders. They said: “Praise Jah, YOU people, because Jehovah our God, the Almighty, has begun to rule as king. 7 Let us rejoice and be overjoyed, and let us give him the glory, because the marriage of the Lamb has arrived and his wife has prepared herself. 8 Yes, it has been granted to her to be arrayed in bright, clean, fine linen, for the fine linen stands for the righteous acts of the holy ones.”

9 And he tells me: “Write: Happy are those invited to the evening meal of the Lamb’s marriage.” Also, he tells me: “These are the true sayings of God.” 10 At that I fell down before his feet to worship him. But he tells me: “Be careful! Do not do that! All I am is a fellow slave of you and of your brothers who have the work of witnessing to Jesus. Worship God; for the bearing witness to Jesus is what inspires prophesying.”

11 And I saw the heaven opened, and, look! a white horse. And the one seated upon it is called Faithful and True, and he judges and carries on war in righteousness. 12 His eyes are a fiery flame, and upon his head are many diadems. He has a name written that no one knows but he himself, 13 and he is arrayed with an outer garment sprinkled with blood, and the name he is called is The Word of God. 14 Also, the armies that were in heaven were following him on white horses, and they were clothed in white, clean, fine linen. 15 And out of his mouth there protrudes a sharp long sword, that he may strike the nations with it, and he will shepherd them with a rod of iron. He treads too the winepress of the anger of the wrath of God the Almighty. 16 And upon his outer garment, even upon his thigh, he has a name written, King of kings and Lord of lords.

17 I saw also an angel standing in the sun, and he cried out with a loud voice and said to all the birds that fly in midheaven: “Come here, be gathered together to the great evening meal of God, 18 that YOU may eat the fleshy parts of kings and the fleshy parts of military commanders and the fleshy parts of strong men and the fleshy parts of horses and of those seated upon them, and the fleshy parts of all, of freemen as well as of slaves and of small ones and great.”

19 And I saw the wild beast and the kings of the earth and their armies gathered together to wage the war with the one seated on the horse and with his army. 20 And the wild beast was caught, and along with it the false prophet that performed in front of it the signs with which he misled those who received the mark of the wild beast and those who render worship to its image. While still alive, they both were hurled into the fiery lake that burns with sulphur. 21 But the rest were killed off with the long sword of the one seated on the horse, which sword proceeded out of his mouth. And all the birds were filled from the fleshy parts of them.